<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Action Dispatcher">

  <topic-statement>
    The action dispatcher routes each decoded input action to the appropriate
    REPL behavior, with state-dependent handling for interruption, scrolling,
    completion, and text editing.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The dispatch table covering all recognized action types, state-dependent
      branching (agent state, viewport offset, active completion), the priority
      ordering for actions with multiple possible targets, and the handling of
      unrecognized actions.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Input parsing">
      How raw terminal input is decoded into semantic action types is handled
      by the input parser and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Viewport">
      The mechanics of scroll offset adjustment and auto-scroll behavior are
      covered by the viewport specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tab completion">
      The mechanics of completion candidate navigation and item commitment are
      covered by the tab completion specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input cursor">
      The mechanics of cursor movement and text insertion within the input buffer
      are covered by the input cursor specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="LLM request">
      How a submitted user message is assembled into an LLM API request is
      covered by the LLM request specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <dispatch-overview order="1">
      On each input event, the dispatcher receives a single action value and
      selects behavior via a switch statement covering all recognized action
      types. Actions that are not recognized are silently ignored with no state
      change.
    </dispatch-overview>

    <enter-action order="2">
      When the Enter action is received, the current input buffer text is
      submitted as a user message and an LLM request is initiated, provided
      the input buffer is non-empty and the agent is in the idle state.

      <notable reason="submit clears the buffer">
        The input buffer is cleared and the viewport is scrolled to the bottom
        as part of the submission.
      </notable>
    </enter-action>

    <escape-action order="3">
      The Escape action is state-dependent:

      - If the agent is waiting for an LLM response or executing a tool, the
        in-flight operation is interrupted.
      - If a completion menu is active, the completion is dismissed.
      - Otherwise, Escape has no effect.
    </escape-action>

    <ctrl-c-action order="4">
      The Ctrl+C action unconditionally sets the quit flag, which causes the
      application to exit on the next event loop iteration. If the agent is
      waiting for an LLM response or executing a tool, the in-flight operation
      is also interrupted before the quit flag is set.
    </ctrl-c-action>

    <vertical-arrow-actions order="5">
      The up and down arrow actions are dispatched to one of three targets in
      priority order:

      1. **Viewport scroll**: if the viewport is scrolled up (offset is non-zero
         for up-arrow, or the viewport is not at the bottom for down-arrow), the
         scroll offset is adjusted by one row.
      2. **Completion navigation**: if a completion menu is active and the
         viewport is at the bottom, the selected completion item is moved up or
         down.
      3. **Cursor history**: if no completion is active and the viewport is at
         the bottom, the input buffer is replaced with the previous or next
         entry from command history.

      <notable reason="scroll takes priority over completion navigation">
        If the user has scrolled the viewport upward, up and down arrows scroll
        the viewport rather than navigating completion candidates, even if a
        completion menu is visible.
      </notable>
    </vertical-arrow-actions>

    <horizontal-arrow-actions order="6">
      The left and right arrow actions always move the cursor in the input
      buffer. If a completion menu is active, it is dismissed before the cursor
      moves.
    </horizontal-arrow-actions>

    <space-action order="7">
      If a completion menu is active, the Space action commits the currently
      selected completion candidate into the input buffer and dismisses the menu.
      If no completion is active, Space inserts a space character at the cursor
      position.
    </space-action>

    <tab-action order="8">
      The Tab action opens or advances the completion menu. If no menu is active,
      a new completion session is started for the current input. If a menu is
      already active, the next candidate is selected.
    </tab-action>

    <ctrl-n-ctrl-p-actions order="9">
      The Ctrl+N and Ctrl+P actions are explicit no-ops. They are recognized by
      the dispatcher but produce no state change.

      <notable reason="Ctrl+N and Ctrl+P are disabled">
        These key bindings are reserved but intentionally inactive. They do not
        navigate history or perform any other action.
      </notable>
    </ctrl-n-ctrl-p-actions>

    <page-scroll-actions order="10">
      Page Up and Page Down scroll the viewport by one full screen height.
      Home and End scroll the viewport to the top and bottom of the scrollback
      respectively.
    </page-scroll-actions>

    <text-editing-actions order="11">
      The remaining recognized actions operate directly on the input buffer:

      - **Backspace**: deletes the character before the cursor.
      - **Delete**: deletes the character at the cursor.
      - **Ctrl+U**: clears the entire input buffer.
      - **Ctrl+W**: deletes the word before the cursor.
      - **Ctrl+A / Home (line)**: moves the cursor to the start of the input.
      - **Ctrl+E / End (line)**: moves the cursor to the end of the input.
      - **Character**: inserts the decoded Unicode codepoint at the cursor.

      For all text-editing actions, if a completion menu is active it is
      dismissed before the edit is applied, except for character insertion which
      may trigger a completion refresh.
    </text-editing-actions>

    <auto-scroll-on-input order="12">
      Any action that modifies the input buffer or submits a message resets the
      viewport scroll offset to zero (bottom of scrollback), ensuring the user
      always sees the most recent content while typing.
    </auto-scroll-on-input>

  </behavior>

</specification>
