<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="ANSI Escape Sequence Parsing">

  <topic-statement>
    The ANSI parsing module detects and measures CSI escape sequences embedded
    in terminal text so that display-width calculations and rendering can skip
    over non-printing control sequences.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      CSI sequence structure and recognition, the skip operation that returns
      a sequence's byte length, color output enablement based on environment
      variables, and 256-color foreground sequence generation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Display width calculation">
      How the widths of individual Unicode codepoints are determined (using
      utf8proc for East Asian wide characters and emoji) is handled by the
      scrollback layout subsystem and is out of scope here. The ANSI module
      provides only the CSI skip step.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Other escape sequence families">
      OSC sequences (ESC + ']'), DCS sequences, and other escape sequence
      types are not recognized by this module. Only CSI sequences (ESC + '[')
      are handled.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <csi-sequence-structure order="1">
      A CSI sequence has the following byte structure:

      1. **Introducer**: ESC (0x1B) followed by '[' (0x5B)
      2. **Parameter bytes** (zero or more): bytes in the range 0x30–0x3F
         (digits, semicolons, colons, and related punctuation)
      3. **Intermediate bytes** (zero or more): bytes in the range 0x20–0x2F
         (space through slash)
      4. **Terminal byte** (exactly one): a byte in the range 0x40–0x7E
         (letters and symbols)

      Any byte outside its expected range causes the sequence to be considered
      invalid.
    </csi-sequence-structure>

    <skip-operation order="2">
      Given a text buffer and a byte position, the skip operation determines
      whether a CSI sequence begins at that position and, if so, returns the
      total byte length of the sequence (including the two-byte introducer and
      the terminal byte). If the position does not begin a valid CSI sequence,
      zero is returned.

      If the buffer ends before the terminal byte is encountered (an incomplete
      sequence), zero is returned. This makes the operation safe to call on
      partial streaming data.

      The operation does not modify the buffer; it only reads.
    </skip-operation>

    <typical-usage order="3">
      Callers that need to compute the display width of a text string iterate
      byte-by-byte through the text. At each position, the skip operation is
      called first. If it returns a non-zero length, the caller advances past
      the entire sequence without counting any display columns for it. If it
      returns zero, the caller decodes the UTF-8 codepoint at that position
      and adds its display width to the running total.

      This pattern allows ANSI color and formatting codes to be embedded in
      stored text without inflating computed display widths or physical line
      counts.
    </typical-usage>

    <color-enablement order="4">
      Color output is enabled by default but disabled when either the
      `NO_COLOR` environment variable is set (regardless of its value) or the
      `TERM` environment variable is set to the value `dumb`. This check is
      performed once at startup and stored as a global flag consulted by all
      color-emitting code.
    </color-enablement>

    <color-sequence-generation order="5">
      Given a 256-color palette index (0–255), the module generates the
      corresponding ANSI SGR foreground color sequence into a caller-supplied
      buffer. The sequence follows the format `\x1b[38;5;<n>m`. If the supplied
      buffer is too small to hold the sequence, zero is written and the
      operation is a no-op rather than truncating.
    </color-sequence-generation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
