<specification topic="Basic REPL Commands">

  <topic-statement>
    The basic REPL commands provide conversation reset, command listing, and
    application exit as core built-in operations available in every agent session.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The /clear, /help, and /exit commands: their argument handling, the sequence
      of side effects each produces, and their error conditions.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Event Rendering">
      How system prompt events are formatted and appended to the scrollback is
      covered by the event rendering specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Logger">
      Log file rotation mechanics are covered by the debug log file specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Command Dispatch">
      How slash commands are parsed, matched by name, and routed to handlers is
      covered by the command dispatch specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <clear-command order="1">
      The `/clear` command resets the active agent's conversation state to the
      same condition it would be in at the start of a fresh session.

      <log-rotation order="1">
        The debug log file is rotated: the current log is closed and a new log
        file is opened in the current working directory. If the current working
        directory cannot be determined, the command returns an IO error without
        performing any further steps.
      </log-rotation>

      <memory-erasure order="2">
        The following in-memory state is discarded in order:
        - The scrollback display buffer is cleared of all visible lines.
        - All messages in the agent's conversation array are freed and the
          count is reset to zero.
        - The token cache, if present, is reset (all turn counts cleared).
        - All conversation marks are freed and the mark count is reset to zero.
        - Any active autocomplete state is cleared.
      </memory-erasure>

      <database-boundary order="3">
        If a database connection and session identifier are present:
        - A boundary record of kind "clear" with no content is inserted into
          the messages table.
        - The agent's effective system prompt is resolved and, if obtained, a
          record of kind "system" containing that prompt is inserted.
        Database failures at either step are logged as warnings and do not
        prevent the command from succeeding; in-memory state is authoritative.
      </database-boundary>

      <scrollback-rebuild order="4">
        The agent's effective system prompt is resolved again. If obtained, it
        is rendered as a system event into the now-empty scrollback. A failure
        to render to the scrollback is the only error condition that causes the
        clear command to return an error.
      </scrollback-rebuild>

      <notable reason="system-prompt-resolved-independently-for-db-and-display">
        The effective system prompt is resolved once for database persistence
        and a second time for scrollback rendering. The two calls are
        independent; each reads from the pinned document list, filesystem, and
        configuration in turn.
      </notable>
    </clear-command>

    <help-command order="2">
      The `/help` command lists all registered slash commands in alphabetical
      order. Any arguments provided are ignored.

      A header line "Available commands:" is appended to the scrollback. The
      command registry is then retrieved and the entries are sorted alphabetically
      by name using a stable index-based sort. For each entry in sorted order,
      a line formatted as "  /<name> - <description>" is appended to the
      scrollback. Errors from any scrollback append operation are returned
      immediately.
    </help-command>

    <exit-command order="3">
      The `/exit` command signals the event loop to terminate and cancels all
      active LLM requests. Any arguments provided are ignored.

      All agents in the REPL's agent array have their provider instances
      invalidated, aborting any in-flight HTTP connections. A quit flag on the
      REPL context is then set. The event loop checks this flag at the top of
      each iteration and exits when it is set. The exit command always returns
      success immediately; the process does not terminate until the event loop
      exits naturally.
    </exit-command>

  </behavior>

</specification>
