<specification topic="Byte Array">

  <topic-statement>
    The byte array is a typed dynamic array of uint8_t values that delegates
    all storage and capacity management to the generic array implementation.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The typed API surface: creation, append, insert, delete, clear, element
      access, and size query.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Generic Array">
      Capacity growth, memory allocation, bounds checking, and element shifting
      are all handled by the generic array implementation. The byte array
      provides only type-specific wrapping.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Creation Parameters">
      <field name="increment" type="positive integer"
             note="initial allocation size in elements; must be greater than zero" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      A new byte array is created with an element size of one byte and the
      caller-supplied increment. The initial data buffer is not allocated until
      the first element is added (lazy allocation). If increment is zero, an
      error is returned.
    </creation>

    <append order="2">
      A single byte is appended after the last existing element. If the current
      capacity is exhausted, the buffer is reallocated at double the current
      capacity. Returns a success or failure result.
    </append>

    <insert order="3">
      A single byte is inserted at a given index, shifting all elements at and
      after that index one position to the right. The index may equal the
      current size (equivalent to append). Returns a success or failure result.
    </insert>

    <delete order="4">
      The element at a given index is removed by shifting all elements after it
      one position to the left and decrementing the size. The index must be
      less than the current size; violation aborts the process.
    </delete>

    <clear order="5">
      The size is reset to zero without deallocating or zeroing the underlying
      buffer. Capacity is preserved.
    </clear>

    <element-access order="6">
      The byte value at a given index is returned. The index must be less than
      the current size; violation aborts the process.
    </element-access>

    <size-query order="7">
      Returns the number of elements currently stored. This is a read-only
      query with no side effects.
    </size-query>

    <notable reason="lazy-allocation">
      The internal buffer is not allocated at creation time. The first append
      or insert triggers the initial allocation at the increment size, after
      which capacity doubles on each exhaustion.
    </notable>

  </behavior>

</specification>
