<specification topic="Clear Command">

  <topic-statement>
    The clear command resets the current agent's conversation state by wiping
    all in-memory data, recording a clear boundary in the database, and
    rendering the current system prompt as the first entry of the fresh session.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      In-memory state erasure (messages, scrollback, token cache, marks,
      completion state), log rotation, database persistence of the clear event
      and system prompt, fallback behavior on database failure, and scrollback
      rendering of the new session start.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="System Prompt Resolution">
      How the effective system prompt is assembled from pinned documents,
      configuration files, and configuration defaults is handled by the agent
      subsystem. This topic requests the resolved prompt and uses it but does
      not assemble it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Scrollback Rendering">
      How the system prompt text is converted to scrollback display entries is
      handled by the event rendering subsystem.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Token Cache">
      How the token cache tracks and prunes token budgets is handled by the
      token cache subsystem. This topic only resets it.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <log-rotation order="1">
      The current log file is closed and a new log file is opened, using the
      current working directory as the log location. This rotation creates a
      permanent record boundary at each conversation reset.
    </log-rotation>

    <in-memory-erasure order="2">
      All conversation state for the current agent is erased from memory:

      1. The scrollback display buffer is cleared of all entries.
      2. The conversation message array is freed and reset to empty.
      3. If a token cache is present, it is reset: cached turn counts are
         cleared and the turn array is emptied.
      4. If any conversation marks exist, each is freed individually and the
         marks array is freed. The mark count is reset to zero.
      5. If autocomplete state is present, it is freed and set to absent.

      These operations happen before any database work. If a subsequent database
      operation fails, the in-memory state remains cleared. Memory is authoritative.
    </in-memory-erasure>

    <database-persistence order="3">
      If a database connection and a valid session identifier are available, two
      database records are written.

      <clear-event order="1">
        A message of kind "clear" is inserted into the current agent's conversation
        history with no content and no metadata. This event becomes the boundary
        marker used during future session restoration to identify where the
        previous context ends and the fresh session begins.

        If the insert fails, a warning is logged and execution continues. The
        clear command does not fail due to this error.
      </clear-event>

      <system-prompt-event order="2">
        The current effective system prompt is resolved. If a non-null prompt is
        obtained, a message of kind "system" is inserted into the conversation
        history with the prompt text as content and an empty JSON object as
        metadata.

        If the insert fails, a warning is logged and execution continues. The
        clear command does not fail due to this error.

        <notable reason="system prompt is fetched twice">
          The effective system prompt is resolved once for database insertion and
          a second time immediately afterward for scrollback rendering. Both
          resolutions use the same prompt assembly process.
        </notable>
      </system-prompt-event>
    </database-persistence>

    <scrollback-rendering order="4">
      The effective system prompt is resolved again. If a non-null prompt is
      obtained, it is rendered to the now-empty scrollback as a system event,
      giving the user a visual indication of the current session context.

      If the scrollback render fails, the clear command returns the error. This
      is the only failure mode that terminates the clear command with an error.
    </scrollback-rendering>

    <no-database-path order="5">
      If no database connection or session identifier is available, the database
      persistence steps are skipped entirely. In-memory erasure and scrollback
      rendering still occur.

      <notable reason="clearing always succeeds even without a database">
        The absence of database connectivity does not prevent the user from
        clearing the conversation. The in-memory state is wiped regardless.
      </notable>
    </no-database-path>

  </behavior>

</specification>
