<specification topic="Command History">

  <topic-statement>
    The command history system maintains an ordered, deduplicated list of submitted
    entries and supports sequential backward/forward navigation through them.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      In-memory storage of submitted command strings, capacity enforcement, deduplication
      and promotion rules, navigation cursor management, and pending input preservation
      during browsing.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Persistent Storage">
      The history system is a pure in-memory structure. It does not read from or write
      to any persistent store. External code may populate an instance by submitting
      entries in sequence, and may read entries back for persistence by querying the
      current state.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input System">
      The history system receives raw command strings for storage and returns stored
      strings during navigation. It does not interpret, validate, or transform the
      content of those strings in any way.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="History Instance">
      <field name="capacity" type="positive integer" note="fixed at creation, never changes" />
      <field name="entry count" type="non-negative integer" note="0 to capacity inclusive" />
      <field name="pending input" type="text" nullable="true" note="saved user input; absent until browsing begins, or after browsing is stopped or an entry is submitted" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="Entry">
      <field name="text" type="non-empty text" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <initialization order="1">
      A history instance is created with a fixed maximum capacity. The entry list starts
      empty. The instance starts in the not-browsing state with no pending input saved.
    </initialization>

    <submitting-an-entry order="2">
      A text string is submitted for storage. The submission proceeds through a fixed
      decision sequence.

      <empty-entry-rejection order="1">
        If the submitted string is empty, it is silently discarded. No state is changed.
      </empty-entry-rejection>

      <duplicate-of-most-recent order="2">
        If the submitted string is identical to the most recently stored entry, the string
        is not added to the list. The navigation cursor resets to the not-browsing position
        and any saved pending input is discarded.

        <notable reason="state mutation without addition">
          Submitting a duplicate of the most recent entry modifies browsing state and
          discards pending input even though nothing is added to the list. A caller
          mid-browse will silently lose their position and saved pending input.
        </notable>
      </duplicate-of-most-recent>

      <existing-entry-promotion order="3">
        If the submitted string matches any stored entry other than the most recent one,
        that existing entry is removed from its current position. All entries that were
        after it shift one position toward the beginning to close the gap. The submitted
        string is then appended as the new most recent entry. The count remains unchanged
        net (one removed, one added).
      </existing-entry-promotion>

      <capacity-enforcement order="4">
        If the submitted string does not exist anywhere in the list and the list has
        reached its capacity, the oldest entry (the one at the beginning of the list) is
        removed. All remaining entries shift one position toward the beginning. The
        submitted string is then appended as the new most recent entry. The count remains
        unchanged net (one removed, one added).
      </capacity-enforcement>

      <normal-addition order="5">
        If the submitted string does not exist anywhere in the list and the list is below
        capacity, the string is appended as the new most recent entry. The count
        increases by one.
      </normal-addition>

      <browsing-reset order="6">
        After any path that modifies the list (existing-entry-promotion,
        capacity-enforcement, or normal-addition), the navigation cursor is reset to the
        not-browsing position and any saved pending input is discarded.
      </browsing-reset>

    </submitting-an-entry>

    <navigating-history order="3">
      Navigation moves a cursor through the stored entries. The cursor exists in one of
      three distinct positions:

      - The browsing position: pointing at one of the stored entries. Browsing status
        is true only in this position.
      - The end position: one step past the last stored entry. Browsing status is false.
        This is the starting position of a newly created instance and the position
        returned to after stopping browsing or submitting an entry.
      - The past-end position: one step beyond the end position. Browsing status is
        false. Reached only by navigating forward from the end position.

      <starting-browsing order="1">
        Browsing is initiated by providing the current pending input string. Any
        previously saved pending input is discarded and replaced with the provided value.

        If the entry list is empty, the pending input is saved but the cursor remains at
        the end position. The browsing status stays false.

        If the entry list is not empty, the pending input is saved and the cursor moves
        to the most recent entry (the last position in the browsing range). Browsing
        status becomes true.

        Initiating browsing when the cursor is already in the browsing position or the
        past-end position discards any previously saved pending input, saves the newly
        provided value, and unconditionally resets the cursor to the most recent entry.

        <notable reason="empty-history non-transition">
          When the entry list is empty, initiating browsing saves the pending input but
          does not change the browsing status to true. The instance is technically not
          browsing even though pending input has been preserved. This is indistinguishable
          from a case where pending input was saved by a previous browsing session that
          was not explicitly stopped.
        </notable>
      </starting-browsing>

      <navigating-backward order="2">
        A backward navigation step moves the cursor one position toward the oldest entry
        and returns the entry now pointed to.

        If the cursor is at the oldest entry (the beginning of the list), nothing is
        returned and the cursor does not move.

        If the cursor is at the end position or the past-end position (not browsing),
        nothing is returned and the cursor does not move.
      </navigating-backward>

      <navigating-forward order="3">
        A forward navigation step behaves differently depending on the current cursor
        position.

        If the cursor is in the browsing position and not at the most recent entry: the
        cursor advances one position toward the most recent entry and returns the entry
        now pointed to.

        If the cursor is in the browsing position at the most recent entry: the cursor
        advances to the end position and returns the saved pending input. The browsing
        status becomes false.

        If the cursor is at the end position: the cursor advances to the past-end
        position and nothing is returned.

        If the cursor is at the past-end position: nothing is returned and the cursor
        does not move.

        <notable reason="end-position consumes a navigation step">
          Navigating forward from the end position advances to the past-end position
          without returning anything. Since both positions report the same not-browsing
          status and both return the same pending input via get-current, the distinction
          is invisible except through its effect on subsequent navigation. A caller that
          navigates forward once from the end position and then tries to navigate backward
          will receive nothing, because backward navigation checks browsing status rather
          than cursor position.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="past-end is a navigation dead end">
          From the past-end position, both forward and backward navigation return nothing
          and do not move the cursor. The only exits from the past-end position are:
          initiating browsing again (which resets to the most recent entry) or submitting
          an entry (which resets to the end position and discards pending input). The
          saved pending input remains accessible via get-current while in the past-end
          position.
        </notable>
      </navigating-forward>

      <stopping-browsing order="4">
        Browsing is explicitly stopped by resetting the cursor to the end position and
        discarding the saved pending input. After stopping, the browsing status is false
        and get-current returns nothing.
      </stopping-browsing>

      <getting-current-entry order="5">
        The entry at the current cursor position is readable without moving the cursor.

        If the cursor is in the browsing position, the entry at that position is returned.

        If the cursor is at the end position or past-end position, the saved pending
        input is returned. If no pending input has been saved, or if it was discarded by
        stopping browsing or submitting an entry, nothing is returned.
      </getting-current-entry>

      <checking-browsing-status order="6">
        The browsing status is true only when the cursor is in the browsing position
        (pointing at a stored entry). It is false when the cursor is at the end position
        or the past-end position.
      </checking-browsing-status>

    </navigating-history>

  </behavior>

</specification>
