<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Command Dispatch">

  <topic-statement>
    The command dispatcher routes slash-prefixed input lines to registered command
    handlers by exact name match and persists successful command output to the
    database.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Command recognition, routing, argument extraction, the complete command
      registry, echo and output formatting, database persistence of command output,
      and error handling for unknown commands.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tab completion">
      Partial command name completion is performed by the tab completion subsystem
      before the user submits the input. The dispatcher only sees complete, submitted
      input and performs no prefix matching.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Individual command behavior">
      What each command does — how it modifies agent state, what it outputs — is
      outside the scope of this specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Command handler">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="exact command name without the leading slash" />
      <field name="handler" type="function reference" note="signature: (allocator context, REPL context, args string or null) → result" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <command-registry order="1">
      The registry contains exactly 18 commands in a fixed ordered list:

      | Name | Purpose |
      |------|---------|
      | `clear` | Clear scrollback, session messages, and marks |
      | `mark` | Create a rollback checkpoint, optionally named |
      | `rewind` | Roll back to a checkpoint, optionally by name |
      | `fork` | Create a child agent |
      | `kill` | Terminate an agent |
      | `send` | Send a message to another agent |
      | `wait` | Block until messages arrive from other agents |
      | `reap` | Remove dead agents |
      | `agents` | Display the agent process tree |
      | `help` | List available commands |
      | `model` | Change the active LLM model and thinking level |
      | `system` | Set or display the system prompt |
      | `tool` | List tools or show a tool's schema |
      | `refresh` | Reload the tool registry from disk |
      | `pin` | Manage pinned document paths |
      | `unpin` | Remove a pinned document path |
      | `toolset` | Restrict which tools are visible to the LLM |
      | `exit` | Quit the application |

      The list is static and never modified at runtime.
    </command-registry>

    <input-parsing order="2">
      Input is recognized as a command when it begins with a forward slash (`/`).
      The dispatcher:

      1. Strips the leading `/`.
      2. Skips any leading whitespace.
      3. Extracts the command name: all characters up to the first whitespace or
         end of string.
      4. Skips whitespace between the command name and the arguments.
      5. Treats the remainder as the arguments string. If no text remains, the
         arguments are absent (null, not an empty string).

      An input of `/` alone (no command name) is rejected with an error.
    </input-parsing>

    <routing order="3">
      The command name is compared against each registry entry using a case-sensitive
      exact string match. The list is scanned from the first entry to the last.
      The first match is used.

      If no entry matches, a warning is appended to the scrollback: `Unknown command
      'name'`, and an invalid-argument error is returned. The input is not persisted
      to the database on an unknown command.
    </routing>

    <echo-and-output order="4">
      Before invoking the handler, the original input line (including the leading
      `/`) is echoed to the scrollback in a dark-gray color, followed by a blank
      line.

      After the handler returns successfully, if the handler appended at least one
      line to the scrollback, an additional blank line is appended. Handlers that
      produce no output do not receive a trailing blank line.

      The echo always appears; it is not conditional on handler success or output.
    </echo-and-output>

    <database-persistence order="5">
      After a handler returns successfully, the command is persisted to the database
      as a `command` event. The persisted record contains:

      - The full original input line as the echo field.
      - Any lines the handler appended to the scrollback during execution as the
        output content.
      - The command name and arguments in a structured data field.

      Failed commands (handlers that return an error) are not persisted.

      If the database write itself fails, the error is logged but the failure is
      not returned to the caller; the command is considered to have completed
      successfully from the user's perspective.
    </database-persistence>

    <handler-contract order="6">
      Each handler receives:
      - A talloc allocator context for temporary allocations.
      - The REPL context for accessing agent state, scrollback, and the database.
      - The arguments string (null if no arguments were supplied).

      Handlers return a result indicating success or failure. Failures are displayed
      to the user by appending a warning to the scrollback before the handler returns,
      not by the dispatcher after the fact.
    </handler-contract>

  </behavior>

</specification>
