<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Configuration Loading">

  <topic-statement>
    The configuration loader assembles application settings from compiled-in
    defaults, an optional system prompt file, and environment variable overrides,
    producing a single configuration record used at startup.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The configuration data contract, the three-tier source priority order,
      default values for all fields, the system prompt file loading and
      validation rules, environment variable override rules with field-specific
      validation, and silent-rejection behavior for invalid overrides.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Configuration consumption">
      How configuration values are used by agents, providers, and the database
      connection is handled by those subsystems and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Credential loading">
      API key retrieval from the keychain or environment is handled by the
      credential loading subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Configuration">
      <field name="AI model" type="text" default="gpt-5-mini" note="identifier for the default language model" />
      <field name="AI temperature" type="floating-point" default="1.0" note="sampling temperature for LLM responses" />
      <field name="AI max completion tokens" type="integer" default="4096" note="maximum tokens in an LLM response" />
      <field name="AI system message" type="text" default="You are a personal agent and are operating inside the Ikigai orchestration platform." note="default system prompt when no file or pinned documents are set" />
      <field name="network address" type="text" default="127.0.0.1" note="address on which the control socket server listens" />
      <field name="network port" type="16-bit unsigned integer" default="1984" note="port on which the control socket server listens" />
      <field name="database host" type="text" default="localhost" note="PostgreSQL server hostname" />
      <field name="database port" type="32-bit signed integer" default="5432" note="PostgreSQL server port" />
      <field name="database name" type="text" default="ikigai" note="PostgreSQL database name" />
      <field name="database user" type="text" default="ikigai" note="PostgreSQL role name" />
      <field name="max tool turns" type="32-bit signed integer" default="50" note="maximum tool call iterations in a single agent conversation" />
      <field name="max output size" type="64-bit signed integer" default="1048576" note="maximum byte length of tool output captured from a child process" />
      <field name="history size" type="32-bit signed integer" default="10000" note="number of command history entries retained" />
      <field name="default provider" type="text" default="openai" note="identifier for the default LLM provider" />
      <field name="sliding context tokens" type="32-bit signed integer" default="100000" note="token budget for the sliding context window" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <loading-sequence order="1">
      Configuration loading proceeds in four steps executed once at startup:

      1. A zeroed configuration record is allocated.
      2. All fields are set to their compiled-in default values.
      3. A system prompt file is checked and, if valid, its content replaces
         the default system message.
      4. Environment variables are checked and, if valid, their values replace
         the corresponding fields.

      The result is a fully populated configuration record where every field
      is set.
    </loading-sequence>

    <system-prompt-file order="2">
      Before defaults are applied, the loader checks for a system prompt file
      at a fixed path within the application data directory. If the file exists
      and passes validation, its content is used as the system message, taking
      priority over the compiled-in default.

      Validation rules for the system prompt file:

      - The file must exist and be readable.
      - The file must not be empty (zero bytes).
      - The file must not exceed 1,024 bytes.
      - The read must complete successfully (no partial reads).

      If any validation step fails, the file is silently ignored and the
      compiled-in default system message is used.

      <notable reason="file is checked before defaults but replaces after">
        The file content is read before defaults are applied, but the
        replacement takes place as part of the defaults step, making file
        content the effective default for the system message field.
      </notable>
    </system-prompt-file>

    <environment-variable-overrides order="3">
      After defaults are applied, environment variables may override six fields.
      Each variable is checked independently; failure of one does not affect
      the others.

      **String fields** (database host, database name, database user, default
      provider): the environment variable value must be a non-empty string.
      Empty strings are treated as absent and the default is retained.
      Valid values replace the current field value.

      **Integer fields** (database port, sliding context token budget): the
      environment variable value is parsed as a decimal integer. Two additional
      constraints apply:
      - The database port must be in the range 1–65535.
      - The token budget must be a positive (non-zero) integer.

      If parsing fails or the constraint is not met, the override is silently
      ignored and the default is retained.

      **Default provider**: checked via a dedicated lookup that queries the
      environment variable and falls back to the configured value if absent.
    </environment-variable-overrides>

    <silent-rejection order="4">
      Overrides that fail validation are never reported to the user. The
      application continues with the default or previously set value. This
      applies to:
      - Empty string environment variables
      - Unparseable numeric environment variables
      - Numeric values outside the valid range

      <notable reason="no warnings are emitted for invalid overrides">
        A misconfigured environment variable (for example, a non-numeric value
        for database port) is silently ignored. Users who expect an override
        to take effect will see the default behavior with no indication of why.
      </notable>
    </silent-rejection>

    <allocation-failure order="5">
      Memory allocation failures during configuration loading cause an immediate
      process abort. There is no partial-configuration recovery path.
    </allocation-failure>

  </behavior>

</specification>
