<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Control Socket">

  <topic-statement>
    The control socket system accepts JSON commands from external clients over
    a Unix domain socket and dispatches responses, including deferred responses
    for the wait_idle command.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Server initialization, connection lifecycle, message dispatch, all four
      command handlers, the deferred wait_idle mechanism, and connection teardown.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Framebuffer serialization">
      The read_framebuffer command delegates serialization of the rendered
      terminal state to a separate subsystem. This specification records what
      is passed to that subsystem and what is returned — the serialization
      logic itself is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Token cache">
      The read_token_cache command reads from the token accounting subsystem.
      This specification records what values are read and how they are
      assembled — the token cache internals are out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Key injection">
      The send_keys command appends decoded bytes to a key injection buffer.
      This specification records when and how that append occurs — the
      downstream processing of injected keys is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent state machine">
      The wait_idle command observes the agent's current state. This
      specification records what value is observed — the state machine
      transitions are out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Request">
      <field name="type" type="text" note="command name; determines dispatch" />
      <field name="keys" type="text" required="false" note="send_keys only; the key sequence to inject" />
      <field name="timeout_ms" type="integer" required="false" note="wait_idle only; milliseconds before timeout response" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Response">
      <field name="type" type="text" required="false" note="present on success responses; value is command-specific" />
      <field name="error" type="text" required="false" note="present on error responses; human-readable description" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Token cache response">
      <field name="total_tokens" type="integer" />
      <field name="budget" type="integer" />
      <field name="turn_count" type="integer" />
      <field name="context_start_index" type="integer" />
      <field name="turns" type="array of objects" note="each object has index (integer) and tokens (integer)" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Server state">
      <field name="listening file descriptor" type="integer" />
      <field name="client file descriptor" type="integer" note="negative one when no client is connected" />
      <field name="socket path" type="text" />
      <field name="wait idle pending" type="boolean" note="true when a wait_idle response has been deferred" />
      <field name="wait idle deadline" type="integer" note="monotonic clock milliseconds at which a deferred wait_idle times out" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <server-initialization order="1">
      The server is initialized with a runtime directory path and produces a
      running socket server.

      <runtime-directory order="1">
        The runtime directory is created if it does not exist, with permissions
        granting access only to the owner (mode 0700). If the directory already
        exists, no error is produced. If creation fails, initialization fails
        and no socket is created.
      </runtime-directory>

      <socket-creation order="2">
        A Unix domain stream socket is created. The socket path is constructed
        by combining the runtime directory with the current process identifier
        in the form `ikigai-<pid>.sock`.

        If the path would exceed the platform's maximum socket path length (108
        bytes on Linux), initialization fails.

        Any file already at the socket path is removed before binding. The
        socket is bound to that path and begins listening with a backlog of one
        pending connection.
      </socket-creation>

      <initialization-failure order="3">
        If initialization fails at any step, any socket file descriptor created
        during the attempt is closed. The caller receives an error. The runtime
        treats the control socket as unavailable and continues operating without
        it.
      </initialization-failure>
    </server-initialization>

    <event-loop-integration order="2">
      The server integrates with the application's main I/O multiplexing loop.
      On each iteration, the server contributes its file descriptors to the
      set of descriptors to monitor.

      <listen-socket-monitoring order="1">
        The listening socket is included in the monitored set unless a
        wait_idle response is currently deferred. When a deferred wait_idle
        is pending, the listening socket is excluded, preventing new
        connections from being accepted until the deferred response is sent.

        <notable reason="new connections blocked during deferred wait_idle">
          A client connected and waiting for a wait_idle response holds
          exclusive access to the server until that response fires. The
          backlog of one means at most one additional connection attempt
          will queue; any further attempts are refused by the operating
          system.
        </notable>
      </listen-socket-monitoring>

      <client-socket-monitoring order="2">
        When a client is connected, its file descriptor is always included in
        the monitored set, regardless of deferred state.
      </client-socket-monitoring>

      <processing-order order="3">
        On each loop iteration, processing occurs in this order: first, the
        deferred wait_idle tick runs; then, a pending new connection is
        accepted if the listening socket is ready; then, a pending client
        request is handled if the client socket is ready.
      </processing-order>
    </event-loop-integration>

    <connection-lifecycle order="3">
      <accepting-connections order="1">
        When the listening socket becomes ready, a connection is accepted. If
        a client is already connected when a new connection arrives, the
        existing client's file descriptor is closed without notification before
        the new connection is accepted.

        <notable reason="silent client eviction">
          Clients have no protection against eviction. A new incoming connection
          will silently terminate any currently connected client, including one
          waiting for a deferred wait_idle response.
        </notable>
      </accepting-connections>

      <request-handling order="2">
        When the connected client's socket becomes ready, up to 4095 bytes are
        read. If the read returns zero bytes (EOF) or a negative value (error),
        the client is disconnected: its file descriptor is closed, the client
        file descriptor is set to negative one, and any pending wait_idle state
        is reset.

        If bytes are read successfully, the data is null-terminated. A newline
        character, if present, is replaced with a null terminator, discarding
        everything from the newline onward.

        <notable reason="partial messages are processed">
          If a request arrives without a trailing newline, it is processed as
          received. There is no waiting for a complete message before dispatch.
        </notable>
      </request-handling>

      <sending-responses order="3">
        Responses are sent using the MSG_NOSIGNAL flag to prevent SIGPIPE
        signals on broken pipe connections.

        If the send fails or is partial, the client file descriptor is closed
        immediately, any pending wait_idle state is reset, and the failure is
        not reported to the caller.

        After a response is sent successfully (for all commands except the
        deferred case), the client connection is closed.

        <notable reason="connection always closed after response">
          The protocol is strictly one-request, one-response, one-close.
          Clients must reconnect to send another request.
        </notable>
      </sending-responses>
    </connection-lifecycle>

    <message-dispatch order="4">
      The received bytes are parsed as JSON. If parsing fails, an error
      response is sent immediately: `{"error":"Invalid JSON"}`.

      The `type` field of the parsed JSON object determines the command. The
      following type values are recognized: `read_framebuffer`,
      `read_token_cache`, `send_keys`, and `wait_idle`. Any other value, or
      the absence of the `type` field, produces an error response:
      `{"error":"Unknown message type"}`.
    </message-dispatch>

    <commands order="5">

      <read-framebuffer order="1">
        The current terminal framebuffer is serialized and returned.

        If no framebuffer is available, the response is:
        `{"error":"No framebuffer available"}`.

        Otherwise, the framebuffer bytes, terminal dimensions (rows and
        columns), cursor position (row and column), and input buffer
        visibility flag are passed to the framebuffer serialization subsystem.
        The serialized result is returned as the response.

        If serialization fails, the response is:
        `{"error":"Serialization failed"}`.
      </read-framebuffer>

      <read-token-cache order="2">
        The current agent's token accounting data is read and returned as a
        JSON object.

        If no agent is active or no token cache is available, the response is:
        `{"total_tokens":0,"budget":100000,"turn_count":0,"context_start_index":0,"turns":[]}`.

        Otherwise, the total token count, budget, turn count, and context
        start turn index are read from the cache. A JSON array is constructed
        containing one object per turn, each with an `index` field (the
        context start index plus the turn's zero-based position) and a
        `tokens` field. The response assembles all of these into a JSON object.

        <notable reason="response is unbounded in size">
          The turns array grows with the number of turns. No limit is imposed
          on the size of the response.
        </notable>
      </read-token-cache>

      <send-keys order="3">
        A sequence of key characters is injected into the application's input.

        The `keys` field is extracted from the request. If absent, the response
        is `{"error":"Missing keys field"}`.

        The keys string is unescaped to produce a raw byte sequence. If
        unescaping fails, the response is `{"error":"Failed to unescape keys"}`.

        On success, the response `{"type":"ok"}` is sent and the connection is
        closed. The unescaped byte sequence is then appended to the key
        injection buffer for processing on the next event loop iteration.

        <notable reason="keys arrive after response">
          The client receives the success response and the connection is closed
          before the keys are submitted to the input pipeline. The effect of the
          keys is not visible until a subsequent event loop iteration.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="no escaping in C client library">
          When the C client library constructs the send_keys JSON request, it
          embeds the keys string directly into the JSON without any escaping.
          A keys string containing double-quote characters, backslashes, or
          newlines will produce malformed JSON, which the server will reject
          with an invalid JSON error.
        </notable>
      </send-keys>

      <wait-idle order="4">
        The command waits until the current agent enters the idle state, up to
        a specified timeout.

        <already-pending order="1">
          If a wait_idle response is already deferred from a previous request,
          the response is `{"error":"wait_idle already pending"}` and the
          command is not processed further.
        </already-pending>

        <timeout-validation order="2">
          The `timeout_ms` field is extracted. If absent or not a positive
          integer, the response is `{"error":"Missing or invalid timeout_ms"}`.
        </timeout-validation>

        <immediate-idle order="3">
          If the agent's current state is idle at the moment the request is
          processed, the response is `{"type":"idle"}` and the connection is
          closed normally.
        </immediate-idle>

        <deferred-response order="4">
          If the agent is not idle, the response is deferred. The current
          monotonic clock time is read and the deadline is set to that time
          plus the requested timeout in milliseconds. The wait_idle pending
          flag is set. No response is sent and the connection is kept open.

          On each subsequent event loop iteration, the deferred tick checks
          two conditions:

          First, if the agent's state is now idle, the response
          `{"type":"idle"}` is sent and the connection is closed.

          Second, if the monotonic clock time has reached or passed the
          deadline, the response `{"type":"timeout"}` is sent and the
          connection is closed.

          In both cases, the wait_idle pending flag is cleared.

          <notable reason="timeout is a soft deadline">
            The timeout is checked once per event loop iteration, not on a
            dedicated timer. The actual elapsed time before a timeout response
            is sent may exceed the requested timeout by up to one full event
            loop cycle.
          </notable>

          <notable reason="failed send clears deferred state">
            If the deferred response send fails (e.g., because the client
            disconnected), the connection is closed and the wait_idle pending
            flag is cleared silently. No error is surfaced.
          </notable>
        </deferred-response>
      </wait-idle>

    </commands>

    <server-shutdown order="6">
      During shutdown, the client connection (if any) is closed, the listening
      socket is closed, and the socket file is removed from the filesystem.
    </server-shutdown>

  </behavior>

</specification>
