<specification topic="Control Socket Client">

  <topic-statement>
    The control socket client sends JSON command requests over a Unix domain
    socket connection and reads JSON responses, providing programmatic access
    to the running ikigai process.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Connection establishment, request serialization, response buffering for
      three command types, and connection teardown.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Socket Path">
      The caller supplies the socket path explicitly. The client does not
      discover the path from the environment, from a file, or from the process
      tree.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Control Socket Server">
      Command dispatch, response generation, and the server-side command
      handlers are covered by the control socket server specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Request">
      <field name="type" type="string" note="command name; one of read_framebuffer, send_keys, read_token_cache" />
      <field name="keys" type="string" required="false" note="send_keys only; key string injected directly without JSON escaping" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Response">
      <field name="content" type="JSON string" note="server response, newline-terminated; structure is command-specific" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <connection order="1">
      A Unix domain stream socket is created and connected to the provided
      path. If the socket path exceeds the operating system's maximum allowed
      length, the socket is closed and an error is returned. If the connection
      attempt fails, the socket is closed and an error is returned.

      The returned file descriptor is the sole identifier for the connection.
      All subsequent operations require the caller to pass this descriptor.
    </connection>

    <protocol order="2">
      Communication uses line-delimited JSON. Each request is a JSON object
      serialized as a single line ending with a newline character. Each response
      is a JSON object serialized as a single line ending with a newline character.
      There are no length-prefix headers.

      The client sends one request and then reads one response before the
      exchange is complete. There is no multiplexing and no validation that
      responses correspond to specific requests.
    </protocol>

    <read-framebuffer-command order="3">
      A request of type "read_framebuffer" is serialized and sent. The response
      is read into a 65536-byte buffer using a read loop. Each read operation's
      result is checked for a newline byte; when a newline is found in the most
      recently received chunk, the loop exits. The loop also exits when the
      buffer is full. The buffered response string is returned to the caller.
    </read-framebuffer-command>

    <send-keys-command order="4">
      A request of type "send_keys" is constructed by inserting the key string
      directly into a JSON template. The key string is not JSON-escaped; if it
      contains characters that are special in JSON (quotation marks, backslashes,
      newlines), the resulting JSON is malformed.

      After sending, a single read of up to 4096 bytes is performed on a
      stack-allocated buffer. The response is not returned to the caller. Instead,
      the response buffer is scanned for the substring "error"; if found, an
      error is returned. Otherwise, success is returned.

      <notable reason="no JSON escaping on key string">
        The key string is embedded verbatim into the JSON request. Callers are
        responsible for ensuring that the key string is valid within a JSON
        string context, or for accepting undefined behavior on malformed output.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="single non-looping read">
        Unlike the other commands, send_keys reads the response with a single
        system call rather than a loop. If the server sends a response longer
        than 4096 bytes, the remainder is left in the socket buffer and will
        corrupt subsequent reads.
      </notable>
    </send-keys-command>

    <read-token-cache-command order="5">
      A request of type "read_token_cache" is serialized and sent. The response
      is read into a 4096-byte buffer using the same loop strategy as
      read_framebuffer: reading until a newline is detected in the last chunk
      or the buffer is full. The buffered response string is returned to the
      caller.
    </read-token-cache-command>

    <disconnection order="6">
      The socket connection is closed by passing the file descriptor to the
      disconnect operation. Calling disconnect with a negative file descriptor
      is a no-op.
    </disconnection>

    <error-behavior order="7">
      Connection failures, send failures, and receive failures all produce IO
      errors. Partial writes are not detected; if the operating system sends
      fewer bytes than requested, the protocol is silently violated and the
      server will receive a malformed request. End-of-file on a receive loop
      causes the loop to exit with whatever bytes were received, returning that
      partial content as the response without error.

      <notable reason="no partial-write detection">
        Write system calls are not checked for partial completion. On a busy
        or slow system, a write may deliver fewer bytes than the full request,
        leaving the server to parse an incomplete JSON line.
      </notable>
    </error-behavior>

  </behavior>

</specification>
