<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Credential Loading">

  <topic-statement>
    The credential loader reads API keys and secrets from a JSON configuration
    file and from environment variables, applying environment variables as
    overrides over file-based values.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Configuration file discovery and path resolution, JSON parsing and field
      extraction, environment variable override, credential retrieval by name,
      and all error handling along each path.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Providers">
      Credential values are passed to provider and tool implementations that
      consume them. Whether a credential value is valid for its intended service
      is determined at connection time by those implementations, not here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Credentials">
      <field name="openai api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: OPENAI_API_KEY" />
      <field name="anthropic api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: ANTHROPIC_API_KEY" />
      <field name="google api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: GOOGLE_API_KEY" />
      <field name="brave api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: BRAVE_API_KEY" />
      <field name="google search api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: GOOGLE_SEARCH_API_KEY" />
      <field name="google search engine id" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: GOOGLE_SEARCH_ENGINE_ID" />
      <field name="ntfy api key" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: NTFY_API_KEY" />
      <field name="ntfy topic" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: NTFY_TOPIC" />
      <field name="database password" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="env var: IKIGAI_DB_PASS" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <configuration-file-discovery order="1">
      When no explicit file path is provided, the path is derived from the
      environment. If the `IKIGAI_CONFIG_DIR` environment variable is set, the
      configuration file is sought at `<IKIGAI_CONFIG_DIR>/credentials.json`.
      Otherwise, the default path is `~/.config/ikigai/credentials.json`.

      A path beginning with `~` is expanded by replacing the tilde with the
      value of the `HOME` environment variable. If `HOME` is not set and the
      path begins with `~`, loading fails and an error is returned. Paths
      not beginning with `~` are used as-is.

      When an explicit file path is provided by the caller, that path is used
      directly, subject to the same tilde expansion rule.
    </configuration-file-discovery>

    <file-loading order="2">
      If the resolved file path does not exist (as determined by a filesystem
      stat), loading continues without error and all credential fields from
      the file remain unset. A missing file is not an error.

      If the file exists, it is parsed as JSON. If parsing fails, the failure
      is silently discarded and loading continues as though the file were empty.
      All credential fields from the file remain unset in this case.

      If parsing succeeds but the JSON root is not an object (e.g., it is an
      array, a string, a number, or null), the file contents are discarded
      silently and all file-sourced fields remain unset.

      If the JSON root is an object, each of the nine recognized field names
      is looked up. For each field, if the JSON value is a non-empty string,
      the credential is set to that string value. If the JSON value is absent,
      is not a string type, or is an empty string, the credential field remains
      unset. No other JSON types (numbers, arrays, booleans, null) are accepted
      as credential values.

      <notable reason="parse errors are silently ignored">
        A corrupted or invalid credentials file produces no error visible to the
        caller. Credentials that would have come from the file are simply absent,
        while environment variable overrides (applied in the next step) still
        take effect.
      </notable>
    </file-loading>

    <environment-variable-override order="3">
      After the file is processed, each of the nine credentials is independently
      checked against its corresponding environment variable. If the environment
      variable is set and its value is a non-empty string, that value replaces
      whatever was loaded from the file for that credential. If the environment
      variable is unset or set to an empty string, the file-sourced value (if
      any) is preserved unchanged.

      The nine environment variable names and their corresponding credentials are:
      `OPENAI_API_KEY`, `ANTHROPIC_API_KEY`, `GOOGLE_API_KEY`, `BRAVE_API_KEY`,
      `GOOGLE_SEARCH_API_KEY`, `GOOGLE_SEARCH_ENGINE_ID`, `NTFY_API_KEY`,
      `NTFY_TOPIC`, and `IKIGAI_DB_PASS`.

      <notable reason="empty environment variables are treated as absent">
        Setting `OPENAI_API_KEY` to an empty string does not clear or override
        a file-sourced value. Only a non-empty environment variable value
        constitutes an override.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="overrides are applied independently per credential">
        Environment variables override individual credentials, not all of them.
        A mix of file-sourced and environment-sourced credentials is the normal
        result when only some environment variables are set.
      </notable>
    </environment-variable-override>

    <credential-retrieval order="4">
      An individual credential is retrieved by supplying its environment
      variable name as a key. The returned value is the credential string if
      set, or null if the credential is absent. If the supplied name does not
      match any of the nine recognized names, null is returned.

      No validation of the credential value's format or content is performed
      at retrieval time.
    </credential-retrieval>

    <no-format-validation order="5">
      Credential values are stored and returned exactly as read from their
      source — no format checking, length validation, or structural verification
      is applied. A credential value of any non-empty string is accepted. Whether
      the value is a valid key for the intended external service is determined
      by that service when the credential is used.
    </no-format-validation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
