<specification topic="Database Connection">

  <topic-statement>
    The database connection system establishes and manages a PostgreSQL connection,
    applies schema migrations on initialization, and suppresses all server notices
    for the lifetime of the connection.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Connection string validation, connection establishment, notice processor
      installation, automatic schema migration, transaction control, and
      connection teardown via memory-managed lifecycle.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Schema Migration">
      How SQL migration scripts are discovered and applied is handled by the
      database migration subsystem. This topic invokes migration but does not
      implement it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="PostgreSQL">
      Actual TCP/socket connection management, authentication, and protocol
      handling are delegated entirely to the libpq client library.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Connection Context">
      <field name="connection" type="opaque handle" note="the established PostgreSQL connection; null before initialization or after teardown" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <initialization order="1">
      Two initialization paths are available. The standard path accepts a data
      directory and constructs the migrations directory path automatically as
      a subdirectory named "migrations" within it. The test path accepts an
      explicit migrations directory, bypassing the construction step. Both
      paths converge on the same connection and migration logic.

      <connection-string-validation order="1">
        The connection string must be non-empty and must begin with one of the
        recognized prefixes: "postgresql://", "postgres://", or a key-value
        format recognized by the PostgreSQL library. If the string is empty or
        does not match a recognized format, an error is returned immediately
        without attempting a connection.
      </connection-string-validation>

      <connection-establishment order="2">
        The connection string is passed verbatim to the PostgreSQL client
        library. No parameter manipulation, DNS pre-resolution, or connection
        string transformation is performed. If the library reports the connection
        as not successfully established, the library's own error message is
        returned as the error detail.

        <notable reason="no retry or reconnection">
          Connection establishment is a single attempt. There is no retry loop,
          exponential backoff, or automatic reconnection after failures or
          disconnects.
        </notable>
      </connection-establishment>

      <notice-suppression order="3">
        Immediately after connection, a notice processor is installed that
        silently discards all server notices, warnings, and informational
        messages. No notice is logged, counted, or passed to any observer.

        <notable reason="suppression is total and irreversible">
          All PostgreSQL notice output is suppressed for the duration of the
          connection. There is no mechanism to re-enable notices or to selectively
          suppress by severity or message content. This prevents server notices
          from appearing on standard error, which would corrupt the terminal
          display in alternate screen buffer mode.
        </notable>
      </notice-suppression>

      <schema-migration order="4">
        After a successful connection, schema migrations are applied
        automatically. If migration fails, the connection context is released
        and the migration error is returned to the caller. There is no option
        to skip migration during initialization.

        <shared topic="Database Schema Migration">
          Pending migration scripts are discovered in the migrations directory,
          sorted by their numeric prefix, and applied in order against the
          established connection. Only scripts with numbers greater than the
          current schema version are applied.
        </shared>
      </schema-migration>
    </initialization>

    <transaction-control order="2">
      Three explicit transaction operations are supported:

      - Begin: starts a new transaction.
      - Commit: commits the current transaction.
      - Rollback: rolls back the current transaction.

      Each operation executes the corresponding SQL statement and returns a
      result indicating success or failure. No implicit transaction management
      is performed; callers are responsible for balancing begin, commit, and
      rollback.
    </transaction-control>

    <connection-teardown order="3">
      The connection context is tied to the memory hierarchy of the allocating
      component. When the owning memory context is released, a registered
      cleanup function automatically closes the PostgreSQL connection and
      nulls the internal handle. No explicit teardown call is required.

      If the connection handle is already null at teardown time (for example,
      if initialization failed partway through), the cleanup function is a
      no-op.
    </connection-teardown>

  </behavior>

</specification>
