<specification topic="Database Schema Migration">

  <topic-statement>
    The database schema migration system applies SQL scripts in version order to
    bring the schema to the current version.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Version detection, migration file discovery and parsing, ordered execution
      of pending migration SQL scripts, and error reporting.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="PostgreSQL">
      This topic submits SQL strings to the database connection and receives
      status codes and error messages in return. The database enforces
      transactional semantics within each migration file; this topic does not
      control transaction boundaries.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="File System">
      This topic reads the contents of migration files identified by scanning a
      directory. File access errors are translated into domain-specific error
      messages and returned to the caller.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database Connection">
      This topic receives an established PostgreSQL connection. Opening,
      configuring, or closing the connection is outside this scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Migration Input">
      <field name="database connection" type="opaque handle" note="established PostgreSQL connection" />
      <field name="migrations directory path" type="string" note="path to directory containing .sql files" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Migration File">
      <field name="migration number" type="integer" note="extracted from filename prefix; 3 or 4 decimal digits" />
      <field name="file path" type="string" note="absolute path to the .sql file" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Result">
      <field name="outcome" type="result" note="OK on full success; ERR with IO code on file system failure; ERR with DB_MIGRATE code on SQL execution failure" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <detecting-current-version order="1">
      Before examining any migration files, the system queries the schema
      metadata table for the current schema version. The query retrieves at most
      one row.

      <fresh-database order="1">
        If the schema metadata table does not yet exist, the query fails with a
        database error. This condition is treated as version zero — the same as
        a fresh, empty database. No error is reported.
      </fresh-database>

      <version-present order="2">
        If the table exists and contains at least one row, the version value from
        the first returned row is parsed as a decimal integer. If the value
        parses cleanly (no trailing non-digit characters, non-negative, within
        integer range), it is used as the current version.
      </version-present>

      <version-invalid order="3">
        If the stored version value fails to parse as a valid non-negative
        integer, the current version is treated as zero. No error is reported.

        <notable reason="silent fallback">
          A corrupted or out-of-range version value silently causes all
          migrations to be re-applied from the beginning, which may fail if the
          schema already partially exists.
        </notable>
      </version-invalid>
    </detecting-current-version>

    <discovering-migration-files order="2">
      The migrations directory is opened for reading. If the directory cannot be
      opened, an IO error is returned immediately with no migrations applied.

      <filename-parsing order="1">
        Each directory entry is examined. An entry is accepted as a migration
        file only when its name satisfies all of the following conditions:

        - The name is at least 9 characters long.
        - The name ends with the exact suffix ".sql".
        - The name begins with exactly 3 or 4 consecutive decimal digit
          characters.
        - The character immediately following the digit prefix is a hyphen "-".
        - The digit prefix parses as a non-negative integer within the range of
          a signed integer.

        The standard directory pseudo-entries "." and ".." are skipped without
        parsing.

        <notable reason="silent discard">
          Any entry that fails any of these conditions is silently skipped. No
          warning or error is produced. A file named "002_wrong-separator.sql"
          (underscore instead of hyphen) or "002-missing-extension.txt" is
          discarded without notice.
        </notable>
      </filename-parsing>

      <sorting order="2">
        All accepted entries are sorted in ascending order by their numeric
        migration number before any SQL is executed.
      </sorting>
    </discovering-migration-files>

    <applying-pending-migrations order="3">
      Each accepted migration entry is examined in sorted order. A migration is
      applied only when its number is strictly greater than the current version.
      Migrations whose number is less than or equal to the current version are
      skipped without reading their files.

      <reading-the-file order="1">
        The SQL file is read into memory in full. If the file cannot be opened,
        its size cannot be determined, or its contents cannot be read, an IO
        error is returned immediately. The specific error message varies by
        failure mode:

        - Cannot open: "Cannot open migration file"
        - Cannot seek within the file: "Cannot seek migration file"
        - Cannot determine file size: "Cannot get migration file size"
        - File exceeds the maximum readable size: "Migration file too large"
        - Any other read failure: "Failed to read migration file"
      </reading-the-file>

      <executing-the-sql order="2">
        The full file contents are submitted to the database as a single
        statement string. The database executes them in one call.

        <notable reason="transaction responsibility">
          Each migration file is responsible for its own transaction boundaries.
          The migration system does not wrap the file contents in BEGIN or
          COMMIT. If a migration file omits transaction control, partial changes
          may be committed if the file fails partway through execution.
        </notable>
      </executing-the-sql>

      <checking-the-result order="3">
        After execution, the status of the database response is inspected. The
        execution is considered successful only when the status indicates either
        a successful command or a result set. Any other status causes an
        immediate DB_MIGRATE error return carrying the database's own error
        message and the migration number that failed. Subsequent migrations are
        not attempted.

        <notable reason="partial application">
          When a migration fails, all previously applied migrations in the same
          run remain committed. There is no rollback of successfully completed
          migrations. The database is left in a partially-migrated state
          requiring manual recovery.
        </notable>
      </checking-the-result>

      <version-update order="4">
        The migration system itself does not update the schema metadata table
        after each migration. Version advancement is expected to be part of
        the SQL in the migration file. If a migration file omits the version
        update, the current version remains unchanged after that migration
        executes, and subsequent runs re-apply the same migration.

        <notable reason="version tracking delegation">
          Incorrect or missing version update statements within migration files
          can cause migrations to be executed repeatedly on subsequent runs.
        </notable>
      </version-update>
    </applying-pending-migrations>

    <successful-completion order="4">
      When all pending migrations have been applied without error, the system
      returns success. All temporary working memory is released.
    </successful-completion>

  </behavior>

</specification>
