<specification topic="db-message-insertion">
  <topic-statement>The database message insertion system validates message kinds and persists conversation messages to a database session.</topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>Kind string validation against the set of recognized message kinds</in-scope>
    <in-scope>Parameterized insertion of a message record into a database session</in-scope>
    <in-scope>In-memory construction of a tool result message record</in-scope>
    <boundary name="message-retrieval">Reading or querying previously inserted messages is not covered here.</boundary>
    <boundary name="session-lifecycle">Creating or managing database sessions is out of scope.</boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="message-record">
      <field name="id" type="integer" notes="0 when not yet persisted; assigned by database on insert" />
      <field name="kind" type="string" notes="one of the 13 recognized kind strings" />
      <field name="content" type="string|null" notes="free-form text content; nullable" />
      <field name="data_json" type="string|null" notes="JSON-encoded auxiliary data; nullable" />
      <field name="agent_uuid" type="string" notes="UUID of the owning agent" />
      <field name="session_id" type="integer" notes="positive integer identifying the database session" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="tool-result-data-json">
      <field name="tool_call_id" type="string" notes="ID of the tool call being responded to" />
      <field name="name" type="string" notes="name of the tool that was invoked" />
      <field name="output" type="string" notes="raw output text from the tool" />
      <field name="success" type="boolean" notes="extracted from the tool_success field of the output JSON; defaults to false if parsing fails" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>
    <kind-validation order="1">
      Exactly 13 kind strings are recognized: "clear", "system", "user", "assistant",
      "tool_call", "tool_result", "mark", "rewind", "agent_killed", "command", "fork",
      "usage", and "interrupted". Validation is an exact, case-sensitive string match
      against each member of this set. Any string not in the set causes validation to
      return false; any exact match returns true.
    </kind-validation>

    <insertion-preconditions order="2">
      Before inserting a message, the system asserts that the database handle and its
      underlying connection are both non-null, and that the session identifier is a
      positive integer greater than zero. Violations of these preconditions abort the
      process immediately rather than returning an error.
    </insertion-preconditions>

    <insertion-execution order="3">
      A temporary memory context is created for the duration of the insertion. A
      parameterized INSERT statement is built with five positional parameters: session
      identifier (rendered as a decimal string), agent UUID, message kind, content
      (which may be null), and auxiliary JSON data (which may be null). The statement
      requests the database to return the assigned message ID. The result is wrapped
      so that it is automatically released when the temporary context is freed.
    </insertion-execution>

    <insertion-success order="4">
      When the database reports a successful command result, the operation returns
      success with no additional value. The temporary memory context and all
      allocations within it are released.
    </insertion-success>

    <insertion-failure order="5">
      When the database reports any result other than a successful command, an error
      message is produced. The temporary memory context is released after the
      operation, so the error message must survive that release.

      <notable reason="error-allocation-context">
        The error message is allocated on the database context rather than on the
        temporary context. Allocating it on the temporary context would cause it to
        be freed before the caller could read it, producing a dangling pointer. By
        attaching it to the longer-lived database context, the error string remains
        valid after the temporary context is destroyed.
      </notable>
    </insertion-failure>

    <tool-result-construction order="6">
      A tool result message record is constructed in memory without being persisted.
      The record carries an ID of zero to signal that it has not yet been assigned a
      database identity. Its kind is fixed as "tool_result". The content field holds
      the provided output text verbatim. The auxiliary JSON data encodes four fields:
      the tool call identifier being responded to, the tool name, the raw output text,
      and a success boolean. The success flag is extracted by parsing the output text
      as JSON and reading the "tool_success" field; if that parse fails or the field
      is absent, success defaults to false.
    </tool-result-construction>
  </behavior>
</specification>
