<specification topic="Database Session Management">

  <topic-statement>
    The database session management module creates new session records and
    retrieves the most recently started active session from the sessions table.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Session record insertion with database-generated ID retrieval, and
      active session lookup with tiebreaking.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Database Connection">
      The underlying PostgreSQL connection and query execution are managed
      externally. This topic only specifies the SQL operations and result
      handling.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Session Startup">
      When sessions are created and how they are used during application
      startup is covered by the session startup specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Session Record">
      <field name="id" type="integer" note="database-generated serial identifier" />
      <field name="started_at" type="timestamp" note="set to the current time by the database on insert" />
      <field name="ended_at" type="timestamp or null" note="null for active sessions; set when the session ends" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <session-creation order="1">
      Inserts a new row into the sessions table using default column values,
      causing the database to populate the started_at timestamp with the
      current time and ended_at with null. The generated session ID is
      retrieved in the same query using a RETURNING clause.

      The returned ID string is parsed as a decimal 64-bit signed integer.
      If the query returns no rows, the process aborts (this would indicate
      an internal database invariant violation). The session ID is returned
      to the caller.
    </session-creation>

    <active-session-lookup order="2">
      Queries for the most recently started session whose ended_at column is
      null. Results are ordered by started_at descending, with the session ID
      used as a secondary sort key to break ties among sessions created in the
      same database transaction.

      If no rows are returned, the output session ID is set to zero and
      success is returned. A session ID of zero is the sentinel indicating
      that no active session was found.

      If the query returns multiple rows, only the first row (the most recent)
      is used. The remaining rows are ignored without error.

      <notable reason="zero-as-sentinel">
        The caller must distinguish session ID zero (no active session) from a
        valid session ID. Zero is never a valid database-generated session ID.
      </notable>
    </active-session-lookup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
