<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Debug Log File">

  <topic-statement>
    The debug log file system provides compile-time-conditional printf-style
    diagnostic logging to a rotating plain-text file.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Compile-time gating of all logging behavior, log directory creation,
      rotation of any pre-existing log file on startup, log file creation,
      per-call write format, immediate flushing, and atexit cleanup.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Structured JSONL Logger">
      The application's persistent structured logger records events in JSONL
      format to a different file path and is always active regardless of build
      mode. This topic is entirely separate from that logger.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Panic Handler">
      If any initialization step fails (missing environment variable, failed
      directory creation, failed file open), the panic handler is invoked and
      the process terminates. The panic handler's behavior is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Log Entry">
      <field name="timestamp" type="text" note="local time formatted as YYYY-MM-DD HH:MM:SS" />
      <field name="source file" type="text" note="the source file path as provided by the compiler" />
      <field name="line number" type="integer" note="the source line number" />
      <field name="function name" type="text" note="the enclosing function name as provided by the compiler" />
      <field name="message" type="text" note="caller-supplied printf-style formatted text" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Archive File Name">
      <field name="timestamp portion" type="text" note="birth time (or mtime fallback) of the previous log file, formatted as YYYY-MM-DDTHH-MM-SSZ±HH-MM using local timezone offset" />
      <field name="suffix" type="text" note="always '.log'" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <compile-time-gating order="1">
      All logging behavior — initialization, the write call, and the public
      macro — is present only in DEBUG builds. In non-DEBUG builds, both the
      initialization call and every log-write call compile to no-ops that
      produce no code and have no side effects. There is no runtime flag or
      environment variable that enables or disables the feature; the build
      configuration is the sole switch.

      <notable reason="entire file excluded from coverage">
        The source file is wrapped in LCOV coverage exclusion directives,
        so coverage tooling does not measure any of its lines.
      </notable>
    </compile-time-gating>

    <initialization order="2">
      Initialization must be called once early in the process lifecycle before
      any log writes are attempted.

      <directory-resolution order="1">
        The log directory path is read from an environment variable. If the
        variable is unset or empty, the process panics immediately.

        If the path does not yet exist as a directory, it is created recursively
        with mode 0755. Any intermediate directories that do not exist are also
        created. Creation proceeds segment by segment; if a segment already
        exists, that is not treated as an error. If creation fails for any other
        reason, the process panics.
      </directory-resolution>

      <rotation order="2">
        If a file named "debug.log" already exists in the log directory, it is
        archived before the new log is opened:

        1. The birth time of the existing file is queried using the statx system
           call with the STATX_BTIME flag. If the kernel does not support birth
           time or does not report it for this file, the file's modification time
           is used as a fallback.

        2. The birth time is converted to local time and formatted as a timestamp
           string with the local timezone offset, using hyphens as separators
           within the time portion to produce a filesystem-safe name of the form
           YYYY-MM-DDTHH-MM-SS±HH-MM.

        3. An archive path is constructed by appending ".log" to the timestamp
           string within the log directory.

        4. If no file at the archive path already exists, the existing "debug.log"
           is renamed to the archive path. If the archive path already exists,
           the rename is skipped and "debug.log" is left in place to be
           overwritten.

        <notable reason="overwrite on archive collision">
          If the archive file already exists — which can happen if two processes
          start within the same second — the existing log is overwritten by the
          new session rather than being preserved or merged. The collision check
          uses a second stat call; there is a TOCTOU race between that check and
          the rename.
        </notable>
      </rotation>

      <file-creation order="3">
        A new "debug.log" file is opened for writing in the log directory,
        truncating any file that was not renamed during the rotation step.
        If the open fails, the process panics.

        A cleanup function is registered with atexit to flush and close the
        file when the process exits normally.

        A header line reading "=== IKIGAI DEBUG LOG ===" is written to the
        new file and flushed immediately.
      </file-creation>
    </initialization>

    <log-write order="3">
      Each log write emits one line to the file. The public interface is a
      macro that automatically supplies the source file path, line number,
      and function name at the call site; the caller supplies only the
      format string and any arguments.

      The write sequence is:
      1. If the log file is not open (not yet initialized, or already closed
         by the atexit handler), the write is silently discarded.
      2. The current local time is obtained and formatted as YYYY-MM-DD HH:MM:SS.
      3. A context prefix is written: "[TIMESTAMP] FILE:LINE:FUNCTION: "
      4. The caller's formatted message is appended using printf-style formatting.
      5. A newline character is appended.
      6. The file is flushed immediately so the file can be tailed in real time.

      <notable reason="no write buffering">
        Every log call flushes the underlying file stream. This enables
        real-time observation via tail -f but imposes a flush cost on every
        log statement.
      </notable>
    </log-write>

    <cleanup order="4">
      The atexit handler flushes and closes the log file, then sets the
      internal file pointer to null. If the file pointer is already null
      when the handler runs, it does nothing.

      <notable reason="atexit handler does not unregister itself">
        The atexit handler is registered once at initialization. It cannot
        be unregistered. If initialization is called more than once (which
        is not a supported usage), multiple handlers would be registered
        and would each attempt to flush and close whatever the file pointer
        points to at exit time.
      </notable>
    </cleanup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
