<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Document Cache">

  <topic-statement>
    The document cache stores the contents of files referenced by internal URIs
    in memory, eliminating repeated filesystem reads when the same document is
    requested multiple times.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Cache entry structure, on-demand loading from the filesystem, URI-to-path
      translation before lookup, cache miss handling, single-entry invalidation,
      bulk clear, and error handling when a file cannot be loaded.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="URI translation">
      How internal URIs are resolved to canonical filesystem paths is handled
      by the paths subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="System prompt assembly">
      How cached document contents are concatenated to form the system prompt
      is handled by the LLM request assembly subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Cache entry">
      <field name="canonical path" type="text" note="absolute filesystem path after URI translation; used as the lookup key" />
      <field name="content" type="text" note="raw file bytes as a null-terminated string; owned by the cache" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Cache">
      <field name="entries" type="dynamic array of cache entry" note="starts with capacity 4; doubles on overflow" />
      <field name="entry count" type="non-negative integer" note="number of entries currently stored" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <lookup order="1">
      A document is retrieved by supplying its internal URI. The URI is first
      translated to a canonical filesystem path. If translation fails, an error
      is returned immediately and the cache is not consulted.

      The cache entries are scanned linearly for an entry whose canonical path
      matches. On a hit, the stored content pointer is returned. The pointer is
      owned by the cache and must not be freed by the caller; it remains valid
      until the entry is invalidated or the cache is cleared.
    </lookup>

    <cache-miss-loading order="2">
      On a cache miss, the file is read from the filesystem at the canonical
      path. If the read succeeds, a new entry is added to the cache with the
      canonical path and the file content, and the content is returned. If the
      array is at capacity, it is doubled before the entry is added.

      If the file cannot be read (for example, because it does not exist or is
      not accessible), an error is returned and no entry is added to the cache.

      <notable reason="content is owned by the cache">
        The file content is allocated within the cache's memory context. Callers
        receive a borrowed pointer and must not attempt to free it.
      </notable>
    </cache-miss-loading>

    <invalidation order="3">
      A single cache entry can be invalidated by supplying its internal URI.
      The URI is translated to a canonical path, and the matching entry (if
      any) is removed. Remaining entries are shifted to fill the gap.

      If URI translation fails or no matching entry is found, the operation
      returns without modifying the cache.

      Bulk invalidation (clear) frees all entries, resets the count to zero,
      and leaves the capacity and array allocation intact for reuse.
    </invalidation>

    <use-by-pinned-documents order="4">
      The primary consumer is the system prompt assembly process. When building
      an effective system prompt from pinned documents, each pinned document URI
      is looked up in the cache in order. If a document fails to load, it is
      silently skipped and the next pinned document is processed.

      Bulk cache clears occur when the tool registry is refreshed (via the
      `/refresh` command), ensuring that document contents are re-read from disk
      if files have changed since they were last cached.
    </use-by-pinned-documents>

    <per-agent-isolation order="5">
      Each agent owns a separate document cache instance. There is no shared
      cache across agents. An agent's cache is freed when the agent is destroyed.
    </per-agent-isolation>

    <allocation-failure order="6">
      Memory allocation failures during cache growth or content storage cause
      an immediate process abort.
    </allocation-failure>

  </behavior>

</specification>
