<specification topic="Event Render Formatting">

  <topic-statement>
    The event render formatting system transforms stored tool call and tool result
    records into display-ready strings.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Formatting tool call records and tool result records for display, including
      prefix detection, JSON extraction, fallback to raw content, and null output handling.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Call Formatting">
      This topic submits a tool call structure (id, name, arguments) and receives
      a formatted, truncated display string. The format and truncation rules are
      defined by the tool call formatting system.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool Result Formatting">
      This topic submits a tool name and output string and receives a formatted,
      truncated display string. The format and truncation rules are defined by the
      tool result formatting system.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Format Buffer">
      This topic creates a format buffer, appends text to it, and retrieves the
      resulting string. Truncation is applied during append.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Tool Call Data JSON">
      <field name="tool_call_id" type="string" note="required; if absent or not a string, falls back to raw content" />
      <field name="tool_name" type="string" note="required; if absent or not a string, falls back to raw content" />
      <field name="tool_args" type="string" note="required; if absent or not a string, falls back to raw content" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool Result Data JSON">
      <field name="name" type="string" note="required; if absent or not a string, falls back to raw formatter" />
      <field name="output" type="string" required="false" nullable="true" note="if absent or not a string, null is passed to result formatter" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <format-tool-call order="1">
      A stored tool call content string and its associated data JSON string are
      submitted for display formatting.

      <prefix-check order="1">
        If the content string is non-null and begins with the tool request prefix,
        the content string is returned as-is without further processing.
      </prefix-check>

      <null-data-fallback order="2">
        If the data JSON string is null, the content string is returned as-is.
      </null-data-fallback>

      <json-parse order="3">
        The data JSON string is parsed. If parsing fails, the content string is
        returned as-is.
      </json-parse>

      <field-extraction order="4">
        The parsed object is checked for string fields named "tool_call_id",
        "tool_name", and "tool_args". If any of these fields is absent or is not
        a string value, the JSON document is released and the content string is
        returned as-is.
      </field-extraction>

      <formatting order="5">
        The three string values are copied into the allocation context. A tool call
        structure is assembled from the copied strings and submitted to the tool call
        formatting system. The formatted, truncated result is returned. The JSON
        document is released before returning.
      </formatting>
    </format-tool-call>

    <format-tool-result order="2">
      A stored tool result content string and its associated data JSON string are
      submitted for display formatting.

      <prefix-check order="1">
        If the content string is non-null and begins with the tool response prefix,
        the content string is returned as-is without further processing.
      </prefix-check>

      <null-data-fallback order="2">
        If the data JSON string is null, the raw tool result formatter is applied
        to the content string and its output is returned.
      </null-data-fallback>

      <json-parse order="3">
        The data JSON string is parsed. If parsing fails, the raw tool result
        formatter is applied to the content string and its output is returned.
      </json-parse>

      <field-extraction order="4">
        The parsed object is checked for a string field named "name". If the field
        is absent or is not a string value, the JSON document is released and the
        raw tool result formatter is applied to the content string.

        A field named "output" is also checked. If it is present and is a string
        value, it is used as the output passed to the tool result formatter. If it
        is absent or not a string, null is passed instead.

        <notable reason="content parameter ignored when data_json is valid">
          When the data JSON parses successfully and contains a valid "name" field,
          the original content parameter is not used. The display output is derived
          entirely from the "name" and "output" fields of the data JSON, even if the
          original content string differs from those values.
        </notable>
      </field-extraction>

      <formatting order="5">
        The tool name and output (or null) are submitted to the tool result formatting
        system. The formatted, truncated result is returned. The JSON document is
        released before returning.
      </formatting>
    </format-tool-result>

    <format-tool-result-raw order="3">
      A raw content string is formatted with the tool response prefix applied and
      the content truncated. This path is taken when no data JSON is available or
      parseable for a tool result.

      <prefix order="1">
        The tool response prefix followed by a space is appended to a new format buffer.
      </prefix>

      <content order="2">
        If the content string is null, the literal text "(no output)" is appended.
        Otherwise, the content string is truncated and appended.
      </content>

      The resulting string from the format buffer is returned.
    </format-tool-result-raw>

  </behavior>

</specification>
