<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Event Rendering">

  <topic-statement>
    The event rendering system converts conversation event records into styled text
    lines and appends them to the scrollback display buffer.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The twelve recognized event kinds, the visual output produced for each (text
      content, color, prefix symbol), per-line color application, tool call and tool
      result formatting, token usage display, the blank-line spacing convention, and
      interruption styling.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Scrollback buffer">
      How appended lines are stored and laid out for rendering is covered by the
      scrollback buffer specification. This specification covers only what text
      is appended.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Terminal rendering">
      How scrollback lines appear on screen is covered by the layer rendering
      specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Event record">
      <field name="kind" type="text" note="one of twelve recognized values; determines how the event is rendered" />
      <field name="content" type="text or null" note="human-readable text content for display" />
      <field name="data json" type="text" note="structured JSON payload; used by command, mark, usage, fork, and tool events" />
      <field name="interrupted" type="boolean" note="when true, the event is rendered with cancellation styling" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <event-kinds order="1">
      Twelve event kinds are recognized. Events fall into two groups: conversation
      events (rendered to the scrollback) and metadata events (not rendered).

      **Rendered:**
      - `user` — text submitted by the user
      - `assistant` — text produced by the LLM
      - `tool_call` — a tool invocation request
      - `tool_result` — the result of tool execution
      - `fork` — a fork marker message
      - `command` — the output of a slash command
      - `mark` — a user bookmark
      - `usage` — token count information

      **Not rendered (silently ignored):**
      - `system` — stored for LLM context but never displayed
      - `rewind` — a rollback marker; handled by the replay system
      - `clear` — handled by the caller before replay
      - `agent_killed` — a metadata record for agent termination

      An unrecognized kind returns an error.
    </event-kinds>

    <blank-line-convention order="2">
      Every rendered event appends a blank line after its content. This blank line
      is a separate logical line in the scrollback buffer. It provides consistent
      visual spacing between events. Events that produce no output (such as zero
      token counts) also produce no blank line.
    </blank-line-convention>

    <color-application order="3">
      Color is applied using 256-color foreground ANSI sequences (`\x1b[38;5;<n>m`)
      followed by a reset (`\x1b[0m`). When color output is disabled (the `NO_COLOR`
      environment variable is set or `TERM=dumb`), no ANSI sequences are emitted.

      For multi-line content, color is applied to each line individually. Every line
      starts with the color sequence and ends with a reset. This prevents color state
      from carrying over into the next scrollback line.
    </color-application>

    <interruption-styling order="4">
      When the interrupted flag is true, the `user`, `tool_call`, and `tool_result`
      events use cancellation styling: the prefix symbol changes to `✗` and the
      color changes to a dark gray (256-color index 242). The `assistant` event
      ignores the interrupted flag.
    </interruption-styling>

    <per-event-rendering order="5">

      <user-event order="1">
        The content is trimmed of trailing whitespace and rendered with a right-
        pointing chevron prefix (`❯`). The default foreground color is used. A blank
        line follows.
      </user-event>

      <assistant-event order="2">
        The content is trimmed of trailing whitespace and rendered with a filled
        circle prefix (`●`) in a light-gray color (256-color index 249). A blank
        line follows.
      </assistant-event>

      <tool-call-event order="3">
        The tool call content is formatted as `→ tool_name: key="value", key=value, …`
        where:
        - The tool name is taken from the event data.
        - Arguments are parsed from the JSON arguments string and rendered as
          key=value pairs. String values are double-quoted; all other JSON types
          (numbers, booleans, null) are unquoted.
        - If the arguments JSON is absent or invalid, the raw arguments string is
          displayed instead.
        - If no arguments are present, only the tool name is shown.
        - The formatted text is truncated at 3 newlines or 400 characters, whichever
          is first. A `…` suffix is appended on truncation.

        The color is a dark gray (256-color index 242). A blank line follows.
      </tool-call-event>

      <tool-result-event order="4">
        The tool result content is formatted as `← tool_name: output` where:
        - The output is extracted from the result JSON based on its type:
          - A JSON string is used directly.
          - A JSON array has its elements joined with `, `.
          - A JSON object or other type is serialized to JSON.
        - If no result content is present, `(no output)` is shown.
        - The formatted text is truncated at 3 newlines or 400 characters. A `…`
          suffix is appended on truncation.

        The color is a dark gray (256-color index 242). A blank line follows.
      </tool-result-event>

      <fork-event order="5">
        The content is trimmed of trailing whitespace and rendered without a prefix,
        in a dark gray color (256-color index 242). A blank line follows.
      </fork-event>

      <command-event order="6">
        Two optional parts are rendered independently, each followed by its own blank
        line if non-empty:

        1. **Echo**: the `echo` field from the data JSON, rendered in a dark gray
           color without a prefix.
        2. **Output**: the `content` field, trimmed of trailing whitespace, rendered
           in a dark gray color without a prefix.

        Either part may be absent. If both are absent, nothing is rendered.
      </command-event>

      <mark-event order="7">
        The label field from the data JSON is read. If present, the text `/mark LABEL`
        is rendered. If absent, the text `/mark` is rendered. No color is applied.
        A blank line follows.
      </mark-event>

      <usage-event order="8">
        Token counts are read from the data JSON fields `input_tokens`,
        `output_tokens`, and optionally `thinking_tokens`. If the total is zero,
        nothing is rendered and no blank line is appended.

        If `thinking_tokens` is present and non-zero, the format is:
        `Tokens: <in> in + <out> out + <thinking> thinking = <total>`

        Otherwise:
        `Tokens: <in> in + <out> out = <total>`

        The color is a dark gray (256-color index 242). A blank line follows.
      </usage-event>

    </per-event-rendering>

    <triggers order="6">
      Event rendering is called in two contexts:

      1. **Live display**: when a new event is created during an active session
         (user input submitted, command executed, LLM response completed, tool
         executed), the event is rendered immediately and the result appears in the
         scrollback.

      2. **Database replay**: when an agent's session is restored from the database,
         all stored events are replayed through the renderer in chronological order
         to reconstruct the scrollback display.
    </triggers>

  </behavior>

</specification>
