<specification topic="External Tool Execution">

  <topic-statement>
    The external tool executor spawns a child process, passes JSON arguments
    via stdin, collects stdout as the result, and enforces a 30-second
    execution timeout.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Pipe creation, fork, child process setup (process group isolation,
      file descriptor redirection, environment variable injection, exec),
      stdin writing with SIGPIPE protection, stdout and stderr collection
      into fixed-size buffers, timeout enforcement via alarm(), process wait
      and exit-code validation, and result allocation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Registry">
      The executable path is provided by the caller. This topic does not
      look up tools by name.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Result Wrapping">
      Raw stdout text is returned as-is. JSON success/failure envelope
      wrapping is applied by the calling layer.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input">
      <field name="tool_path" type="text" note="absolute path to executable" />
      <field name="agent_id" type="text" nullable="true"
             note="set as IKIGAI_AGENT_ID environment variable if non-null" />
      <field name="arguments_json" type="text"
             note="JSON string written to child's stdin" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Output">
      <field name="child_pid_out" type="pid_t" required="false"
             note="child PID written here if pointer is non-null" />
      <field name="out_result" type="text"
             note="null-terminated stdout content; talloc-owned by caller" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <pipe-creation order="1">
      Three pairs of pipes are created: one for stdin, one for stdout, and
      one for stderr. If any pipe creation fails, all previously opened file
      descriptors are closed and an IO error is returned.
    </pipe-creation>

    <process-fork order="2">
      The process is forked. If fork fails, all six file descriptors are
      closed and an IO error is returned.
    </process-fork>

    <child-process-setup order="3">
      In the child process:
      - A new process group is created with the child as leader. This
        isolates the child from the parent's process group for interrupt
        handling.
      - The parent sides of all three pipes are closed.
      - The child sides are redirected: stdin pipe to fd 0, stdout pipe to
        fd 1, stderr pipe to fd 2.
      - If agent_id is non-null, the environment variable IKIGAI_AGENT_ID
        is set to that value, overwriting any existing value.
      - The executable at tool_path is executed with no additional arguments
        (only argv[0] which equals tool_path).
      - If execution fails, the child exits with status 1 immediately.

      All child-process code is excluded from coverage measurement (it runs
      in a forked copy of the address space, not the test process).
    </child-process-setup>

    <parent-process order="4">
      The child's PID is stored in child_pid_out if that pointer is non-null.
      The child sides of all three pipes are closed. The parent retains the
      write end of the stdin pipe and the read ends of the stdout and stderr
      pipes.
    </parent-process>

    <stdin-write order="5">
      SIGPIPE is temporarily suppressed to prevent a crash if the child exits
      before reading all input. The arguments JSON string is written to the
      child's stdin pipe. The write end is closed to signal EOF to the child.
      The original SIGPIPE disposition is restored.
    </stdin-write>

    <output-collection order="6">
      A 30-second alarm is set. Stdout is read into a 65,536-byte buffer in
      a loop until the read returns zero or negative, or the buffer fills to
      65,535 bytes. Stderr is read into a separate 65,536-byte buffer in the
      same manner. The alarm is cancelled after both streams are collected.

      <notable reason="silent-truncation">
        If either stdout or stderr exceeds 65,535 bytes, the remainder is
        silently discarded. No error is reported for truncation.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="timeout-behavior">
        If the child has not produced output within 30 seconds, the alarm
        signal interrupts the blocking read call. The read returns -1 and
        the loop exits. Subsequent processing continues with whatever was
        collected.
      </notable>
    </output-collection>

    <wait-and-validate order="7">
      The child process is waited for. If the child did not exit normally or
      exited with a non-zero status, an IO error is returned. If stderr
      content was collected, it is included in the error message; otherwise
      a generic non-zero-exit message is used.

      If the child exited successfully but produced no stdout output, an IO
      error is returned ("Tool produced no output").
    </wait-and-validate>

    <result-allocation order="8">
      The stdout buffer is null-terminated. Its contents are copied into a
      talloc allocation owned by the caller's context. If allocation fails,
      the process aborts. The pointer is written to out_result and success
      is returned.
    </result-allocation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
