<specification topic="File Reading">

  <topic-statement>
    The file reading utility reads the complete contents of a file from the filesystem
    into a null-terminated in-memory buffer.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Opening a file, determining its size, reading all bytes into a heap-allocated
      buffer, and null-terminating the result.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Filesystem">
      This topic opens, seeks, reads, and closes a file by path. Any operation that
      fails produces an I/O error returned to the caller.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Memory Management">
      The output buffer is allocated as a child of the provided context. The caller
      is responsible for managing its lifetime through talloc.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input">
      <field name="path" type="text" note="filesystem path to read" />
      <field name="out_size" type="pointer to unsigned integer" required="false" note="receives byte count if provided" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="Output">
      <field name="content" type="text buffer" note="heap-allocated, null-terminated, contains all file bytes followed by a null byte" />
      <field name="size" type="unsigned integer" note="number of bytes in the file, not counting the null terminator; only written if out_size was provided" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <reading-a-file order="1">

      <open order="1">
        The file is opened in binary read mode. If the open fails, an I/O error is
        returned and no further operations are attempted.
      </open>

      <size-determination order="2">
        The file position is seeked to the end to determine file size. If the seek
        fails, the file is closed and an I/O error is returned. The byte offset at
        the end is retrieved. If that operation fails, the file is closed and an I/O
        error is returned. The position is then seeked back to the beginning. If that
        seek fails, the file is closed and an I/O error is returned.
      </size-determination>

      <overflow-check order="3">
        If the file size exceeds the maximum unsigned 32-bit value minus one, the
        file is closed and an I/O error is returned indicating the file is too large.

        <notable reason="boundary uses UINT_MAX not SIZE_MAX">
          The overflow boundary is UINT_MAX (4,294,967,295) rather than SIZE_MAX.
          On 64-bit systems where SIZE_MAX is much larger, this artificially limits
          the maximum readable file size to approximately 4 GB.
        </notable>
      </overflow-check>

      <buffer-allocation order="4">
        A buffer of size plus one bytes is allocated. Allocation failure terminates
        the process immediately.
      </buffer-allocation>

      <read order="5">
        All bytes are read into the buffer. The file is closed immediately after the
        read regardless of success. If the number of bytes read does not equal the
        expected file size, an I/O error is returned.

        <notable reason="buffer leaks on read failure">
          When a short read is detected, an I/O error is returned but the allocated
          buffer is not freed. The allocated memory remains attached to the provided
          context until that context is freed.
        </notable>
      </read>

      <null-termination order="6">
        A null byte is written immediately after the last byte of file content. The
        content pointer and file size are written to the caller's output parameters.
        The size output parameter is only written if it was provided by the caller.
        The result carries the content pointer.
      </null-termination>

    </reading-a-file>

  </behavior>

</specification>
