<specification topic="Fork Argument Parsing">

  <topic-statement>
    The fork argument parsing system extracts an optional model override and
    an optional system prompt from the raw argument string of the fork
    command, and applies or inherits provider configuration for the child
    agent.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Tokenization of fork command arguments, extraction of the model
      specification flag and the quoted prompt string, validation of argument
      syntax, application of a model override to a child agent, and
      inheritance of provider configuration from a parent agent.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Agent Fork">
      How the child agent is created, how its conversation history is
      initialized, and how it is integrated into the REPL are handled by the
      agent fork subsystem. This topic covers only the argument parsing phase
      and the resulting configuration changes to the child agent record.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Model Selection">
      How model names are parsed into provider and thinking-level components
      is delegated to the model selection subsystem.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Fork Arguments">
      <field name="model specification" type="string or absent" note="value following the --model flag; absent if flag not present" />
      <field name="system prompt" type="string or absent" note="content extracted from between double quotes; absent if no quoted string present" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <argument-parsing order="1">
      The raw argument string is tokenized to extract two optional components:
      a model specification and a quoted system prompt. The two components may
      appear in either order.

      The model specification is indicated by the flag "--model" followed by
      a whitespace-delimited token. If "--model" appears without a following
      token, a syntax error is returned.

      The system prompt is enclosed in double quotes. The content between the
      opening and closing quote is extracted verbatim. If an opening quote is
      present without a matching closing quote, a syntax error is returned.
      An empty quoted string (two adjacent double-quote characters) is valid
      and produces an empty prompt string.

      Any non-whitespace text that is neither part of the "--model" flag, its
      value, nor a quoted string is treated as a syntax error.

      <notable reason="parsing is order-independent">
        The "--model" flag and the quoted string may appear in any order
        relative to each other. "/fork --model gpt-x \"prompt\"" and
        "/fork \"prompt\" --model gpt-x" are equivalent.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="empty argument string is valid">
        An absent or whitespace-only argument string is accepted without error.
        Both the model specification and the system prompt are treated as
        absent.
      </notable>
    </argument-parsing>

    <model-override-application order="2">
      When a model specification is present in the parsed arguments, it is
      applied to the child agent. The specification is parsed by the model
      selection subsystem to extract a provider identifier, a model name, and
      an optional thinking level.

      If the model name is not recognized, an error is returned. If a thinking
      level is specified, it is applied to the child agent. If no thinking
      level is specified, the child agent's thinking level is not modified at
      this stage.

      The child agent's provider and model fields are updated to the resolved
      values.

      <notable reason="thinking level is conditional">
        The model specification string may optionally include a thinking level
        in the form "model/level". If the level component is absent, the child
        agent's existing thinking level is preserved.
      </notable>
    </model-override-application>

    <provider-config-inheritance order="3">
      When no model specification is present in the parsed arguments, the
      child agent inherits the parent agent's provider configuration. The
      parent's provider identifier, model name, and thinking level are copied
      to the child agent.

      If either the parent's provider or model field is absent (null), that
      field is not copied.

      <notable reason="root agents may have null provider and model">
        A parent agent that has not yet made an LLM request may have null
        provider and model fields. Inheritance skips null fields silently,
        leaving the child with no provider or model configured.
      </notable>
    </provider-config-inheritance>

  </behavior>

</specification>
