<specification topic="fork-event-persistence">
  <topic-statement>The fork event persistence system builds and inserts database records for both sides of a fork operation, capturing a snapshot of the child agent's pinned documents and toolset configuration.</topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>Mapping of thinking level enum values to their canonical string representations</in-scope>
    <in-scope>Construction of a human-readable fork feedback message</in-scope>
    <in-scope>Insertion of paired parent and child fork event records into the database</in-scope>
    <in-scope>Snapshot of pinned document paths and toolset filter at the moment of forking</in-scope>
    <boundary name="agent-creation">Spawning the child agent process or initializing its state is out of scope.</boundary>
    <boundary name="fork-command-parsing">Parsing the user's fork command arguments is covered separately.</boundary>
    <boundary name="pin-document-lifecycle">Managing pinned documents beyond snapshotting them at fork time is out of scope.</boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="thinking-level-strings">
      <field name="MIN" type="string" notes="maps to &quot;min&quot;" />
      <field name="LOW" type="string" notes="maps to &quot;low&quot;" />
      <field name="MED" type="string" notes="maps to &quot;medium&quot;" />
      <field name="HIGH" type="string" notes="maps to &quot;high&quot;" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="parent-fork-event-data">
      <field name="child_uuid" type="string" notes="UUID of the newly created child agent" />
      <field name="fork_message_id" type="integer" notes="ID of the message that triggered the fork" />
      <field name="role" type="string" notes="fixed value &quot;parent&quot;" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="child-fork-event-data">
      <field name="parent_uuid" type="string" notes="UUID of the parent agent" />
      <field name="fork_message_id" type="integer" notes="ID of the message that triggered the fork" />
      <field name="role" type="string" notes="fixed value &quot;child&quot;" />
      <field name="pinned_paths" type="JSON array of strings" notes="paths of all currently pinned documents on the child agent at fork time" />
      <field name="toolset_filter" type="JSON array of strings" notes="names of all tools in the child agent's toolset filter; empty array when no filter is set" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>
    <thinking-level-mapping order="1">
      Four thinking level values are mapped to strings for use in human-readable output
      and database records: the minimum level maps to "min", low maps to "low", medium
      maps to "medium", and high maps to "high".
    </thinking-level-mapping>

    <fork-feedback-message order="2">
      After a fork completes, a human-readable feedback string is produced describing
      the newly created child. The string takes the form:
      "Forked child {uuid} ({provider}/{model}/{thinking_level_string})"
      where the thinking level is rendered using the four-value mapping above.
    </fork-feedback-message>

    <parent-event-insertion order="3">
      A fork event record is inserted into the database on behalf of the parent agent.
      The record's kind is "fork" and its agent field identifies the parent. The
      auxiliary JSON data encodes the child's UUID, the ID of the message that
      triggered the fork, and the role string "parent".
    </parent-event-insertion>

    <child-event-insertion order="4">
      A second fork event record is inserted into the database on behalf of the child
      agent. The record's kind is "fork" and its agent field identifies the child. The
      auxiliary JSON data encodes the parent's UUID, the same triggering message ID,
      and the role string "child". It also includes two snapshot arrays captured from
      the child agent's state at the moment of forking.
    </child-event-insertion>

    <pinned-paths-snapshot order="5">
      The child event record includes a JSON array named "pinned_paths" containing one
      string entry per currently pinned document on the child agent. Each entry is the
      path of that pinned document. The array preserves all pinned paths as they exist
      at fork time and serves as a durable record of the child's initial document
      context.
    </pinned-paths-snapshot>

    <toolset-filter-snapshot order="6">
      The child event record includes a JSON array named "toolset_filter" containing
      one string entry per tool name present in the child agent's toolset filter. When
      no toolset filter has been configured, the array is empty. This snapshot captures
      the tool restrictions active on the child at the moment of forking.
    </toolset-filter-snapshot>

    <insertion-result order="7">
      The operation returns success if both event records are inserted without error,
      or an error if either insertion fails. No partial-success state is defined; a
      failure on either record propagates as the return value.
    </insertion-result>
  </behavior>
</specification>
