<specification topic="Format Buffer">

  <topic-statement>
    The format buffer accumulates formatted text incrementally and provides
    access to the assembled result as a null-terminated string.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Creating a format buffer, appending text via printf-style formatting or
      direct string append, inserting indentation, retrieving the accumulated
      string and its length, and applying a line-and-character truncation limit
      when appending content.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Byte Array">
      The format buffer stores its content in an underlying resizable byte
      array. This topic drives growth through appends but does not manage
      the byte array's internal layout.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Callers">
      Callers create the buffer, append to it, then retrieve the final string.
      The returned string pointer remains valid for the lifetime of the
      caller-provided allocation context.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Format Buffer">
      <field name="underlying byte array" type="opaque" note="resizes automatically as content is appended" />
      <field name="allocation context" type="pointer" note="the talloc context provided at creation" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="Truncated Append Input">
      <field name="content" type="text" note="must be non-null" />
      <field name="content length" type="unsigned integer" note="byte count of content" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      A new format buffer is created under a caller-provided allocation context.
      The internal byte array is initialized with a 32-byte growth increment.
      The buffer begins empty. If any allocation fails during creation, the
      process terminates immediately.

      The allocation context is stored internally and used when the accumulated
      string is later retrieved.
    </creation>

    <printf-style-append order="2">
      A format string and variadic arguments are rendered to a temporary buffer
      using standard printf-style formatting. The byte count required for the
      formatted output is determined first; then the formatted bytes are
      appended one at a time to the internal byte array.

      If the printf rendering fails (format string error or output truncation
      detected), an error is returned. The buffer's existing content is not
      modified on error.

      If any internal memory allocation fails, the process terminates
      immediately.
    </printf-style-append>

    <string-append order="3">
      A null-terminated string is appended to the internal byte array one byte
      at a time. An empty string is a no-op that returns success without
      modifying the buffer. If any internal memory allocation fails, the process
      terminates immediately.
    </string-append>

    <indentation order="4">
      A non-negative indentation level is specified. That many space characters
      (0x20) are appended to the buffer. A level of zero is a no-op. Negative
      indentation levels are not accepted (the caller must ensure the value is
      non-negative). If any internal memory allocation fails, the process
      terminates immediately.
    </indentation>

    <string-retrieval order="5">
      The accumulated content is returned as a null-terminated string. If the
      last byte in the buffer is not already a null terminator, one is appended
      before returning. The returned pointer points into the buffer's internal
      storage and remains valid until the buffer's allocation context is freed.

      <notable reason="mutates buffer on first call">
        Retrieving the string is not a pure read operation. If the buffer does
        not yet end with a null terminator, this operation appends one,
        permanently modifying the buffer's byte array. Subsequent retrievals
        detect the null terminator already present and return without further
        modification.
      </notable>
    </string-retrieval>

    <length-retrieval order="6">
      The number of content bytes in the buffer is returned, excluding any
      trailing null terminator. If the last byte is a null terminator, the
      reported length is one less than the internal array size. Otherwise the
      length equals the internal array size. This operation does not modify
      the buffer.
    </length-retrieval>

    <truncated-append order="7">
      Content up to a combined limit of 3 lines and 400 characters is appended
      to the buffer. The content is scanned byte by byte:

      - Each newline (0x0A) increments the line count. If the line count
        exceeds 3, scanning stops at the newline position.
      - Each byte increments the character count. If the character count
        reaches 400, scanning stops after that byte.

      If scanning stopped before the end of the content, only the bytes up
      to the stopping point are appended, followed by "..." to indicate
      truncation. If the entire content fits within the limits, it is appended
      in full without the truncation indicator.

      If the content length is zero, the literal text "(no output)" is appended
      instead of the content.
    </truncated-append>

  </behavior>

</specification>
