<specification topic="Framebuffer Serialization">

  <topic-statement>
    The framebuffer serialization system converts raw terminal framebuffer bytes
    into a structured JSON representation that encodes text content and styling metadata.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Parsing ANSI escape sequences from framebuffer bytes, extracting text and style
      information, and producing a JSON document describing rows, spans, colors, and
      cursor state.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Framebuffer Source">
      This topic receives a byte buffer containing raw terminal output (text intermixed
      with ANSI escape sequences), terminal dimensions, and cursor state. It does not
      produce or maintain the framebuffer.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Consumers">
      This topic produces a JSON string. What consumes that string is outside this
      topic's scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input">
      <field name="framebuffer bytes" type="byte array" />
      <field name="row count" type="integer" />
      <field name="column count" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor row" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor column" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor visible" type="boolean" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Style">
      <field name="foreground color" type="integer" note="256-color palette index; 0 means unset" />
      <field name="bold" type="boolean" />
      <field name="dim" type="boolean" />
      <field name="reverse" type="boolean" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Span">
      <field name="text" type="string" note="content segment sharing a single style" />
      <field name="style" type="Style" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Line">
      <field name="row" type="integer" note="zero-based row index" />
      <field name="spans" type="array of Span" note="always at least one span per line" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="JSON Output">
      <field name="type" type="string" note="always the string 'framebuffer'" />
      <field name="rows" type="integer" />
      <field name="cols" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor_row" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor_col" type="integer" />
      <field name="cursor_visible" type="boolean" />
      <field name="lines" type="array of Line JSON objects" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <entry-validation order="1">
      If the framebuffer byte pointer is null, the operation fails immediately and
      returns an error. No output is produced.
    </entry-validation>

    <initialization order="2">
      Before parsing begins, a line array is allocated with one slot per terminal row.
      Each slot is initialized with its row index, an empty span array (initial capacity
      four), and a fresh text buffer (initial capacity 256 bytes). A single empty initial
      span is prepared in a transient working area for accumulating text during the parse.
    </initialization>

    <parsing-framebuffer-bytes order="3">
      The parser iterates through every byte in the framebuffer, advancing one character
      at a time unless an escape sequence or multi-byte UTF-8 character causes a larger
      jump.

      <cursor-hide-skip order="1">
        When the cursor-hide escape sequence (ESC[?25l) is encountered, it is skipped
        entirely and contributes no text or style change.
      </cursor-hide-skip>

      <cursor-home-skip order="2">
        When the cursor-home escape sequence (ESC[H) is encountered, it is skipped
        entirely and contributes no text or style change.
      </cursor-home-skip>

      <escape-sequence-dispatch order="3">
        Any other byte pair matching ESC followed by '[' triggers escape sequence
        handling. The parser inspects the bytes immediately following the '[' to
        determine which sequence applies.

        <foreground-color order="1">
          A sequence of the form ESC[38;5;NNNm (where NNN is a decimal integer)
          sets the foreground color to the parsed index value. Before the color
          is applied, any accumulated text in the current span is flushed to the
          current line. The new color takes effect for subsequent text. If the
          byte sequence does not match the expected prefix "38;5;" exactly or
          there are insufficient bytes remaining, the sequence is skipped.
        </foreground-color>

        <reset order="2">
          A sequence ending in 'm' preceded by '0' resets all style flags. Any
          accumulated text in the current span is flushed to the current line. The
          foreground color, bold, dim, and reverse flags are all cleared to their
          zero/false defaults.
        </reset>

        <bold order="3">
          A sequence matching the bold attribute sets the bold flag. Any accumulated
          text in the current span is flushed before the flag is updated.
        </bold>

        <dim order="4">
          A sequence matching the dim attribute sets the dim flag. Any accumulated
          text in the current span is flushed before the flag is updated.
        </dim>

        <reverse order="5">
          A sequence matching the reverse attribute sets the reverse flag. Any
          accumulated text in the current span is flushed before the flag is updated.
        </reverse>

        <unknown-sequence-skip order="6">
          Any escape sequence that does not match the recognized patterns is skipped.
          The parser advances past the ESC[ prefix and then continues advancing until
          it reaches a byte value in the printable ASCII range (0x20 to 0x7E inclusive),
          at which point it stops (without consuming that byte). This ensures unknown
          sequences do not produce text output.
        </unknown-sequence-skip>
      </escape-sequence-dispatch>

      <carriage-return-linefeed order="4">
        When a CR+LF pair is encountered, the current line is finalized. If the
        current span contains any accumulated text (or if the current line has no
        spans yet), the span is flushed to the current line. The parser then advances
        to the next line. The current row index increments by one.

        <notable reason="empty-line handling">
          The flush condition for CRLF checks either text_len > 0 OR span_count == 0.
          This ensures that even a line with no text produces at least one flush,
          which combined with the post-processing step guarantees every line has at
          least one span in the output.
        </notable>
      </carriage-return-linefeed>

      <regular-character order="5">
        Any byte that is not part of an escape sequence or CRLF is appended to the
        current span's text buffer. If the text buffer is full, it is doubled in
        capacity before the character is added.
      </regular-character>
    </parsing-framebuffer-bytes>

    <post-processing order="4">
      After the parse loop completes, every line in the line array is checked. If a
      line has zero spans, an empty span is allocated and added to it. This guarantees
      that every line in the output has at least one span, even if the line received
      no text during parsing.
    </post-processing>

    <span-flushing order="5">
      Flushing moves the current working span into the line's span array. If the
      accumulated text buffer is empty, the span is discarded without being added.
      If adding the span would exceed the line's span array capacity, the capacity
      is doubled. After flushing, a new 256-byte text buffer is allocated for the
      next span, and the new span inherits the current style.

      <notable reason="silent discard on empty span">
        If the current span has no text, flush is a no-op. No empty span is added
        to the line during normal text flushing (only the post-processing step adds
        empty spans to lines with zero spans).
      </notable>
    </span-flushing>

    <json-construction order="6">
      After parsing and post-processing, the output JSON document is constructed
      from the collected lines.

      <top-level-envelope order="1">
        The root JSON object contains the fields: type (the literal string
        "framebuffer"), rows, cols, cursor_row, cursor_col, cursor_visible, and lines.
        The lines value is a JSON array.
      </top-level-envelope>

      <line-json order="2">
        Each line is serialized as a JSON object with fields row (integer) and spans
        (JSON array). Lines are comma-separated within the array.
      </line-json>

      <span-json order="3">
        Each span is serialized as a JSON object with fields text and style. Text
        content is JSON-escaped (double quotes and backslashes are escaped with a
        preceding backslash). Style is a JSON object.
      </span-json>

      <style-json order="4">
        The style JSON object contains only non-default fields. A foreground color
        is included only if it is non-zero. Bold, dim, and reverse are included only
        if true. If all style attributes are at their defaults, the style object is
        empty. Fields within the style object are comma-separated and appear in the
        order: fg, bold, dim, reverse.
      </style-json>
    </json-construction>

    <memory-management order="7">
      All intermediate allocations (line arrays, span arrays, text buffers) are
      made under a temporary context that is freed after the final JSON string is
      produced. The JSON output string is allocated under the caller-provided context
      and outlives the intermediate allocations.
    </memory-management>

  </behavior>

</specification>
