<specification topic="Fuzzy Filter">

  <topic-statement>
    The fuzzy filter scores and ranks a candidate string list against a search
    query, returning the best-matching results up to a caller-specified limit.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Prefix filtering, fuzzy subsequence scoring, result sorting, and result
      count limiting.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tab Completion">
      The fuzzy filter is invoked by the tab-completion system to rank
      completion candidates. Candidate generation and selection are handled
      externally.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Fzy Library">
      Subsequence matching and scoring are delegated to the vendored fzy
      library. The fzy library's behaviour is not specified here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input">
      <field name="candidates" type="array of strings" note="caller-owned; not copied" />
      <field name="candidate_count" type="non-negative integer" />
      <field name="search" type="string" note="may be empty; must not be null" />
      <field name="max_results" type="positive integer" note="upper bound on returned results" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Result Entry">
      <field name="candidate" type="string pointer" note="points into the original candidates array; not a copy" />
      <field name="score" type="double" note="higher values indicate better matches" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Output">
      <field name="result array" type="array of result entries" note="talloc-owned by the caller's context; null when no results" />
      <field name="count" type="non-negative integer" note="number of entries in the result array" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <prefix-filter order="1">
      Before fuzzy scoring is applied, candidates are filtered by prefix. A
      candidate passes only if it begins with the search string, compared
      case-insensitively. Candidates that do not pass the prefix test are
      excluded from scoring entirely.

      An empty search string passes all candidates through the prefix filter,
      because every string begins with an empty prefix.
    </prefix-filter>

    <fuzzy-scoring order="2">
      Each candidate that passed the prefix filter is tested for a fuzzy match:
      the search string's characters must all appear in the candidate in order
      (not necessarily consecutively). Candidates that fail this test are
      excluded. Candidates that pass receive a numeric score; higher scores
      indicate a closer match.
    </fuzzy-scoring>

    <sorting order="3">
      Scored candidates are sorted in descending score order. Candidates with
      higher scores appear first in the result array.
    </sorting>

    <result-limiting order="4">
      If the number of matching candidates exceeds max_results, only the first
      max_results entries (the highest-scoring) are returned. If the number of
      matches is at or below max_results, all matches are returned.

      If no candidates match, null is returned and the output count is zero.
    </result-limiting>

    <notable reason="candidate-pointers-are-aliases">
      Result entries hold pointers directly into the caller-supplied candidates
      array. The caller must ensure candidate strings remain valid for as long
      as the result array is in use.
    </notable>

    <notable reason="zero-candidates-returns-null">
      When candidate_count is zero, the function returns null immediately
      without consulting the search string.
    </notable>

  </behavior>

</specification>
