<specification topic="Generic Array">

  <topic-statement>
    The generic array is a type-agnostic resizable collection that stores fixed-size
    elements contiguously and grows its capacity on demand.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Array creation, element appending, element insertion, element deletion, element
      replacement, element access, size and capacity queries, and the byte-typed
      specialization of the generic array.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Memory Management">
      This topic allocates memory and panics on allocation failure. Memory ownership
      follows the talloc hierarchy — the array and its buffer are children of the
      context provided at creation. Freeing the context frees the array and buffer.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Array">
      <field name="element size" type="unsigned integer" note="bytes per element; must be greater than zero" />
      <field name="increment" type="unsigned integer" note="capacity for first allocation; must be greater than zero" />
      <field name="size" type="unsigned integer" note="current number of elements; starts at zero" />
      <field name="capacity" type="unsigned integer" note="allocated capacity in elements; starts at zero" />
      <field name="buffer" type="pointer" nullable="true" note="null until first insertion or append" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      A new array is created by supplying an element size and an increment value. If
      either value is zero, creation fails with an invalid-argument error and no array
      is returned. On success, the array starts with zero elements, zero capacity, and
      no allocated buffer. No buffer is allocated at creation time.
    </creation>

    <appending order="2">
      An element is appended to the end of the array. If the current number of elements
      equals the current capacity, the array grows before the element is copied. The
      element is copied by value using the element size specified at creation. The
      element count increases by one. The operation always succeeds — any allocation
      failure terminates the process.

      <shared topic="Capacity Growth">
        When the array is full, capacity is expanded. If the current capacity is zero,
        the new capacity equals the increment. Otherwise the new capacity doubles. The
        buffer is reallocated to hold the new capacity. Allocation failure terminates
        the process immediately.
      </shared>
    </appending>

    <insertion order="3">
      An element is inserted at a specified index. The index must be between zero and
      the current element count inclusive — inserting at the end is valid. If the array
      is full, it grows first. All elements from the insertion index to the end are
      shifted one position toward the end to make room. The new element is then copied
      into the vacated slot. The element count increases by one. Allocation failure
      terminates the process.
    </insertion>

    <deletion order="4">
      An element at a specified index is removed. All elements after the deleted index
      are shifted one position toward the beginning. The element count decreases by one.
      The allocated buffer capacity is never reduced. No validation is performed — the
      index must be within bounds.
    </deletion>

    <replacement order="5">
      An element at a specified index is overwritten by copying the new element value
      into the slot. The element count does not change. The index must be within bounds
      — no validation is performed.
    </replacement>

    <clearing order="6">
      All elements are removed by setting the element count to zero. The allocated
      buffer is not freed and the capacity is unchanged. After clearing, the array
      reports zero elements but its capacity remains at whatever it was before.
    </clearing>

    <element-access order="7">
      A direct pointer into the buffer at the requested index is returned. The pointer
      is valid until the next mutation that may reallocate the buffer. The index must
      be within bounds — no validation is performed.
    </element-access>

    <size-and-capacity-queries order="8">
      The current element count and current allocated capacity can each be queried
      independently. Both return unsigned integer values.
    </size-and-capacity-queries>

    <byte-typed-specialization order="9">
      A byte-typed specialization of the generic array stores unsigned 8-bit values.
      It has the same creation, append, insert, delete, clear, and size operations as
      the generic array, using an element size of one byte. The get operation differs:
      it returns the byte value directly rather than a pointer into the buffer.
      There is no capacity query exposed by the byte-typed specialization.
    </byte-typed-specialization>

    <overflow-protection order="10">
      <notable reason="theoretical only">
        Integer overflow protection is present for capacity doubling and buffer
        allocation size, but these limits require storing more elements than any
        64-bit system can physically hold (on the order of exabytes). In practice,
        the process runs out of memory and aborts long before the overflow condition
        could be reached.
      </notable>
    </overflow-protection>

  </behavior>

</specification>
