<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Google Gemini Content Block Serialization">

  <topic-statement>
    The Google content block serializer transforms canonical message content
    blocks into the parts format required by the Gemini API, including role
    mapping per model series and per-type part construction for text, thinking,
    tool call, tool result, and redacted thinking blocks.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Role string mapping for user, assistant, and tool roles, content block
      serialization for all canonical block types (text, thinking, tool call,
      tool result, redacted thinking), tool result name lookup by backward scan,
      thought signature injection as a leading part for the first assistant
      message, and thought signature retrieval from assistant message metadata.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Request serialization">
      How the parts produced here are assembled into the full Gemini request
      JSON body (systemInstruction, contents array, tools, toolConfig,
      generationConfig) is covered by the Google request serialization
      specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Thought signature storage">
      How thought signatures are extracted from streaming responses and stored
      in message metadata is covered by the Google streaming event processing
      specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Thinking level computation">
      How abstract thinking levels are translated into numeric budgets or level
      strings is covered by the Google thinking configuration specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Role mapping">
      <field name="user role" type="text" note="always maps to the string 'user'" />
      <field name="assistant role" type="text" note="always maps to the string 'model'" />
      <field name="tool role" type="text" note="maps to 'user' for Gemini 3 models; maps to 'function' for all other models" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Text part">
      <field name="text" type="string" note="the text content of the block" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Thinking part">
      <field name="text" type="string" note="the thinking text content" />
      <field name="thought" type="boolean" note="always true; marks the part as a thinking part" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool call part">
      <field name="functionCall" type="object" note="nested object containing name and args" />
      <field name="functionCall.name" type="string" note="the tool name" />
      <field name="functionCall.args" type="object" note="the tool arguments as a parsed JSON object, not a string" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool result part">
      <field name="functionResponse" type="object" note="nested object containing name and response" />
      <field name="functionResponse.name" type="string" note="the function name looked up from prior messages, or the tool call ID as fallback" />
      <field name="functionResponse.response" type="object" note="wrapper object with a 'content' field" />
      <field name="functionResponse.response.content" type="string" note="the result content string" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Thought signature part">
      <field name="thoughtSignature" type="string" note="the opaque thought signature string; injected as a standalone part object" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <role-mapping order="1">
      Each message has a canonical role that is mapped to a Gemini role string
      before serialization. The mapping is:

      - User role → "user"
      - Assistant role → "model"
      - Tool role → "user" when the model is Gemini 3; "function" for all
        other models (including Gemini 2.5, other Gemini models, and null model)

      Role determination for the tool role performs a model series check.
      When the model identifier is null, the tool role maps to "function"
      (the non-Gemini-3 path).

      <notable reason="tool role differs by Gemini series">
        Gemini 3 introduced a requirement that tool result messages use the
        "user" role rather than the older "function" role. Sending "function"
        role to a Gemini 3 endpoint is incorrect. The serializer branches on
        model series to emit the appropriate role string.
      </notable>
    </role-mapping>

    <parts-assembly order="2">
      Each message's content is serialized into a "parts" array. The parts
      array is constructed in two phases:

      Phase 1 — Thought signature injection: If a thought signature is
      available and the current message is the first assistant-role message
      encountered during iteration, a standalone thought signature part is
      prepended as the first element of the parts array. This part is an
      object with a single "thoughtSignature" key set to the signature string.

      Phase 2 — Content block parts: Each content block in the message is
      serialized in order and appended to the parts array.

      <notable reason="thought signature injected only into first assistant message">
        The thought signature is injected at most once per request, into the
        first assistant message in the conversation. Subsequent assistant
        messages receive no injected signature part, even if a signature is
        available.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="thought signature only on Gemini 3">
        The thought signature value passed during serialization is null for
        non-Gemini-3 models. Phase 1 is a no-op when the signature is null,
        so no thoughtSignature part is ever injected for non-Gemini-3 models.
      </notable>
    </parts-assembly>

    <text-block-serialization order="3">
      A text content block produces a single part object with one field:
      - "text": the text string from the block

      No additional fields are added.
    </text-block-serialization>

    <thinking-block-serialization order="4">
      A thinking content block produces a single part object with two fields:
      - "text": the thinking text from the block
      - "thought": true (boolean)

      The "thought" field distinguishes this part from a regular text part
      when the Gemini API returns or receives it. Both fields are always
      present together.
    </thinking-block-serialization>

    <redacted-thinking-block-serialization order="5">
      A redacted thinking content block produces no output. The block is
      silently skipped and no part object is added to the parts array.

      <notable reason="redacted thinking blocks are dropped entirely">
        Unlike Anthropic serialization which re-emits redacted thinking blocks
        with their opaque data, the Google serializer discards them. Gemini
        does not have an equivalent concept for redacted thinking.
      </notable>
    </redacted-thinking-block-serialization>

    <tool-call-block-serialization order="6">
      A tool call content block produces a single part object with one field:
      - "functionCall": an object containing "name" and "args"

      The "name" field is the tool name string. The "args" field is the tool
      arguments parsed from their stored JSON string representation into a live
      JSON object. The arguments are embedded as a JSON object, not a string.

      <notable reason="args are parsed to object, not passed as string">
        Tool call arguments in canonical form are stored as a JSON string.
        During serialization the string is parsed into a JSON object before
        embedding. The Gemini API requires args as a structured object, unlike
        the OpenAI Chat Completions API which accepts a string.
      </notable>
    </tool-call-block-serialization>

    <tool-result-block-serialization order="7">
      A tool result content block produces a single part object with one field:
      - "functionResponse": an object containing "name" and "response"

      The "name" field is resolved by scanning prior messages (see tool result
      name lookup). The "response" field is an object with a single "content"
      key set to the result content string.

      <notable reason="response is wrapped in an object">
        The result content string is not placed directly under "functionResponse".
        It is nested one level deeper inside a "response" object with the key
        "content". This nesting is required by the Gemini API format.
      </notable>
    </tool-result-block-serialization>

    <tool-result-name-lookup order="8">
      A tool result block carries a tool call ID that refers to a prior tool
      call. To serialize the result, the corresponding tool name must be found.
      The name is not stored directly in the tool result block; it must be
      retrieved by scanning the message history.

      The lookup scans all messages before the current message index, in
      forward order (oldest first). For each message, all content blocks are
      checked. When a tool call block is found whose ID matches the tool result's
      tool call ID, the tool name from that block is returned immediately.

      If no matching tool call block is found after scanning all prior messages,
      the tool call ID itself is used as the function name.

      <notable reason="fallback uses tool call ID as name">
        If the matching tool call is not found in prior messages — for example
        because it was truncated from the context window — the tool call ID
        string is used verbatim as the function name in the serialized
        functionResponse. This produces a syntactically valid but semantically
        incorrect response; the Gemini API may reject it or treat it as an
        unknown function.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="forward scan stops before current message">
        The scan covers only messages at indices strictly less than the current
        message index. The current message and any later messages are not
        examined. This ensures only causally prior tool calls are candidates.
      </notable>
    </tool-result-name-lookup>

    <thought-signature-retrieval order="9">
      Before request serialization begins, the most recent thought signature is
      retrieved from the message history for Gemini 3 models.

      The retrieval scans messages in reverse order (newest first). Only
      assistant-role messages are examined. For each candidate assistant
      message, the message metadata field is inspected. If the metadata is
      non-null, non-empty, and parseable as JSON, the "thought_signature" key
      is extracted. If the key is present, is a string, and is non-empty, its
      value is returned as the thought signature.

      Scanning stops at the first assistant message that yields a valid
      signature. If no such message is found, the result is null.

      The retrieved signature is copied into owned storage before the parsed
      metadata document is released, ensuring the signature string remains
      valid for the duration of serialization.

      <notable reason="only assistant messages are scanned">
        User messages, tool messages, and system messages are skipped entirely
        during the reverse scan. Only messages with the assistant role can
        carry a thought signature in their metadata.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="malformed metadata JSON is silently skipped">
        If an assistant message's metadata field contains malformed JSON or
        a JSON structure that does not have "thought_signature" as a non-empty
        string, that message is skipped and the scan continues to the next
        older assistant message. No error is reported.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="retrieval is skipped for non-Gemini-3 models">
        The entire reverse scan is short-circuited when the model is not
        classified as Gemini 3. The returned signature is null unconditionally
        for non-Gemini-3 models, even if thought signatures happen to be stored
        in the message metadata.
      </notable>
    </thought-signature-retrieval>

  </behavior>

</specification>
