<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Google Thinking Configuration">

  <topic-statement>
    The Google thinking configuration system classifies Gemini models into
    series and translates an abstract thinking level into the API parameters
    that control thinking depth for each series.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The model series classification (Gemini 2.5 vs Gemini 3 vs other),
      the budget-based thinking configuration for Gemini 2.5 models including
      the per-model budget tables and power-of-2 calculation, the level-string
      configuration for Gemini 3 models including per-model level tables and
      fallback defaults, the can-disable-thinking determination, and the
      validation rules for thinking levels per model.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Request serialization">
      How the computed thinking budget or level string is embedded into the
      Google API JSON request body is covered by the provider serialization
      specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <model-series-classification order="1">
      Each Gemini model is classified into one of three series by substring
      search in the model identifier:

      - If the identifier contains `gemini-3`: classified as Gemini 3
      - If the identifier contains `gemini-2.5`: classified as Gemini 2.5
      - Otherwise: classified as other (no thinking support)

      Classification is performed by substring match, not prefix or exact
      match. Order matters: `gemini-3` is checked before `gemini-2.5`.

      <notable reason="substring match means embedded substrings match">
        A hypothetical identifier like `my-gemini-3-custom` would be
        classified as Gemini 3 because it contains the substring `gemini-3`.
      </notable>
    </model-series-classification>

    <gemini-2-5-budget-thinking order="2">
      Gemini 2.5 models use token budget thinking, similar to budget-based
      Anthropic models.

      <per-model-budget-limits order="1">
        Token budget limits are defined per exact model identifier:

        - `gemini-2.5-pro`: minimum 128 tokens, maximum 32,768 tokens.
          This model cannot fully disable thinking (minimum budget > 0).
        - `gemini-2.5-flash-lite`: minimum 512 tokens, maximum 24,576 tokens.
          This model cannot fully disable thinking.
        - `gemini-2.5-flash`: minimum 0 tokens, maximum 24,576 tokens.
          This model can disable thinking (minimum budget is 0).

        For Gemini 2.5 models whose identifier does not match any table entry,
        the budget calculation returns -1 (unsupported).
      </per-model-budget-limits>

      <budget-calculation order="2">
        Given a model's minimum budget `min` and maximum budget `max`, the
        range is `max - min`. The four thinking levels produce:

        - MIN → `min` exactly
        - LOW → floor to nearest power of 2 of `min + range / 3`
        - MED → floor to nearest power of 2 of `min + (2 × range) / 3`
        - HIGH → `max` exactly

        The power-of-2 floor finds the largest power of 2 not exceeding the
        input. Integer division is used for range thirds.

        <notable reason="gemini-2.5-pro and gemini-2.5-flash-lite have non-zero minimum">
          At MIN thinking level, `gemini-2.5-pro` produces a budget of 128
          and `gemini-2.5-flash-lite` produces 512. Thinking cannot be
          disabled for these models via the MIN level; the API always receives
          a positive budget.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="gemini-2.5-flash can disable thinking">
          At MIN thinking level, `gemini-2.5-flash` produces a budget of 0,
          which signals the API to disable thinking.
        </notable>
      </budget-calculation>

      <can-disable-thinking order="3">
        A Gemini 2.5 model can disable thinking if and only if its minimum
        budget is exactly 0. Only `gemini-2.5-flash` satisfies this
        condition among the registered models. Unknown Gemini 2.5 models
        (not in the table) cannot disable thinking.

        Gemini 3 models cannot disable thinking (they use level strings,
        and MIN maps to the lowest available level, not silence).

        Non-thinking models (series classified as other) are considered to
        be unable to disable thinking, as they have no thinking to disable.
      </can-disable-thinking>
    </gemini-2-5-budget-thinking>

    <gemini-3-level-thinking order="3">
      Gemini 3 models use level strings rather than numeric budgets.

      <per-model-level-mappings order="1">
        Level strings are defined per exact model identifier:

        - `gemini-3-flash-preview`:
          MIN → `"minimal"`, LOW → `"low"`, MED → `"medium"`, HIGH → `"high"`
        - `gemini-3-pro-preview`:
          MIN → `"low"`, LOW → `"low"`, MED → `"high"`, HIGH → `"high"`
          (MIN and LOW collapse to `"low"`; MED and HIGH collapse to `"high"`)
        - `gemini-3.1-pro-preview`:
          MIN → `"low"`, LOW → `"low"`, MED → `"medium"`, HIGH → `"high"`
          (MIN and LOW both yield `"low"`)

        <notable reason="gemini-3-pro-preview has only two distinct levels">
          This model has only two observable outcomes: `"low"` for MIN and
          LOW levels, and `"high"` for MED and HIGH levels.
        </notable>
      </per-model-level-mappings>

      <unknown-gemini-3-model-fallback order="2">
        For Gemini 3 models whose identifier does not match any entry in
        the level table, a safe default mapping is applied:

        - MIN → `"low"`
        - LOW → `"low"`
        - MED → `"high"`
        - HIGH → `"high"`

        This means unknown Gemini 3 models also have only two distinct
        observable levels: `"low"` and `"high"`.
      </unknown-gemini-3-model-fallback>
    </gemini-3-level-thinking>

    <thinking-validation order="4">
      Before a request is built, a thinking level can be validated for a
      given model:

      - If the model identifier is null: validation fails with an error.
      - For level MIN:
        - If the model is Gemini 2.5 and cannot disable thinking (minimum
          budget > 0): validation fails with an error describing that the
          minimum budget is positive.
        - Otherwise: validation succeeds.
      - For levels LOW, MED, HIGH:
        - If the model does not support thinking (series classified as other):
          validation fails with an error naming the unsupported model.
        - Otherwise: validation succeeds.

      Validation is purely advisory; the runtime does not call it
      automatically before every request. It is exposed for use by higher
      layers that wish to report errors before attempting serialization.
    </thinking-validation>

    <thought-signature-handling order="5">
      Gemini 3 models produce a thought signature in their responses — an
      opaque value that must be injected into the first assistant message
      of the next request. The implementation scans assistant messages in
      reverse order to find the most recent stored thought signature.

      If found, the signature is prepended as the first part of the first
      assistant message's content array in the serialized request.

      <notable reason="only gemini-3 models trigger signature lookup">
        For non-Gemini-3 models, the thought signature lookup is skipped
        entirely. Even if a thought signature was stored from a previous
        Gemini 3 session, it is not included when the model is switched to
        a non-Gemini-3 model.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="tool result serialization uses reverse message scan">
        When serializing a tool result, the implementation scans backward
        through previous messages to find the function name matching the
        tool call ID. If no match is found, the tool call ID itself is
        used as the function name in the serialized response.
      </notable>
    </thought-signature-handling>

  </behavior>

</specification>
