<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Google Gemini Request Serialization">

  <topic-statement>
    The Google Gemini request serializer transforms a canonical LLM request into
    the Gemini API JSON format, assembling system instructions, message contents,
    tool definitions, tool configuration, and generation configuration, and also
    produces the URL and HTTP headers needed to deliver the request.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      System instruction serialization, message contents serialization, tool
      definition serialization including parameter schema cleanup, tool
      configuration serialization, generation configuration serialization
      including thinking configuration for Gemini 2.5 and Gemini 3, URL
      construction for streaming and non-streaming modes, and HTTP header
      construction.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Content block serialization">
      How individual message content blocks (text, thinking, tool call, tool
      result) are transformed into Gemini parts format is covered by the Google
      content serialization specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Thinking configuration">
      How thinking levels are translated into budgets or level strings per model
      is covered by the Google thinking configuration specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Streaming event processing">
      How the Gemini API response is parsed back into normalized stream events
      is covered by the Google streaming event processing specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Canonical request inputs consumed">
      <field name="system_prompt" type="text or null" note="serialized as systemInstruction; skipped when null or empty string" />
      <field name="messages" type="ordered array" note="serialized as contents array; each message contributes one content object" />
      <field name="model" type="text" note="used for series classification (Gemini 2.5 vs Gemini 3) and thinking support checks" />
      <field name="tool_count" type="integer" note="when zero, both tools and toolConfig sections are omitted entirely" />
      <field name="tools" type="array of tool definitions" note="each has name, description, and parameters JSON string" />
      <field name="tool_choice_mode" type="integer enumeration" note="0=AUTO, 1=NONE, 2=ANY; controls functionCallingConfig mode string" />
      <field name="max_output_tokens" type="integer" note="when greater than zero, emitted as maxOutputTokens in generationConfig" />
      <field name="thinking.level" type="enumeration" note="MIN/LOW/MED/HIGH; drives thinking configuration inclusion and value" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Serialized JSON structure">
      <field name="systemInstruction" type="object" note="present only when system prompt is non-null and non-empty; contains parts array with a single text part" />
      <field name="contents" type="array" note="always present; one object per message with role and parts" />
      <field name="tools" type="array" note="present only when tool_count > 0; wraps functionDeclarations array inside a single object" />
      <field name="toolConfig" type="object" note="present only when tool_count > 0; contains functionCallingConfig with mode string" />
      <field name="generationConfig" type="object" note="present only when maxOutputTokens > 0 or thinking config is needed; contains maxOutputTokens and optionally thinkingConfig" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <system-instruction-serialization order="1">
      When the system prompt is null or an empty string, no system instruction
      is added to the document and serialization continues normally.

      When the system prompt is non-null and non-empty, a "systemInstruction"
      key is added to the root object. Its value is an object with a single
      "parts" key whose value is an array containing one object. That object
      has a single "text" key set to the system prompt string.

      <notable reason="empty string skipped as well as null">
        Both a null system prompt and a zero-length system prompt string result
        in the systemInstruction key being absent from the output. Callers that
        pass an empty string get the same output as callers that pass null.
      </notable>
    </system-instruction-serialization>

    <contents-serialization order="2">
      All messages are serialized in order into a "contents" array on the root
      object. Each message produces one content object with a "role" string and
      a "parts" array. Role mapping and parts assembly are delegated to the
      content block serializer, which is invoked once per message.

      Before iterating messages, the thought signature for Gemini 3 models is
      located by scanning assistant messages in reverse order. If found, the
      signature string is preserved for injection into the first assistant
      message during parts serialization.

      The thought signature is resolved once before iteration begins and is
      passed unchanged to each message's parts serialization. Injection into
      the message body is determined by the content block serializer when it
      encounters the first assistant-role message.

      <notable reason="thought signature scoped to Gemini 3 only">
        The thought signature lookup is skipped entirely for non-Gemini-3
        models. The signature value passed to the content serializer is null
        when the model is not Gemini 3 or when no assistant message with a
        stored signature is found.
      </notable>
    </contents-serialization>

    <tool-definitions-serialization order="3">
      When tool_count is zero, no "tools" key is added to the root object.

      When tools are present, a "tools" array is added to the root object. The
      array contains a single object with a "functionDeclarations" key. The
      value of "functionDeclarations" is an array with one entry per tool.

      Each function declaration object contains:
      - "name": the tool name string
      - "description": the tool description string
      - "parameters": the parsed parameter schema as a JSON object

      The tool parameters are stored in canonical form as a JSON string. They
      are parsed into a live JSON object during serialization, then the
      "additionalProperties" key is removed from the top-level parameters
      object before embedding it in the declaration.

      <notable reason="additionalProperties removal is top-level only">
        The removal of "additionalProperties" is applied only to the top-level
        parameters object, not recursively to nested schema objects. Nested
        schemas that contain "additionalProperties" are left unchanged.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="single wrapper object in tools array">
        All function declarations are collected into one object containing
        "functionDeclarations". The "tools" array always contains exactly one
        such wrapper object, regardless of how many tools are present.
      </notable>
    </tool-definitions-serialization>

    <tool-configuration-serialization order="4">
      When tool_count is zero, no "toolConfig" key is added to the root object.

      When tools are present, a "toolConfig" object is added to the root
      object. It contains a "functionCallingConfig" object with a "mode" string
      mapped from the canonical tool choice mode:

      - 0 (auto) → "AUTO"
      - 1 (none) → "NONE"
      - 2 (required/any) → "ANY"
      - Any other value → "AUTO" (default fallback)

      <notable reason="toolConfig always accompanies tools">
        Tool configuration is absent if and only if tool_count is zero. It is
        never absent when tools are present, even if the mode is the default
        AUTO value.
      </notable>
    </tool-configuration-serialization>

    <generation-config-serialization order="5">
      A "generationConfig" object is added to the root object only when at
      least one of the following is true:
      - max_output_tokens is greater than zero
      - Thinking configuration must be included

      If neither condition holds, the generationConfig key is absent entirely.

      When present, the generationConfig object contains:

      <max-output-tokens order="1">
        When max_output_tokens is greater than zero, a "maxOutputTokens" integer
        field is added with that value. When max_output_tokens is zero or
        absent, the field is omitted.
      </max-output-tokens>

      <thinking-config order="2">
        Whether thinking configuration is included depends on model series:

        For Gemini 3 models: thinkingConfig is always included, regardless of
        thinking level, because Gemini 3 has no concept of "no thinking" — the
        lowest level is still an active thinking mode.

        For Gemini 2.5 models: thinkingConfig is included only when the
        thinking level is not MIN and the model supports thinking. At MIN level,
        no thinkingConfig is emitted (unless Gemini 3 logic applies).

        For all other models: thinkingConfig is never included.

        When thinkingConfig is included, the object always contains:
        - "includeThoughts": true (boolean, always present when thinkingConfig
          is emitted)

        Additionally:
        - For Gemini 2.5: a "thinkingBudget" integer field is added with the
          computed token budget for the given model and level. The budget value
          is omitted if the computed budget is negative (indicating the model
          is not in the table), though in practice Gemini 2.5 models in the
          table always return a non-negative budget.
        - For Gemini 3: a "thinkingLevel" string field is added with the
          level string for the given model and level.

        <notable reason="Gemini 3 always emits thinkingConfig regardless of level">
          Even when the user selects the lowest thinking level on a Gemini 3
          model, thinkingConfig with "includeThoughts": true and a thinkingLevel
          string is always emitted. The Gemini 3 API does not support omitting
          the thinking config entirely.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="includeThoughts always true when thinkingConfig present">
          The "includeThoughts" field is set to true unconditionally whenever
          thinkingConfig is included. There is no path that emits thinkingConfig
          with "includeThoughts": false.
        </notable>
      </thinking-config>
    </generation-config-serialization>

    <serialization-order order="6">
      The five components are assembled in a fixed order onto the root object:
      1. systemInstruction
      2. contents
      3. tools
      4. toolConfig
      5. generationConfig

      Each component is serialized and added independently. Failure in any
      component aborts serialization and returns a parse error result. On
      failure the partially built document is discarded.
    </serialization-order>

    <url-construction order="7">
      The endpoint URL is constructed from four inputs: base URL, model
      identifier, API key, and streaming flag.

      The URL format is:

        {base_url}/models/{model}:{method}?key={api_key}{alt_param}

      Where:
      - method is "streamGenerateContent" when streaming, "generateContent"
        when non-streaming
      - alt_param is "&amp;alt=sse" when streaming, empty string when
        non-streaming

      <notable reason="alt=sse appended after key parameter">
        The streaming alt parameter is appended after the API key query
        parameter with an ampersand separator, not as a separate query
        parameter with a question mark.
      </notable>
    </url-construction>

    <header-construction order="8">
      HTTP headers are constructed based on the streaming flag.

      For streaming requests, two headers are produced:
      - "Content-Type: application/json"
      - "Accept: text/event-stream"

      For non-streaming requests, one header is produced:
      - "Content-Type: application/json"

      The header array is null-terminated in both cases. The array length
      (excluding the null terminator) is 2 for streaming and 1 for
      non-streaming.
    </header-construction>

  </behavior>

</specification>
