<specification topic="Google Streaming Event Processing">

  <topic-statement>
    The Google streaming event processor translates Gemini SSE response parts
    into normalized stream events, handling text, thinking, function calls,
    tool ID generation, thought signature extraction, and finish reason mapping.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Part-type dispatch (text, thinking, function call), random tool call ID
      generation, finish reason string mapping, thought signature extraction,
      usage metadata extraction, and error status mapping.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Provider Serialization">
      How messages are serialized into the Google request format is covered
      by the provider serialization specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="SSE Parser">
      Raw SSE byte splitting and event framing are covered by the SSE parser
      specification. This topic processes already-parsed JSON event objects.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <tool-id-generation order="1">
      Google's API does not provide unique identifiers for tool calls. A
      22-character random identifier is generated for each tool call using
      the alphabet:
      ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZabcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz0123456789-_

      The random number generator is seeded with the current time once per
      process (on the first tool call). Subsequent IDs are generated without
      re-seeding.

      <notable reason="weak-randomness">
        IDs are generated with rand() seeded once at process startup. They
        are not cryptographically random and are not guaranteed to be unique
        across processes or across a large number of calls.
      </notable>
    </tool-id-generation>

    <finish-reason-mapping order="2">
      Google finishReason strings are mapped to internal finish reasons:
      - "STOP" → STOP
      - "MAX_TOKENS" → LENGTH
      - "SAFETY", "BLOCKLIST", "PROHIBITED_CONTENT", "IMAGE_SAFETY",
        "IMAGE_PROHIBITED_CONTENT", "RECITATION" → CONTENT_FILTER
      - "MALFORMED_FUNCTION_CALL", "UNEXPECTED_TOOL_CALL" → ERROR
      - All other values (including absent) → UNKNOWN
    </finish-reason-mapping>

    <thought-signature-extraction order="3">
      The thought signature is a provider-opaque value that accompanies
      Gemini 3 function call results. It is searched for in two locations
      in the response JSON:
      1. Directly on the response root object.
      2. Within candidates[0].

      If found in either location, the signature is serialized as a JSON
      object with key "thought_signature" and returned as a null-terminated
      string. If not found or the value is an empty string, null is returned.

      For performance, the signature search is only performed when the model
      uses the Gemini 3 series.
    </thought-signature-extraction>

    <parts-iteration order="4">
      Each streaming chunk contains a parts array within the response content.
      Parts are processed in order:

      <thinking-part order="1">
        A part with a "thought" field set to true is a thinking part. Any
        open tool call is ended before processing. The thinking flag is set.
        The part's text content is emitted as a THINKING_DELTA event.
      </thinking-part>

      <text-part order="2">
        A part with a text field and no "thought" flag is a text part. Any
        open tool call is ended before processing. If the previous part was
        a thinking part, the part index is incremented before emission. The
        text is emitted as a TEXT_DELTA event.
      </text-part>

      <function-call-part order="3">
        A part with a functionCall field is a tool invocation. If no tool
        call is currently open, a new tool call ID is generated, the function
        name is extracted, and a TOOL_CALL_START event is emitted. The
        function arguments are serialized from the parsed JSON object back to
        a string and emitted as a TOOL_CALL_DELTA event. The accumulated
        arguments string is updated by concatenation.

        On Gemini 3 models, a thoughtSignature field adjacent to the
        functionCall in the part is also extracted and stored alongside the
        tool call state.
      </function-call-part>
    </parts-iteration>

    <usage-metadata order="5">
      The final streaming chunk includes a usageMetadata object. The following
      fields are extracted:
      - promptTokenCount → input tokens
      - candidatesTokenCount → raw output tokens
      - thoughtsTokenCount → thinking tokens

      Output tokens are calculated as candidatesTokenCount minus
      thoughtsTokenCount (because thinking tokens are counted separately).
      The cachedContentTokenCount field is not used; cached token count is
      always reported as zero.

      After extracting usage, any open tool call is ended, and a DONE event
      is emitted with the finish reason and usage counts.
    </usage-metadata>

    <error-status-mapping order="6">
      In-stream error events contain a status string. These are mapped to
      error categories:
      - "UNAUTHENTICATED" → AUTH
      - "RESOURCE_EXHAUSTED" → RATE_LIMIT
      - "INVALID_ARGUMENT" → INVALID_ARG
      - All other values → UNKNOWN

      The error message and category are emitted as an ERROR stream event.
    </error-status-mapping>

  </behavior>

</specification>
