<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="History Persistence">

  <topic-statement>
    The history persistence system loads command history from a JSONL file at
    startup and appends new entries to that file when commands are submitted.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      File path resolution, directory creation, JSONL parsing and validation
      during load, capacity enforcement during load, entry formatting and
      writing during append, and graceful degradation on I/O errors.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="In-memory history">
      This specification covers the file I/O layer only. The in-memory history
      structure that receives loaded entries and supplies entries to be appended
      is covered in the Command History specification.

      <shared topic="Command History">
        The in-memory history structure maintains an ordered list up to a
        configured capacity. Loaded entries are submitted to it one by one in
        chronological order. If the number of valid entries in the file exceeds
        the capacity, only the most recent entries are submitted (oldest are
        discarded at load time before submission).
      </shared>
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="History file entry">
      <field name="cmd" type="text" note="the full command string exactly as submitted" />
      <field name="ts" type="text" note="UTC timestamp in ISO-8601 format: YYYY-MM-DDTHH:MM:SSZ" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="File format">
      <field name="encoding" type="text" note="JSONL (JSON Lines): one JSON object per line, terminated by a newline character" />
      <field name="path" type="text" note=".ikigai/history relative to the current working directory; not configurable" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <directory-management order="1">
      Before any file operation, the `.ikigai` directory is ensured to exist.

      If the directory already exists, no action is taken. If the path exists
      but is not a directory (e.g., it is a plain file), an error is returned.

      If the directory does not exist, it is created with permissions allowing
      owner read, write, and execute, and group and other read and execute
      (`0755`). If creation fails for any reason other than the directory having
      been created by another process between the existence check and the
      creation attempt, an error is returned. The race condition case — where
      the directory appears between the check and the creation — is treated as
      success.
    </directory-management>

    <loading order="2">
      History is loaded at startup by reading and parsing the history file.

      <file-not-found order="1">
        If the history file does not exist, an empty file is created at the
        history file path and loading completes with no entries. The empty file
        creation ensures that subsequent existence checks succeed.
      </file-not-found>

      <empty-file order="2">
        If the file exists but contains no bytes, loading completes with no
        entries. No entries are submitted to the in-memory structure.
      </empty-file>

      <line-by-line-parsing order="3">
        If the file contains data, it is read in full and split into lines at
        newline characters. Empty lines are silently skipped.

        Each non-empty line is parsed as JSON. If any of the following
        conditions applies, the line is skipped and a warning is recorded; no
        error is returned and parsing continues with the next line:

        The line is not valid JSON.

        The JSON root value is not an object.

        The JSON object does not contain a `cmd` field, or the `cmd` field's
        value is not a string.

        If the line is valid and the `cmd` field is a non-empty string, the
        command value is extracted. The `ts` field and any other fields are not
        examined and do not affect whether the line is accepted.

        <notable reason="ts field is never read">
          The timestamp field written during append is never read during load.
          It is present in the format but is entirely ignored by the parser.
        </notable>
      </line-by-line-parsing>

      <capacity-enforcement order="4">
        After all lines have been parsed, the collection of successfully
        extracted command strings is compared against the history capacity. If
        the number of valid entries exceeds the capacity, the oldest entries
        (those appearing earliest in the file) are discarded until the count
        equals the capacity. Only the most recent entries are submitted to the
        in-memory structure.

        Entries are submitted to the in-memory history in chronological order,
        oldest first, so that the most recently submitted command ends up as
        the most recent entry.
      </capacity-enforcement>

      <load-error-handling order="5">
        A failure to create the history directory, or a failure to read the
        file after it is known to exist, produces an error. In both cases, the
        calling system logs the error but continues operating without history
        from the file. The application does not abort.

        Individual malformed lines do not produce errors; they produce warnings.
        Loading always succeeds unless the file cannot be read at all.
      </load-error-handling>
    </loading>

    <appending order="3">
      A command string is appended to the history file each time a command is
      submitted.

      <entry-format order="1">
        The entry is formatted as a JSON object containing two fields: `cmd`
        holds the command string, and `ts` holds the current UTC time formatted
        as an ISO-8601 timestamp (`YYYY-MM-DDTHH:MM:SSZ`). The formatted object
        is written to the file followed by a newline character.
      </entry-format>

      <append-mode order="2">
        The file is opened in append mode. The formatted JSON line is written
        and the file is closed. No explicit flush or synchronization to disk is
        performed beyond what the operating system provides on close.

        <notable reason="not atomic">
          A process crash after the file is opened but before the write
          completes can produce a partial line at the end of the file. The
          partial line will be rejected as malformed JSON on the next load and
          will be silently skipped.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="no locking">
          No file locking is performed. If multiple processes append to the
          same history file simultaneously, the resulting file may contain
          entries in a non-chronological order relative to when they were
          submitted, but both entries will be present and parseable.
        </notable>
      </append-mode>

      <append-error-handling order="3">
        A failure to create the directory, open the file, format the entry, or
        write to the file produces an error. The calling system logs the error
        but continues operating. The in-memory history is not affected; only
        the file write is skipped.
      </append-error-handling>
    </appending>

  </behavior>

</specification>
