<specification topic="HTML Parsing Wrapper">

  <topic-statement>
    The HTML parsing wrapper exposes the HTML document parsing and document
    freeing operations through the link-seam mechanism so tests can substitute
    or intercept them.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The two wrapped HTML operations: parsing an in-memory HTML byte buffer into
      a document tree, and releasing a parsed document's memory. The build-mode
      selection between inline and weak-symbol form.
    </in-scope>
    <boundary name="Link-seam mechanism">
      The MOCKABLE attribute and the inline-vs-weak-symbol compilation strategy
      are shared infrastructure.
      <shared topic="Link Seam Wrappers">
        In release builds the wrappers are static inline; in debug builds they
        are weak symbols that tests can override.
      </shared>
    </boundary>
    <boundary name="HTML parsing library">
      The actual document parsing and tree construction are performed by an
      external HTML parsing library. This wrapper does not modify those behaviors.
    </boundary>
    <boundary name="Curl HTTP wrappers">
      The HTML parsing wrapper header explicitly includes the HTTP client wrapper
      header as a dependency, making the full HTTP wrapper surface available to
      any translation unit that includes this header. The HTTP wrappers themselves
      are documented separately.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <parse-html-buffer order="1">
      Parses an HTML document from a caller-supplied byte buffer. The caller
      provides the buffer, its size in bytes, a URL string used as the document's
      base URI, a character encoding name, and an integer options bitmask. Returns
      an opaque document handle on success, or null on failure. All arguments are
      forwarded to the underlying library unchanged; no preprocessing or validation
      occurs.
    </parse-html-buffer>

    <free-document order="2">
      Releases all memory associated with a parsed HTML document. Accepts the
      opaque document handle returned by the parse operation. Forwards the handle
      to the underlying library's free routine unchanged. Returns nothing. No
      null-check is performed before forwarding; passing null is undefined behavior
      inherited from the underlying library.
    </free-document>

    <umbrella-exclusion order="3">
      <notable reason="not included in the aggregation umbrella">
        This wrapper family is not pulled in by the master wrapper umbrella header.
        Translation units that require HTML parsing operations must include this
        header directly. Every other wrapper family is collected by the umbrella;
        this one is the sole exception.
      </notable>
    </umbrella-exclusion>

  </behavior>

</specification>
