<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="HTTP Multiplexer">

  <topic-statement>
    The HTTP multiplexer manages concurrent non-blocking HTTP requests by
    integrating a multi-handle HTTP client into the select-based event loop,
    driving requests to completion through repeated polling.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Request lifecycle (addition, polling, streaming callbacks, completion
      detection), file descriptor registration with select, timeout hints,
      response body accumulation, error categorization, and cleanup on
      cancellation or destruction.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="REPL event loop">
      How the event loop calls into the multiplexer at each iteration is
      covered by the REPL event loop specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Provider serialization">
      How request bodies and response bodies are formatted for specific LLM
      providers is handled by the provider implementations and is out of scope
      here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Request">
      <field name="URL" type="text" note="fully qualified HTTP or HTTPS endpoint" />
      <field name="method" type="text" note="HTTP method (GET, POST, etc.)" />
      <field name="headers" type="ordered list of text" note="HTTP request headers as name: value strings" />
      <field name="body" type="bytes or absent" note="request body for POST and similar methods; absent for GET" />
      <field name="streaming callback" type="function or null" note="invoked with each chunk of response data as it arrives; null if streaming is not needed" />
      <field name="completion callback" type="function" note="invoked once when the request finishes, with HTTP status, error information, and the full accumulated response body" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Completion result">
      <field name="outcome" type="enumeration" note="one of: success (2xx), client error (4xx), server error (5xx), network error" />
      <field name="HTTP status code" type="integer or absent" note="the HTTP response code; absent on network-level errors" />
      <field name="error message" type="text or null" note="human-readable description on failure; null on success" />
      <field name="response body" type="bytes" note="the complete accumulated response body; valid for the duration of the completion callback only" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <request-addition order="1">
      A request is submitted by supplying the URL, method, headers, optional
      body, and callbacks. The multiplexer initializes a new transfer handle,
      configures it with the supplied options, registers a write callback for
      incoming data, and adds it to the active transfer pool. An internal
      response buffer (initially 4,096 bytes, growing by doubling) is allocated
      for the request. The call returns immediately; the request is processed
      asynchronously on subsequent event loop iterations.
    </request-addition>

    <fd-set-registration order="2">
      Before each select call, the event loop queries the multiplexer for the
      file descriptors currently associated with active transfers and for a
      timeout hint (in milliseconds). The multiplexer populates the read, write,
      and exception FD sets by delegating to the underlying multi-handle
      interface. The event loop incorporates these sets into its select call and
      uses the minimum of the multiplexer's timeout hint and its own timeout.
    </fd-set-registration>

    <polling order="3">
      When select returns (either because an FD became ready or because the
      timeout expired), the event loop calls the multiplexer's perform
      operation. Perform advances all active transfers — reading socket data,
      parsing response headers, and invoking data callbacks — and returns a
      count of still-running transfers.
    </polling>

    <streaming-callback order="4">
      As response bytes arrive on the network, the write callback fires
      synchronously within the perform call. For each chunk:

      1. If a streaming callback was registered for the request, it is invoked
         with the chunk bytes. This allows the provider to process partial
         responses (for example, parsing server-sent events) without waiting
         for the full body.
      2. The bytes are appended to the request's response buffer, extending
         it by doubling capacity as needed. This produces a complete accumulated
         body regardless of whether a streaming callback is registered.

      <notable reason="accumulation is independent of streaming">
        The response body is always accumulated in full, even when a streaming
        callback is provided. The completion callback always receives the
        complete body.
      </notable>
    </streaming-callback>

    <completion-detection order="5">
      After each perform call, the multiplexer checks the transfer completion
      queue. For each completed transfer:

      1. The outcome is determined: 2xx responses are success; 4xx are client
         errors; 5xx are server errors; cURL-level failures (network timeouts,
         DNS errors, connection refused) are network errors.
      2. The completion callback is invoked with the outcome, HTTP status code
         (if available), error message (if applicable), and the accumulated
         response body.
      3. The transfer handle is removed from the pool and freed.
      4. The request's internal resources (response buffer, header list) are
         released.

      The completion callback must not assume the response body or error message
      remain valid after the callback returns.
    </completion-detection>

    <cancellation-and-cleanup order="6">
      When the multiplexer is destroyed or a cancel operation is invoked, all
      in-flight transfers are stopped:

      1. Each active transfer handle is removed from the multi-handle pool.
      2. Transfer-specific resources (response buffer, header list, body copy)
         are freed.
      3. If destroying (not just cancelling), the multi-handle itself is
         released.

      Completion callbacks are not invoked for cancelled transfers.
    </cancellation-and-cleanup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
