<specification topic="Input Action Dispatcher">

  <topic-statement>
    The input action dispatcher routes user input events to specialized
    handlers and manages scroll detection, completion state, and interrupt
    requests within the REPL.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Dispatching all 29 input action types to their respective handlers,
      scroll detection interception and buffered arrow flush, escape-key
      interrupt handling, and tool process interrupt with SIGTERM/SIGKILL
      escalation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Specialized Handlers">
      Text editing, completion cycling, history browsing, viewport scrolling,
      agent navigation, and LLM submission are handled by separate modules.
      This topic dispatches to them and propagates any errors they return.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input Parser">
      Raw bytes are parsed into input actions externally. This topic receives
      fully parsed actions.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <scroll-detection-pre-processing order="1">
      Arrow-up and arrow-down events are intercepted before main dispatch and
      passed to the scroll detector state machine along with the current
      CLOCK_MONOTONIC timestamp. The detector may:
      - Buffer the event (returning a signal that the caller is done — no
        further processing for this action)
      - Absorb the event as part of a mouse-scroll burst (same signal)
      - Classify it as a scroll-up or scroll-down and execute the corresponding
        viewport scroll action
      - Pass it through as a plain arrow key (continue to main dispatch)

      If the scroll detector is absent, arrow events fall through to main
      dispatch immediately.
    </scroll-detection-pre-processing>

    <pending-arrow-flush order="2">
      When any event other than arrow-up, arrow-down, or unknown arrives, the
      scroll detector's pending buffered arrow (if any) is flushed first. A
      flushed arrow-up triggers the arrow-up viewport action; a flushed
      arrow-down triggers the arrow-down viewport action. This occurs before
      the incoming event is processed.
    </pending-arrow-flush>

    <char-input order="3">
      If a completion is active and the character is a space, the completion
      is committed. Otherwise: any active history browsing is stopped, the
      viewport offset is reset to zero, the codepoint is inserted into the
      input buffer, and the completion context is updated with the new text.
    </char-input>

    <newline order="4">
      Delegated to the LLM action handler, which determines whether the input
      is a slash command or a regular user message and acts accordingly.
    </newline>

    <insert-newline order="5">
      The viewport offset is reset to zero and a literal newline is inserted
      into the input buffer without submitting.
    </insert-newline>

    <backspace-and-delete order="6">
      The viewport offset is reset to zero, the character before or after the
      cursor is removed, and the completion context is updated.
    </backspace-and-delete>

    <arrow-left-and-right order="7">
      Any active completion is dismissed. The viewport offset is reset to zero.
      The cursor moves one position in the input buffer.
    </arrow-left-and-right>

    <cursor-control-keys order="8">
      Ctrl+A, Ctrl+E, Ctrl+K, Ctrl+U, and Ctrl+W all reset the viewport
      offset to zero and then perform their respective input buffer operations:
      move to line start, move to line end, kill to line end, kill entire
      line, and delete word backward.
    </cursor-control-keys>

    <history-navigation order="9">
      Ctrl+P and Ctrl+N return success immediately with no action. These keys
      are reserved for future reverse-search functionality.
    </history-navigation>

    <ctrl-c order="10">
      An interrupt request is submitted for any in-flight operation, then the
      REPL quit flag is set to trigger graceful shutdown.
    </ctrl-c>

    <tab order="11">
      Delegated to the completion handler, which triggers or cycles completions.
    </tab>

    <escape order="12">
      The current agent state is read atomically. If the agent is in
      WAITING_FOR_LLM or EXECUTING_TOOL state, an interrupt request is
      submitted. If the agent is idle and a completion is active with an
      original input saved, the input buffer is restored to that original text
      before the completion is dismissed.
    </escape>

    <viewport-scrolling order="13">
      Arrow-up and arrow-down (after scroll detection pass-through), page-up,
      page-down, scroll-up, and scroll-down all delegate to the viewport
      action handlers.
    </viewport-scrolling>

    <agent-navigation order="14">
      Navigation-prev-sibling, navigation-next-sibling, navigation-parent,
      and navigation-child delegate to the agent tree navigation system.
    </agent-navigation>

    <unknown-input order="15">
      Returns success immediately with no action.
    </unknown-input>

    <interrupt-request order="16">
      Called from Ctrl+C and the escape key handler. The agent state is read
      atomically. If the agent is idle, nothing happens. Otherwise, the
      interrupt-requested flag is set on the agent. Then:

      <llm-cancellation order="1">
        If the agent is in WAITING_FOR_LLM state and the provider has a cancel
        operation, that operation is invoked to abort the in-flight HTTP stream.
      </llm-cancellation>

      <tool-process-termination order="2">
        If the agent is in EXECUTING_TOOL state and a child process PID is
        recorded, SIGTERM is sent to the entire process group. The system then
        polls every 100 milliseconds (up to 2000 milliseconds total) using a
        non-blocking wait. If the process has not exited after 2000
        milliseconds, SIGKILL is sent.
      </tool-process-termination>
    </interrupt-request>

    <multiline-scrollback-append order="17">
      A helper operation splits a multi-line string by newline characters and
      appends each resulting segment to the scrollback as a separate line.
      Empty segments at boundaries are included when they appear before the
      end of the string.
    </multiline-scrollback-append>

  </behavior>

</specification>
