<specification topic="Input Buffer Layout">

  <topic-statement>
    The input buffer layout system calculates and caches the number of physical
    terminal rows occupied by the input buffer's text content.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Computing physical line count from logical text lines and terminal width,
      with dirty-flag-based caching; display width calculation for UTF-8 text with
      ANSI escape sequence exclusion; layout invalidation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Input Buffer Text">
      This topic reads the current text content and byte length from the input buffer.
      It does not modify the text.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="ANSI Escape Sequence Skipping">
      This topic delegates ANSI CSI escape sequence detection to the ANSI parsing
      system to obtain a byte skip count for each sequence encountered.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <invalidate-layout order="1">
      The layout cache is marked dirty. Any subsequent call to ensure layout will
      trigger a full recalculation regardless of whether the terminal width has changed.
    </invalidate-layout>

    <ensure-layout order="2">
      The cached physical line count is updated to reflect the current text content
      and terminal width.

      <cache-check order="1">
        If the layout is not dirty and the cached terminal width equals the supplied
        terminal width, the operation returns immediately without recalculation.
      </cache-check>

      <empty-buffer order="2">
        If the text is empty (null or zero length), the physical line count is set
        to zero. The cached width is updated and the dirty flag is cleared.
      </empty-buffer>

      <line-scan order="3">
        The text is scanned one byte at a time. At each newline character or at the
        end of the text, the display width of the preceding segment (from the previous
        boundary to the current position) is computed, and the number of physical
        rows that segment occupies is added to a running total.

        <display-width-calculation order="1">
          Display width is calculated by iterating through the segment:

          - ANSI CSI escape sequences are detected and skipped entirely; they
            contribute zero width.
          - Each remaining UTF-8 codepoint is decoded. Invalid UTF-8 bytes are
            treated as one column each, and decoding advances by one byte.
          - Valid codepoints contribute their Unicode display width (as defined
            by the Unicode standard for terminal display), which may be 0, 1, or 2.

          The total display width of the segment is the sum of all column widths.
        </display-width-calculation>

        <physical-lines-per-segment order="2">
          Given a segment's display width and the terminal width:

          - A segment with zero byte length (an empty line, i.e. consecutive
            newlines or a leading newline) contributes exactly 1 physical row.
          - A segment with zero display width (contains only zero-width characters)
            contributes exactly 1 physical row.
          - Otherwise, the number of physical rows is the ceiling of
            (display_width / terminal_width), computed as integer division with
            rounding up: (display_width + terminal_width - 1) / terminal_width.

          <unreachable reason="terminal_width is always positive in all callers">
            If terminal_width is zero or negative, the segment contributes exactly
            1 physical row.
          </unreachable>
        </physical-lines-per-segment>
      </line-scan>

      <cache-update order="4">
        After all segments are processed, the total physical line count is stored
        in the cache. The cached terminal width is updated to the supplied width,
        and the dirty flag is cleared.
      </cache-update>
    </ensure-layout>

    <get-physical-lines order="3">
      Returns the cached physical line count. The returned value reflects the last
      completed call to ensure layout; no recalculation is performed.
    </get-physical-lines>

  </behavior>

</specification>
