<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Input Parser">

  <topic-statement>
    The keyboard input parser translates a stream of raw TTY bytes into semantic
    input actions one byte at a time, handling UTF-8 multibyte characters and ANSI
    escape sequences through two independent stateful sub-parsers.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      All 28 semantic action types, the byte routing decision tree, UTF-8 decoding
      with overlong and surrogate rejection, legacy control character mapping,
      printable ASCII fast path, escape sequence buffering and dispatch, legacy CSI
      arrow and tilde sequences, SGR mouse scroll sequences, CSI u protocol, shifted
      character translation via keyboard layout, and error recovery.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Action handling">
      What happens after an action is produced — cursor movement, history navigation,
      text insertion, etc. — is handled by the REPL action dispatcher and is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Key injection">
      Bytes injected programmatically by the key injection subsystem are fed to this
      same parser. Whether a byte originates from the TTY or from injection is
      indistinguishable at the parser level and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input action">
      <field name="type" type="enumeration" note="one of 28 semantic action types; see behavior section for the complete list" />
      <field name="codepoint" type="32-bit unsigned integer" note="the Unicode codepoint for the character action type only; zero for all other action types" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Parser state">
      <field name="escape buffer" type="byte array of 16 bytes" note="accumulates bytes of an in-progress escape sequence; indexed by escape length" />
      <field name="escape length" type="non-negative integer" note="number of bytes currently in the escape buffer" />
      <field name="in escape" type="boolean" note="true while collecting an escape sequence" />
      <field name="UTF-8 buffer" type="byte array of 4 bytes" note="accumulates bytes of an in-progress multibyte UTF-8 sequence" />
      <field name="UTF-8 length" type="non-negative integer" note="bytes accumulated so far for the current UTF-8 sequence" />
      <field name="UTF-8 expected" type="non-negative integer" note="total bytes required to complete the current UTF-8 sequence (2, 3, or 4)" />
      <field name="in UTF-8" type="boolean" note="true while collecting a multibyte UTF-8 sequence" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <semantic-actions order="1">
      The parser produces exactly one of 28 action types per byte. Most actions
      carry no payload. The character action carries a Unicode codepoint.

      Actions with no payload:
      - Newline (Enter key — submit the current line)
      - Insert newline (Shift/Ctrl/Alt+Enter — insert a newline without submitting)
      - Backspace
      - Delete (forward delete)
      - Arrow left, arrow right, arrow up, arrow down
      - Page up, page down
      - Scroll up, scroll down (mouse wheel)
      - Ctrl+A (move to line start)
      - Ctrl+C (interrupt)
      - Ctrl+E (move to line end)
      - Ctrl+K (kill to end of line)
      - Ctrl+N (next history entry)
      - Ctrl+P (previous history entry)
      - Ctrl+U (kill entire line)
      - Ctrl+W (delete word backward)
      - Tab (completion trigger)
      - Escape
      - Navigate to previous sibling agent (Ctrl+Left)
      - Navigate to next sibling agent (Ctrl+Right)
      - Navigate to parent agent (Ctrl+Up)
      - Navigate to child agent (Ctrl+Down)
      - Unknown (byte was valid but produced no semantic result, or sequence is incomplete)

      The character action carries a codepoint and represents a typeable Unicode
      character — printable ASCII or any valid non-control Unicode codepoint.
    </semantic-actions>

    <byte-routing order="2">
      Each byte received is routed through the following decision tree in strict order.
      Only one path executes per byte.

      1. If currently collecting a UTF-8 continuation sequence, attempt to append the
         byte as a continuation byte. See UTF-8 decoding.

      2. If currently collecting an escape sequence, dispatch the byte to the escape
         sequence parser. See escape sequence parsing.

      3. If the byte is `0x1B` (ESC), enter escape collection mode (escape length reset
         to zero, in-escape set to true) and return Unknown.

      4. If the byte matches a control character listed in the legacy control character
         table below, return the corresponding action immediately.

      5. If the byte is in the range `0x20`–`0x7E` inclusive, return a character action
         with the byte value as the codepoint (printable ASCII fast path). Exception:
         byte `0x7F` (DEL) is treated as Backspace, not a printable character.

      6. If the byte is a UTF-8 lead byte (`0xC0`–`0xF7`), enter UTF-8 collection mode.
         See UTF-8 decoding.

      7. All other bytes produce Unknown with no state change.
    </byte-routing>

    <legacy-control-characters order="3">
      The following byte values map directly to actions without entering any state
      machine:

      - `0x01` → Ctrl+A
      - `0x03` → Ctrl+C
      - `0x05` → Ctrl+E
      - `0x09` → Tab
      - `0x0A` → Insert newline
      - `0x0B` → Ctrl+K
      - `0x0D` → Newline
      - `0x0E` → Ctrl+N
      - `0x10` → Ctrl+P
      - `0x15` → Ctrl+U
      - `0x17` → Ctrl+W
      - `0x7F` → Backspace

      All other byte values in the ranges `0x00`–`0x08`, `0x0C`, `0x0F`–`0x12`,
      `0x13`–`0x14`, `0x16`, `0x18`–`0x1A` produce Unknown.
    </legacy-control-characters>

    <utf8-decoding order="4">
      UTF-8 multibyte sequences are decoded incrementally. Lead bytes are recognized
      by bit pattern:

      - `110xxxxx` (range `0xC0`–`0xDF`): 2-byte sequence
      - `1110xxxx` (range `0xE0`–`0xEF`): 3-byte sequence
      - `11110xxx` (range `0xF0`–`0xF7`): 4-byte sequence

      When a lead byte is detected, UTF-8 collection mode is entered: the byte is
      stored, the expected total is set (2, 3, or 4), and Unknown is returned.

      Each subsequent byte is tested as a continuation byte: it must match the
      pattern `10xxxxxx` (value in `0x80`–`0xBF`). If the pattern does not match,
      UTF-8 mode is exited immediately and Unknown is returned; the offending byte
      is discarded without being re-processed.

      When the collected byte count reaches the expected total, the codepoint is
      assembled by extracting the data bits from each byte. The assembled codepoint
      is then validated:

      - Overlong encodings (a 2-byte encoding of a codepoint below U+0080, a 3-byte
        encoding below U+0800, or a 4-byte encoding below U+10000) produce U+FFFD
        (replacement character) instead of the encoded value.
      - UTF-16 surrogate codepoints (U+D800 through U+DFFF) produce U+FFFD.
      - Codepoints above U+10FFFF produce U+FFFD.

      All valid or replaced codepoints are returned as a character action. UTF-8
      collection mode is then exited.

      <notable reason="invalid continuation byte discards the byte">
        When a non-continuation byte is received while in UTF-8 mode, only the mode
        is reset — the bad byte is not reprocessed. It is silently discarded, and the
        next byte is treated as the start of a new sequence.
      </notable>
    </utf8-decoding>

    <escape-sequence-parsing order="5">
      When the ESC byte (`0x1B`) is received outside of escape mode, the parser
      enters escape collection mode and returns Unknown. Subsequent bytes are
      appended to the escape buffer (up to 15 bytes). On each byte, the buffer is
      tested against the patterns below in order. When a pattern matches completely,
      the corresponding action is returned and escape mode is exited.

      <first-byte order="1">
        The first byte after ESC determines the sequence class:

        - `[` (0x5B): begins a CSI sequence; continue collecting.
        - ESC (`0x1B`): a second consecutive ESC produces the Escape action and
          exits escape mode.
        - Any other byte: exit escape mode and return Unknown.

        <notable reason="bare ESC key is not recognized via legacy sequences">
          A bare ESC byte followed by nothing (or by a non-recognized byte) does not
          produce the Escape action. The Escape action is produced only by a double
          ESC or by the CSI u encoding `ESC [ 27 ; 1 u`. Terminals that send a bare
          ESC for the Escape key are not supported without using CSI u mode.
        </notable>
      </first-byte>

      <legacy-arrow-keys order="2">
        Four 3-byte sequences `ESC [ A`, `ESC [ B`, `ESC [ C`, `ESC [ D`
        (final bytes 0x41–0x44) map to arrow up, down, right, and left respectively.
      </legacy-arrow-keys>

      <modified-arrow-keys order="3">
        Sequences of the form `ESC [ 1 ; N A/B/C/D` carry a modifier number N.
        The NumLock bit (bit 7, value 128) is masked off before interpreting N.
        Only modifier 5 (Ctrl) is handled; it maps the four arrow directions to
        the four agent-navigation actions (Ctrl+Up/Down/Left/Right). All other
        modifier values produce Unknown.
      </modified-arrow-keys>

      <mouse-scroll-sgr order="4">
        Sequences beginning with `ESC [ <` and ending with `M` (press) are parsed
        as SGR mouse sequences. The button number is extracted from the parameter
        before the first semicolon. Button 64 produces scroll up; button 65 produces
        scroll down. All other SGR mouse sequences produce Unknown.
      </mouse-scroll-sgr>

      <tilde-sequences order="5">
        Selected sequences ending with `~` or matching specific Home/End forms map
        to actions:

        - `ESC [ H` and `ESC [ 1 ~` and `ESC [ 1 ; N H` → Ctrl+A (line start)
        - `ESC [ F` and `ESC [ 4 ~` and `ESC [ 1 ; N F` → Ctrl+E (line end)
        - `ESC [ 3 ~` → Delete
        - `ESC [ 5 ~` → Page up
        - `ESC [ 6 ~` → Page down

        Modifier values in Home/End sequences are accepted but not further
        distinguished; they all map to the same line-boundary action.
      </tilde-sequences>

      <csi-u-protocol order="6">
        Sequences of the form `ESC [ keycode ; modifiers u` implement the CSI u
        keyboard protocol. The keycode and modifiers are parsed as decimal integers.
        The NumLock bit (bit 7) is masked off the modifier before use.

        Modifier values:
        - 1: no modifier
        - 2: Shift
        - 5: Ctrl

        Keycode/modifier combinations and their actions:

        - 13 / 1 → Newline
        - 13 / 2, 3, 5, 6 → Insert newline
        - 9 / 1 → Tab
        - 27 / 1 → Escape
        - 127 / 1 → Backspace
        - 97 / 5 → Ctrl+A
        - 99 / 5 → Ctrl+C
        - 101 / 5 → Ctrl+E
        - 107 / 5 → Ctrl+K
        - 110 / 5 → Ctrl+N
        - 112 / 5 → Ctrl+P
        - 117 / 5 → Ctrl+U
        - 119 / 5 → Ctrl+W
        - 32–126 / 1 → Character action with the keycode as codepoint
        - 32–126 / 2 → Character action with the shifted translation of the keycode
        - Any keycode above 50000 → Unknown
        - All other combinations → Unknown

        For shifted characters (modifier 2, keycode 32–126), a keyboard layout
        lookup is performed to determine what character would be produced by pressing
        that key with Shift held. If the lookup fails for any reason (layout not
        available, keycode not found, result codepoint is zero), the original keycode
        is returned as the codepoint unchanged.
      </csi-u-protocol>

      <discardable-sequences order="7">
        Sequences that end with `m` (SGR color and style codes) are silently discarded;
        they produce Unknown. Certain short tilde sequences not listed in the tilde
        table above are also silently discarded. These are recognized so that terminal
        color output interleaved with key sequences does not leave the parser in a
        permanently stuck escape state.
      </discardable-sequences>

      <escape-buffer-overflow order="8">
        If 15 bytes have been collected in the escape buffer and no recognized
        sequence has terminated, the next byte triggers overflow handling: the
        escape buffer is reset, escape mode is exited, and Unknown is returned.
        No bytes are processed after the overflow; the overflowing byte is discarded.
      </escape-buffer-overflow>
    </escape-sequence-parsing>

    <state-independence order="6">
      The escape sub-parser and the UTF-8 sub-parser are mutually exclusive at
      runtime: the byte routing decision tree checks in-UTF-8 mode first. In
      practice, a valid terminal will never interleave UTF-8 continuation bytes with
      escape sequences, so this ordering produces correct results without any explicit
      conflict detection.
    </state-independence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
