<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Input Buffer">

  <topic-statement>
    The input buffer stores UTF-8 text entered by the user, tracks a cursor
    position within that text, and computes the display layout needed to render
    the text correctly across wrapped terminal lines.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Text storage and growth, codepoint insertion and deletion, cursor position
      as a dual byte-and-grapheme representation, word-level deletion, line-level
      navigation and deletion, multi-line vertical movement with column
      preservation, display width calculation with ANSI sequence exclusion,
      physical-line count calculation, and layout cache invalidation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Rendering">
      How the input buffer's text and cursor position are drawn to the terminal
      is handled by the input layer renderer and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Action dispatcher">
      What user input triggers which editing operation is decided by the action
      dispatcher and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input buffer">
      <field name="text" type="dynamic byte array" note="UTF-8 encoded character data; all inserted content is valid UTF-8" />
      <field name="length" type="non-negative integer" note="number of bytes currently in the text array, not counting any null terminator" />
      <field name="cursor byte offset" type="non-negative integer" note="byte position of the cursor within the text array; authoritative for text manipulation" />
      <field name="cursor grapheme offset" type="non-negative integer" note="count of Unicode grapheme clusters from the start of the text to the cursor; authoritative for display and navigation semantics" />
      <field name="target column" type="non-negative integer" note="grapheme column preserved across vertical cursor movements; reset to zero by any horizontal movement" />
      <field name="layout dirty" type="boolean" note="true when the cached physical line count is stale and must be recomputed" />
      <field name="cached physical lines" type="non-negative integer" note="number of terminal rows the text occupies at the cached terminal width; valid only when layout is not dirty" />
      <field name="cached terminal width" type="positive integer" note="terminal column width used for the most recent physical-line calculation" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <text-storage order="1">
      Text is stored in a dynamically allocated byte array. The array grows
      as characters are inserted; it never shrinks. All text stored in the
      buffer is guaranteed to be valid UTF-8 — the insert operations encode
      each codepoint to UTF-8 before appending, so no runtime validation is
      performed on reads.
    </text-storage>

    <insertion order="2">
      A Unicode codepoint is inserted at the current cursor position by encoding
      it to its 1–4 byte UTF-8 representation and inserting those bytes at the
      cursor's byte offset. A newline character is inserted as a single byte.
      After insertion, the cursor advances by the number of bytes inserted, the
      cursor's grapheme offset is resynchronized, and the layout cache is
      invalidated.
    </insertion>

    <backspace-deletion order="3">
      Backspace deletes the complete UTF-8 character immediately before the
      cursor. The operation scans backward from the cursor's byte position to
      find the boundary of the preceding character (skipping UTF-8 continuation
      bytes), removes all of that character's bytes, and moves the cursor to
      where the deleted character began. If the cursor is at position zero,
      backspace is a no-op. The layout cache is invalidated on any deletion.
    </backspace-deletion>

    <forward-deletion order="4">
      Forward delete removes the complete UTF-8 character at the cursor
      position. The character's byte length is determined by its leading byte,
      and all bytes are removed. The cursor does not move — it now points to
      the character that immediately followed the deleted one. If the cursor is
      at or past the end of the text, this is a no-op.
    </forward-deletion>

    <word-deletion order="5">
      Word deletion removes the word immediately before the cursor, implementing
      standard Ctrl+W semantics. The operation:

      1. Skips whitespace bytes backward from the cursor.
      2. Identifies the character class of the first non-whitespace byte
         (alphanumeric, or punctuation / other).
      3. Deletes backward through all consecutive bytes of the same class.

      Character classes are: alphanumeric (ASCII letters and digits), whitespace
      (space, tab, newline, carriage return), and all other bytes (including
      multi-byte UTF-8 leading bytes, which are treated as alphanumeric for
      this purpose). The cursor is moved to the deletion boundary.
    </word-deletion>

    <cursor-representation order="6">
      The cursor is maintained as two synchronized values: a byte offset for
      text manipulation and a grapheme offset for display and navigation. The
      byte offset is the primary value for all text operations. After any
      operation that changes the byte offset, the grapheme offset is
      resynchronized by counting Unicode grapheme clusters from the start of
      the buffer to the new byte position.

      Grapheme cluster boundaries are determined by Unicode standard grapheme
      break rules. A base character and its combining diacritics form a single
      grapheme; independent characters each form their own grapheme.
    </cursor-representation>

    <horizontal-cursor-movement order="7">
      Moving the cursor left positions it at the immediately preceding grapheme
      boundary. Moving right positions it at the next grapheme boundary. Both
      directions are no-ops at their respective boundaries (start and end of
      text). Either movement resets the target column to zero.
    </horizontal-cursor-movement>

    <line-navigation order="8">
      The buffer supports navigation to logical line boundaries defined by
      newline characters:

      - **Line start**: moves the cursor to the byte position immediately after
        the preceding newline, or to zero for the first line.
      - **Line end**: moves the cursor to the byte position of the next newline,
        or to the text length if none follows. The newline itself is excluded
        from the position.

      Both operations reset the target column.

      <notable reason="line-end excludes the newline byte">
        Positioning at line end places the cursor before the newline, not after
        it. Pressing right from line end moves to the next line's start.
      </notable>
    </line-navigation>

    <vertical-cursor-movement order="9">
      Moving the cursor up or down preserves the user's intended column across
      lines of differing lengths.

      On the first vertical movement, the current grapheme column is stored as
      the target column. Subsequent vertical movements aim for that stored
      target column in the destination line. If the destination line is shorter
      than the target column, the cursor is placed at the line end.

      Any horizontal movement (left, right, line-start, line-end, or word
      deletion) resets the target column to zero, so the next vertical movement
      establishes a fresh target.
    </vertical-cursor-movement>

    <line-deletion order="10">
      Two line-deletion operations are supported:

      - **Kill line**: deletes the entire current line, including its newline
        character. The cursor moves to where the line began. If the buffer
        becomes empty, the cursor is at position zero.
      - **Kill to end of line**: deletes from the cursor to (but not including)
        the newline. If the cursor is already at line end, this is a no-op.

      Both operations invalidate the layout cache.
    </line-deletion>

    <layout-calculation order="11">
      The buffer computes how many physical (wrapped) terminal rows its text
      occupies at a given terminal width. The calculation:

      1. Splits the text at newline characters into logical lines.
      2. For each logical line, computes the display width by walking the UTF-8
         text and summing per-codepoint display widths (0, 1, or 2 columns)
         while skipping ANSI escape sequences entirely.
      3. For each logical line, computes the physical row count as the ceiling
         of display width divided by terminal width, with a minimum of one row
         per logical line.
      4. Sums the per-line physical row counts.

      An empty buffer (no text) has zero physical lines.

      <notable reason="ANSI sequences occupy no visual space">
        ANSI color and formatting sequences embedded in the text are skipped
        during display-width measurement so they do not inflate the computed
        row count.
      </notable>
    </layout-calculation>

    <layout-cache order="12">
      The physical line count is cached alongside the terminal width at which
      it was computed. The cache is invalidated whenever text is modified (set
      dirty). On the next call that requires the layout, if the cache is dirty
      or the terminal width has changed, the layout is recomputed and the cache
      is updated.

      Callers that change the terminal width should recompute after resizing;
      the cache detects the mismatch automatically.
    </layout-cache>

    <clear-operation order="13">
      Clearing the buffer sets the text length to zero, resets the cursor to
      position zero, resets the target column, and invalidates the layout cache.
      Allocated memory is not released — the buffer retains its capacity for
      future input.
    </clear-operation>

    <error-handling order="14">
      Memory allocation failures during text buffer growth cause an immediate
      process abort. Navigation and editing operations at boundaries (cursor at
      start or end, empty buffer) are silent no-ops and never return errors.
    </error-handling>

  </behavior>

</specification>
