<specification topic="Input Layer Rendering">

  <topic-statement>
    The input layer renders the agent's text input buffer as terminal rows,
    preserving newlines and reserving cursor space when the buffer is empty.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Visibility determination from an external flag, height calculation by
      scanning text bytes with column tracking, and rendering that converts
      newlines to terminal row endings and appends a trailing clear-to-EOL
      sequence.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Input Buffer">
      The text content, its byte length, and the visibility flag are managed
      by the REPL context. This layer stores raw non-owning pointers to live
      REPL state and reads them at each call.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Layer Protocol">
      How the layer's visibility, height, and render functions are invoked by
      the rendering pipeline is covered by the Layer Rendering specification.
      This topic covers only the implementations of those three functions for
      the input layer.

      <shared topic="Layer Rendering">
        The rendering pipeline calls the visibility predicate once per frame.
        If it returns false, height and render are not called. If true, height
        is called to measure the layer, and render is called with a terminal
        width, a zero-indexed start row within the layer, and a row count.
      </shared>
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="External State (accessed via live raw pointers)">
      <field name="visible flag" type="boolean" note="controls layer visibility; read via pointer at each visibility check" />
      <field name="text pointer" type="pointer to string" note="the input buffer text; read via pointer at each height and render call" />
      <field name="text length" type="non-negative integer" note="byte length of the text; read via pointer at each height and render call" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <visibility order="1">
      The layer is visible when the external boolean flag is true. It is
      invisible when the flag is false.
    </visibility>

    <height-calculation order="2">
      When the text length is zero, the height is 1. A single row is always
      reserved to provide space for cursor placement, even with no text.

      When the text length is non-zero, the height is computed by scanning
      each byte of the text in order, tracking physical rows and a current
      column position. Both counters start at 1 and 0 respectively.

      For each byte:
      - If the byte is a newline character (\n): the physical row count is
        incremented by one, and the column position is reset to zero.
      - For any other byte: the column position is incremented by one. If the
        column position equals or exceeds the terminal width, the physical row
        count is incremented by one and the column position is reset to zero.

      The final physical row count is returned as the height.

      <notable reason="byte-level column counting">
        Each non-newline byte increments the column counter by exactly one,
        regardless of the byte's role in a multi-byte sequence. Multi-byte
        UTF-8 characters are counted as multiple columns, not one. ANSI escape
        sequences are also counted byte-by-byte, inflating the column count
        for styled text.
      </notable>
    </height-calculation>

    <rendering order="3">
      The width, start_row, and row_count parameters are accepted by the render
      function but none of them are used in any part of the output.

      <notable reason="render parameters ignored">
        The render function's width, start_row, and row_count parameters are
        all discarded. The full text is always rendered from byte zero,
        regardless of viewport clipping parameters.
      </notable>

      <empty-buffer order="1">
        When the text length is zero, the ANSI erase-to-end-of-line sequence
        (ESC[K) followed by carriage-return and line-feed (\r\n) is appended
        to the output. This produces a single blank row that preserves the
        cursor's visual position.
      </empty-buffer>

      <non-empty-buffer order="2">
        When the text length is non-zero, each byte is processed in order:
        - A newline character (\n) is replaced by the ANSI erase-to-end-of-line
          sequence (ESC[K) followed by carriage-return and line-feed (\r\n).
        - Any other byte is output verbatim as a single byte.

        After all bytes have been processed, if the last byte of the text is
        not a newline, the ANSI erase-to-end-of-line sequence (ESC[K) followed
        by carriage-return and line-feed (\r\n) is appended to terminate the
        final partial row.

        <notable reason="no padding or truncation">
          Lines wider than the terminal width are not truncated, and lines
          shorter than the terminal width are not padded. The ESC[K sequence
          erases any stale content from the cursor to the end of the terminal
          line, which serves as implicit right-side clearing without adding
          spaces.
        </notable>
      </non-empty-buffer>

    </rendering>

  </behavior>

</specification>
