<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Internal Tool Registration">

  <topic-statement>
    The internal tool registration process installs the four built-in
    agent-communication tools — fork, kill, send, and wait — into the shared
    tool registry using hardcoded JSON schemas.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The JSON schema definitions for each built-in tool, the sequence and
      method by which schemas are parsed and tools are added to the registry,
      and the association between each tool name and its handler and
      completion hook.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Registry">
      The registry's storage and lookup behavior is managed by the tool
      registry subsystem. This topic only populates the registry; it does
      not define how tools are retrieved or dispatched.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool Handlers">
      The execution logic for each tool (fork handler, kill handler, send
      handler, wait handler) is implemented separately. This topic wires the
      associations but does not define the handler behaviors.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Shared Initialization">
      Registration is triggered by the shared context initialization and the
      registry refresh command. Those callers are out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>

    <contract name="Fork Tool Schema">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="'fork'" />
      <field name="description" type="text" note="instructs the LLM that this creates a child agent with a specific task, inheriting parent history, working independently with its own LLM stream" />
      <field name="parameters.name" type="string" note="required; short human-readable label for the child agent" />
      <field name="parameters.prompt" type="string" note="required; the task for the child agent to work on" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Kill Tool Schema">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="'kill'" />
      <field name="description" type="text" note="instructs the LLM that this terminates an agent and all its descendants, returning a list of killed UUIDs" />
      <field name="parameters.uuid" type="string" note="required; UUID of the agent to terminate, described as cascading to all descendants" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Send Tool Schema">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="'send'" />
      <field name="description" type="text" note="instructs the LLM that this sends a message to another agent retrievable with the wait tool" />
      <field name="parameters.to" type="string" note="required; UUID of the recipient agent, described as 'must be running'" />
      <field name="parameters.message" type="string" note="required; message content to send" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Wait Tool Schema">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="'wait'" />
      <field name="description" type="text" note="instructs the LLM that this waits for messages from other agents, supporting next-message and fan-in modes" />
      <field name="parameters.timeout" type="number" note="required; maximum seconds to wait; 0 for non-blocking instant check" />
      <field name="parameters.from_agents" type="array of string" note="optional; specific agent UUIDs for fan-in mode; omit to wait for next message from anyone" />
    </contract>

  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <registration-sequence order="1">
      Registration parses all four schemas and registers all four tools in a
      fixed sequence: fork, kill, send, wait. The sequence is:

      1. A temporary allocation context is created to hold schema string buffers
         during parsing.
      2. For each of the four tools, the hardcoded JSON schema string is copied
         into the temporary context and parsed into an in-memory JSON document.
         The JSON allocator used for parsing is backed by the registry's own
         allocation context, so the parsed documents are owned by the registry.
         If parsing fails, the process panics immediately.
      3. Each tool is registered with the registry under its name, with its
         parsed schema document, its handler, and its completion hook (if any).
         If registration fails, the process panics immediately.
      4. The temporary allocation context is freed, releasing the schema string
         buffers. The parsed documents are unaffected because they were allocated
         under the registry context.

      <notable reason="panic on any failure">
        All failure paths during registration — schema parse failure, registry
        add failure — terminate the process via panic. There is no partial
        registration or graceful degradation.
      </notable>
    </registration-sequence>

    <completion-hooks order="2">
      Two of the four tools have completion hooks that run on the main thread
      after the tool handler returns from the background tool thread:

      - The fork tool has a completion hook that transfers the newly created
        child agent from the tool thread's allocation context into the REPL's
        agent array.
      - The kill tool has a completion hook that sets the dead flag on the
        corresponding in-memory agent entry.
      - The send tool has no completion hook.
      - The wait tool has no completion hook.

      <notable reason="kill schema describes cascade; kill handler does not cascade">
        The kill tool's schema description tells the LLM that termination
        "cascades to all descendants." The actual handler only terminates the
        directly named agent without cascading to any descendants. The "killed"
        array in the result always contains exactly one UUID.
      </notable>
    </completion-hooks>

    <schema-ownership order="3">
      Schema JSON documents are allocated using a talloc-backed JSON allocator
      that attaches all allocations to the registry's context. This means the
      documents live for the lifetime of the registry and are freed when the
      registry is destroyed. The schema string buffers used during parsing are
      owned by the temporary context and are freed immediately after registration
      completes.
    </schema-ownership>

  </behavior>

</specification>
