<specification topic="Internal Function Wrappers">

  <topic-statement>
    The internal function wrappers expose a fixed set of application-internal
    operations through the link-seam mechanism so tests can inject failures or
    substitute behavior without modifying production code.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The seventeen internal application operations exposed as link seams, the
      void-pointer type erasure used in debug-mode declarations, the build-mode
      selection between inline (release) and weak-symbol (debug) form, and the
      transparent passthrough contract for each wrapped call.
    </in-scope>
    <boundary name="Link-seam mechanism">
      The MOCKABLE attribute and the build-mode dispatch strategy are shared
      infrastructure.
      <shared topic="Link Seam Wrappers">
        In release builds the wrappers are static inline and carry their concrete
        type casts inline. In debug builds they are weak symbols whose declarations
        use void pointers to avoid pulling application headers into consumer
        translation units.
      </shared>
    </boundary>
    <boundary name="Wrapped operations">
      Each wrapper forwards to the real implementation. The semantics of paths
      translation, database operations, scrollback, REPL rendering, agent state
      transitions, request building, HTTP multiplexing, tool execution, template
      processing, and token counting are documented in separate specifications for
      those subsystems.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Type erasure in debug declarations">
      <field name="structured context arguments" type="void*" note="opaque pointers in the debug-mode header declarations; cast to concrete types inside the .c implementation" />
      <field name="structured context arguments" type="concrete pointer" note="fully typed in the release-mode inline definitions; no casting visible to callers" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <type-erasure-strategy order="1">
      In debug builds, the wrapper declarations in the header use generic opaque
      pointer types in place of the concrete structured types. This avoids
      requiring consumers of the wrapper header to also include the full set of
      application domain headers. The .c implementation file includes the concrete
      headers and performs the type cast internally before forwarding to the real
      function.

      In release builds, the inline definitions include the concrete headers and
      carry the casts directly, so callers see the full types and no erasure occurs.

      <notable reason="asymmetric type visibility">
        A test that calls a wrapper in debug mode sees a void pointer signature,
        while production code compiled in release mode sees a fully typed
        signature. The two compilation modes present different call sites to the
        compiler.
      </notable>
    </type-erasure-strategy>

    <uri-translation-seams order="2">
      Two path-translation operations are wrapped: converting an application-scheme
      URI to a filesystem path, and converting a filesystem path to an
      application-scheme URI. Both accept an allocator context, an opaque paths
      configuration handle, an input string, and an output string pointer. Both
      return a result value. All arguments are forwarded unchanged after casting
      the opaque handle to the concrete type.
    </uri-translation-seams>

    <external-tool-execution-seam order="3">
      The external tool execution operation is wrapped. It accepts an allocator
      context, a tool path string, an agent identifier string, a JSON arguments
      string, an output pointer for the child process ID, and an output pointer for
      the result string. Returns a result value. All arguments are forwarded
      unchanged.
    </external-tool-execution-seam>

    <database-seams order="4">
      Two database operations are wrapped.

      Database initialization accepts an allocator context, a connection string,
      a data directory path, and an output pointer for the opaque database context.
      Returns a result value.

      Message insertion accepts an opaque database context handle, a session
      identifier, an agent UUID string, a message kind string, a content string,
      and a JSON data string. Returns a result value.

      Both forward all arguments unchanged after casting the opaque handle.
    </database-seams>

    <scrollback-seam order="5">
      The scrollback line-append operation is wrapped. It accepts an opaque
      scrollback handle, a text buffer, and a byte length. Returns a result value.
      All arguments are forwarded unchanged after casting.
    </scrollback-seam>

    <repl-rendering-seam order="6">
      The REPL frame rendering operation is wrapped. It accepts an opaque REPL
      context handle and returns a result value. The handle is cast to the concrete
      type and forwarded.
    </repl-rendering-seam>

    <agent-provider-seam order="7">
      The agent provider retrieval operation is wrapped. It accepts an opaque
      agent handle and an output pointer for the opaque provider handle. Returns a
      result value. Both handles are cast to concrete types internally.
    </agent-provider-seam>

    <request-building-seam order="8">
      The request build operation is wrapped. It accepts an allocator context, an
      opaque agent handle, an opaque tool registry handle, and an output pointer
      for the opaque request handle. Returns a result value. All opaque handles
      are cast to concrete types internally.
    </request-building-seam>

    <http-multi-seams order="9">
      Two HTTP multiplexer operations are wrapped.

      The creation operation accepts a parent allocator context and an output
      pointer. The underlying call returns a result value; when that result
      indicates success, the ok field of the result is written to the output
      pointer before the result is returned. This means the caller receives the
      created handle via the output pointer rather than directly from the result
      value.

      The info-read operation accepts an opaque HTTP multiplexer handle and an
      opaque logger handle. It returns nothing. Both handles are cast to concrete
      types internally.

      <notable reason="result unpacking in the http-multi-create wrapper">
        The HTTP multi creation wrapper unpacks the result's ok pointer into a
        separate out-parameter, diverging from the raw underlying function
        signature. All other wrappers forward their result values without
        modification.
      </notable>
    </http-multi-seams>

    <agent-tool-loop-seams order="10">
      Three operations supporting the tool execution loop are wrapped.

      Starting tool execution accepts an opaque agent handle and returns nothing.

      Querying whether the loop should continue accepts a const opaque agent handle
      and returns an integer (nonzero means continue, zero means stop).

      Submitting a tool loop continuation accepts an opaque REPL context handle and
      an opaque agent handle and returns nothing.

      All three forward their arguments unchanged after casting.
    </agent-tool-loop-seams>

    <agent-state-seams order="11">
      Two agent state-management operations are wrapped.

      Message addition accepts an opaque agent handle and an opaque message handle.
      Returns a result value. Both handles are cast to concrete types internally.

      Transitioning the agent to idle accepts an opaque agent handle and returns
      nothing. The handle is cast to the concrete type internally.
    </agent-state-seams>

    <template-processing-seam order="12">
      The template processing operation is wrapped. It accepts an allocator
      context, a template text string, an opaque agent handle, an opaque
      configuration handle, and an output pointer for the opaque result handle.
      Returns a result value. All opaque handles are cast to concrete types
      internally.
    </template-processing-seam>

    <token-counting-seam order="13">
      The HTTP-based token counting operation is wrapped. It accepts an allocator
      context, a URL string, an API key string, a request body string, an output
      pointer for the response string, and an output pointer for the HTTP status
      code. Returns a result value. All arguments are forwarded unchanged.
    </token-counting-seam>

  </behavior>

</specification>
