<specification topic="JSON Allocator">

  <topic-statement>
    The JSON allocator bridges the JSON parsing library's pluggable allocation interface
    to the talloc hierarchical memory manager so that all JSON-allocated memory is
    tracked under a talloc context.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Construction of an allocator object that routes JSON library allocation calls
      through talloc.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="JSON Library">
      The allocator object produced by this component is passed directly to the JSON
      library. The library uses it whenever it needs to allocate, reallocate, or free
      memory during document parsing and construction.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Memory Management">
      Allocations are made as talloc children of the context provided at allocator
      creation. Frees are performed directly on the pointer without needing the parent
      context, which is the expected behavior of talloc.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <allocator-creation order="1">
      An allocator object is created by providing a talloc context. The result is
      returned by value (not heap-allocated). The allocator carries three operations:

      <allocation order="1">
        When the JSON library requests memory of a given size, it is allocated as a
        talloc child of the context provided at allocator creation.
      </allocation>

      <reallocation order="2">
        When the JSON library requests a resize, the pointer is reallocated to the
        new size. The old size argument provided by the JSON library is ignored —
        talloc tracks allocation sizes internally.
      </reallocation>

      <deallocation order="3">
        When the JSON library releases memory, the pointer is freed via talloc. The
        context argument provided by the JSON library is ignored — talloc does not
        require the parent context to free a child.
      </deallocation>
    </allocator-creation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
