<specification topic="JSON Wrapper Seam">

  <topic-statement>
    The JSON wrapper seam exposes JSON library operations as individually
    mockable link seams so that tests can intercept any JSON call without
    modifying production code.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Sixteen wrappers covering: reading a JSON document from a file path,
      reading a JSON document from a memory buffer, writing a mutable JSON
      document to a file path, traversing to the document root, looking up an
      object field by key, extracting a signed integer value, extracting a
      string value, creating a mutable object node, creating a mutable array
      node, adding a string field to a mutable object, adding a signed-integer
      field to a mutable object, adding an unsigned-integer field to a mutable
      object, adding a boolean field to a mutable object, adding an arbitrary
      value field to a mutable object, appending an arbitrary value to a
      mutable array, and performing a deep copy of an immutable value into a
      mutable document.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="JSON Library">
      Each wrapper delegates unconditionally to the corresponding JSON library
      operation. The wrapper adds no logic, transformation, or error handling
      of its own. The library's return value is passed through unchanged.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Test Infrastructure">
      Tests define strong-symbol replacements for any subset of these wrappers.
      The strong definition shadows the default weak symbol, giving the test
      full control over that operation — for example, returning NULL from the
      parse wrapper to simulate a malformed-JSON failure path.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Allocator Integration">
      The file-reading and file-writing wrappers accept an optional custom
      allocator parameter that the JSON library uses for its internal
      allocations. Supplying a talloc-backed allocator (described separately
      in the JSON Allocator specification) causes all document memory to be
      tracked under a talloc context. The wrappers themselves impose no policy
      on this parameter.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <build-mode-selection order="1">
      The wrappers exist in two forms depending on the build configuration.

      In a debug or test build (when the NDEBUG macro is not defined), each
      wrapper is compiled as a weak symbol. A weak symbol has a default
      implementation but yields to any strong-symbol definition of the same
      name in the final link. This is the mechanism that makes individual
      wrappers replaceable in tests.

      In a release build (when NDEBUG is defined), each wrapper is a static
      inline function defined in the header. No separate compilation unit is
      involved; the call is inlined at every call site with zero runtime
      overhead and no exported symbol.

      <notable reason="Coverage exclusion">
        The debug-build compilation unit that contains all sixteen wrapper
        bodies is marked to be excluded from line-coverage measurement. This
        is intentional: the wrappers are unconditional one-line delegators and
        measuring their coverage adds noise without signal.
      </notable>
    </build-mode-selection>

    <document-reading-from-file order="2">
      Reads a JSON document from the file at the given path. Accepts flags
      that control parsing strictness, an optional custom allocator for
      document memory, and an output struct that receives a detailed error
      description on failure. Returns a parsed document handle on success, or
      NULL on failure with the error struct populated.
    </document-reading-from-file>

    <document-reading-from-buffer order="3">
      Reads a JSON document from the given byte buffer of the given length.
      Accepts flags that control parsing strictness. Uses the library's default
      allocator; there is no allocator parameter on this overload. Returns a
      parsed document handle on success, or NULL on failure.
    </document-reading-from-buffer>

    <document-writing-to-file order="4">
      Writes a mutable JSON document to the file at the given path. Accepts
      flags that control serialization style (e.g., pretty-printing), an
      optional custom allocator for scratch memory during serialization, and an
      output struct that receives a detailed error description on failure.
      Returns true on success, false on failure.
    </document-writing-to-file>

    <root-access order="5">
      Returns the root value of a parsed document. The document handle is the
      sole input. The return value is a borrowed pointer into the document's
      memory; its lifetime is bounded by the document's lifetime.
    </root-access>

    <object-field-lookup order="6">
      Looks up a field in a JSON object value by its string key using a linear
      scan. Returns the associated value if the key is present, or NULL if not
      found or if the input is not an object.
    </object-field-lookup>

    <signed-integer-extraction order="7">
      Extracts the signed 64-bit integer contained in a JSON number value.
      Returns the integer. Behavior is undefined if the value is not a numeric
      type or if the numeric value falls outside the 64-bit signed range.
    </signed-integer-extraction>

    <string-extraction order="8">
      Extracts the null-terminated string contents of a JSON string value.
      Returns a pointer into the document's internal storage; the pointer is
      valid for the lifetime of the document. Returns NULL if the value is not
      a string type.
    </string-extraction>

    <mutable-object-creation order="9">
      Creates an empty mutable JSON object node within a mutable document.
      The node's memory is owned by the document. Returns the node handle.
    </mutable-object-creation>

    <mutable-array-creation order="10">
      Creates an empty mutable JSON array node within a mutable document.
      The node's memory is owned by the document. Returns the node handle.
    </mutable-array-creation>

    <mutable-object-string-field order="11">
      Adds a key-value pair to a mutable object where the value is a string.
      The key and value strings are copied into the document's memory. Returns
      true on success, false if the operation fails.
    </mutable-object-string-field>

    <mutable-object-signed-integer-field order="12">
      Adds a key-value pair to a mutable object where the value is a signed
      64-bit integer. Returns true on success, false on failure.
    </mutable-object-signed-integer-field>

    <mutable-object-unsigned-integer-field order="13">
      Adds a key-value pair to a mutable object where the value is an unsigned
      64-bit integer. Returns true on success, false on failure.
    </mutable-object-unsigned-integer-field>

    <mutable-object-boolean-field order="14">
      Adds a key-value pair to a mutable object where the value is a boolean.
      Returns true on success, false on failure.
    </mutable-object-boolean-field>

    <mutable-object-arbitrary-field order="15">
      Adds a key-value pair to a mutable object where the value is an
      already-constructed mutable node (object, array, or scalar). The value
      node must belong to the same mutable document. Returns true on success,
      false on failure.
    </mutable-object-arbitrary-field>

    <mutable-array-element-append order="16">
      Appends an already-constructed mutable node to a mutable array. The
      node must belong to the same mutable document as the array. Returns true
      on success, false on failure.
    </mutable-array-element-append>

    <immutable-to-mutable-copy order="17">
      Performs a deep copy of an immutable JSON value (from a parsed document)
      into a mutable document, recursively duplicating all child nodes. Returns
      the root of the copied subtree as a mutable node owned by the target
      document, or NULL on failure.
    </immutable-to-mutable-copy>

    <test-override-pattern order="18">
      A test that needs to control a specific JSON operation defines a function
      with the exact same signature as the wrapper, without any weak attribute.
      Because the linker resolves strong symbols before weak ones, the test's
      definition becomes the active implementation for that link unit. The test
      can then consult file-local flags to decide whether to forward the call
      normally or return NULL to simulate a failure (e.g., a parse error or
      allocation failure inside the library).

      File-local (static) state is the standard pattern for these flags, since
      each test file compiles into its own binary and tests within a file run
      sequentially.
    </test-override-pattern>

  </behavior>

</specification>
