<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Key Injection">

  <topic-statement>
    The key injection system buffers programmatically supplied byte sequences
    and feeds them into the REPL input pipeline one byte at a time, ahead of
    real keyboard input.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Buffer initialization, byte appending with dynamic growth, single-byte
      draining with auto-reset, pending-byte query, escape sequence unescaping,
      and event loop integration with priority over TTY input.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Input parser">
      Drained bytes are fed to the same stateful input parser that processes
      real keyboard bytes. The parsing of bytes into semantic actions (arrow
      keys, control characters, Unicode codepoints, etc.) is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Control socket">
      The control socket supplies raw key strings that are unescaped before
      being appended to the buffer. The socket protocol and command dispatch
      are out of scope; this specification covers behavior from the point at
      which unescaped bytes are available.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Injection buffer state">
      <field name="data" type="byte array" note="dynamically allocated; initial capacity 256 bytes; never shrinks" />
      <field name="write position" type="non-negative integer" note="byte offset of the next append; increases monotonically until drain completes" />
      <field name="read position" type="non-negative integer" note="byte offset of the next byte to drain" />
      <field name="capacity" type="positive integer" note="allocated size; doubles when an append would exceed it" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <buffer-initialization order="1">
      The buffer is created with an initial capacity of 256 bytes. Both the
      write position and the read position start at zero.
    </buffer-initialization>

    <byte-appending order="2">
      A byte sequence of a given length is appended to the buffer. If the
      current write position plus the incoming length would reach or exceed
      the current capacity, the capacity is doubled repeatedly until it is
      large enough. The bytes are then copied into the buffer starting at
      the write position, and the write position is advanced by the number
      of bytes appended.

      The read position is not affected by an append.

      <notable reason="capacity never shrinks">
        Once the buffer grows, it does not release that capacity, even after
        the buffer is fully drained and reset.
      </notable>
    </byte-appending>

    <byte-draining order="3">
      A single byte is removed from the front of the unread portion of the
      buffer and returned to the caller.

      If the read position equals the write position (no unread bytes remain),
      the operation signals that no byte is available and returns without
      modifying any state.

      If an unread byte is available, it is read from the current read
      position and the read position is advanced by one. If after this
      advance the read position equals the write position (the buffer has
      been fully drained), both positions are reset to zero, making the
      entire buffer capacity available for future appends.

      <notable reason="drain is one byte at a time">
        The caller must call drain repeatedly to consume multiple bytes. This
        constraint is intentional — see event loop integration below.
      </notable>
    </byte-draining>

    <pending-query order="4">
      The number of unread bytes in the buffer is the write position minus
      the read position. This value is zero when the buffer is empty and
      positive when bytes are waiting to be drained.
    </pending-query>

    <escape-unescaping order="5">
      Before bytes are appended, a key string may be unescaped to convert
      C-style escape sequences into their raw byte equivalents. The input
      string is scanned left to right. Each recognized escape sequence is
      replaced with the corresponding byte:

      `\r` produces a carriage return byte (0x0D).
      `\n` produces a linefeed byte (0x0A).
      `\t` produces a tab byte (0x09).
      `\\` produces a backslash byte (0x5C).
      `\xNN` where `NN` are two hexadecimal digits produces the byte with
      that numeric value.

      Any backslash not followed by one of these recognized sequences is
      output as a literal backslash byte. The character following the
      backslash is processed normally on the next step.

      All non-backslash characters are copied verbatim to the output.
    </escape-unescaping>

    <event-loop-integration order="6">
      On each iteration of the main event loop, the injection buffer is
      checked for pending bytes before the event loop blocks on I/O.

      <priority-over-tty order="1">
        If the buffer contains at least one unread byte, one byte is drained
        and fed to the input parser. The event loop then continues to the
        next iteration without waiting for I/O. This repeats until the buffer
        is empty.

        Only when the buffer is empty does the event loop proceed to block
        on I/O, at which point real keyboard input may be read.
      </priority-over-tty>

      <one-byte-per-iteration order="2">
        Only one byte is drained per event loop iteration, even if many bytes
        are pending. After each byte is processed, the frame is rendered and
        the loop restarts.

        <notable reason="prevents interleaving with TTY escape sequences">
          The input parser is stateful. A multi-byte escape sequence (such
          as an arrow key) must be delivered as consecutive bytes to the
          same parser invocations. If injected bytes were drained in bulk
          and then real TTY bytes arrived, the two streams could interleave
          inside an escape sequence, producing incorrect parse results. The
          one-byte-per-iteration design ensures injected bytes are fully
          consumed before any TTY bytes enter the parser.
        </notable>
      </one-byte-per-iteration>

      <same-parser-as-tty order="3">
        Injected bytes are fed to the same stateful input parser instance
        that receives real keyboard bytes. From the parser's perspective,
        injected bytes are indistinguishable from bytes typed at the keyboard.
      </same-parser-as-tty>
    </event-loop-integration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
