<specification topic="Keyboard Layout Translator">

  <topic-statement>
    The keyboard layout translator builds a reverse keymap from the system
    keyboard layout and uses it to convert unshifted ASCII codepoints to
    their shifted equivalents, enabling correct shifted-character output
    for terminals that send only the base keycode.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      XKB context and keymap initialisation, reverse keymap construction,
      shifted-codepoint translation, and resource cleanup.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Escape Sequence Parser">
      The escape sequence parser invokes translation when it receives a CSI u
      sequence with a Shift modifier. This module does not handle escape
      sequence parsing.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="XKB Library">
      Keymap loading, state management, and keysym lookup are delegated to
      libxkbcommon. Internal XKB behaviour is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <initialisation order="1">
      During input parser setup, an XKB context is created using system
      defaults (RMLVO names are NULL, causing libxkbcommon to read from
      environment variables and system configuration). A keymap is compiled
      from that context, and an XKB state object is created from the keymap.
      The Shift modifier mask is queried from the keymap.

      If any XKB allocation fails, previously allocated objects are
      dereferenced and the translator is marked as uninitialised. Subsequent
      translation calls return the original codepoint without modification.

      A reverse keymap is then built from the successfully initialised keymap
      and state (see below).

      <notable reason="non-fatal-on-failure">
        Failure to initialise the keyboard translator does not prevent the
        input system from operating. Shifted keys will be passed through with
        their unshifted codepoints rather than being translated.
      </notable>
    </initialisation>

    <reverse-keymap-construction order="2">
      A 128-element array indexed by ASCII codepoint is populated with X11
      keycodes. For each keycode from 9 to 100 inclusive, the unshifted keysym
      at that keycode is resolved and converted to a Unicode codepoint. If the
      resulting codepoint is in the printable ASCII range (32–127) and no
      mapping has been recorded for that codepoint yet, the keycode is stored
      at that index.

      Scanning is limited to keycodes 9–100 to avoid the numeric keypad,
      which can produce the same keysyms as the main keyboard and would
      otherwise create ambiguous mappings.

      Codepoints that map to multiple keycodes retain only the first (lowest
      keycode) assignment.

      All XKB modifiers are cleared before scanning so that only the base
      (unshifted) layer is consulted.
    </reverse-keymap-construction>

    <shifted-codepoint-translation order="3">
      Given an input codepoint, the translator:

      1. Returns the original codepoint unchanged if the translator is
         uninitialised.
      2. Returns the original codepoint if it falls outside the range 32–127.
      3. Looks up the keycode in the reverse map. If no keycode was recorded
         for that codepoint (zero), returns the original.
      4. Temporarily applies the Shift modifier to the XKB state.
      5. Queries the keysym for the located keycode under the Shift modifier
         and converts to a Unicode codepoint.
      6. Clears all modifiers from the XKB state.
      7. Returns the shifted codepoint if non-zero; otherwise returns the
         original.

      <notable reason="state-mutation">
        Each translation call temporarily mutates the XKB state by applying
        and then clearing the Shift modifier. The state is always restored
        before returning, making the operation safe for sequential calls from
        a single thread.
      </notable>
    </shifted-codepoint-translation>

    <cleanup order="4">
      The translator is registered as a talloc destructor on the input parser
      context. When the parser is freed, all three XKB objects (context,
      keymap, state) are dereferenced in the correct order. The destructor
      handles null pointers safely and always returns zero to satisfy the
      talloc destructor protocol.
    </cleanup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
