<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Layer Rendering">

  <topic-statement>
    The layer rendering pipeline composes an ordered stack of independently-sized layers
    into a single terminal frame by clipping each layer to a scrollable viewport and
    writing the result in one atomic operation.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Layer protocol (visibility, height, render contracts), the fixed seven-layer stack
      composition, viewport clipping algorithm, per-frame output assembly, atomic TTY
      write, cursor position calculation from text, SIGWINCH-triggered resize handling,
      and the per-layer rendering behavior for each of the seven layer types.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Scrollback layout">
      The computation of physical row counts for scrollback text, including line wrapping
      at a given terminal width, is performed by the scrollback layout subsystem and is
      out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input cursor tracking">
      The byte-offset representation of the cursor position within the input buffer is
      maintained by the input cursor subsystem. This specification covers only how that
      byte offset is translated to a terminal row and column for the final cursor
      placement escape sequence.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Spinner animation timing">
      The periodic timer that advances the spinner animation frame is managed by the
      event loop. This specification covers only the frame set and what the spinner
      renders on each call.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tab completion state">
      Whether a completion session is active, and the list of candidates it contains,
      is managed by the tab completion subsystem. This specification covers only how
      those candidates are rendered.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Layer protocol">
      <field name="visibility predicate" type="function" note="returns true if the layer should participate in the current frame; when false, the height and render functions are not called for this frame" />
      <field name="height function" type="function" note="accepts the terminal width in columns and returns the layer's total height in rows, accounting for line wrapping" />
      <field name="render function" type="function" note="accepts the terminal width, a zero-indexed first row within the layer, and a row count; appends exactly that many rows to the output buffer" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Layer stack">
      <field name="layers" type="ordered array of layer references" note="seven layers in fixed top-to-bottom order: banner, scrollback, spinner, separator, input buffer, completion, status" />
      <field name="scroll position" type="non-negative integer" note="the document row at the top of the visible area; 0 means the beginning of the stack" />
      <field name="viewport height" type="positive integer" note="the terminal height in rows; determines how many document rows are visible" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <layer-stack-composition order="1">
      The layer stack always contains exactly seven layers in a fixed top-to-bottom order:

      1. Banner вЂ” a decorative ASCII-art header, 6 rows tall when visible.
      2. Scrollback вЂ” the conversation history; variable height.
      3. Spinner вЂ” a one-row animated wait indicator.
      4. Separator вЂ” a one-row horizontal rule with optional embedded text.
      5. Input buffer вЂ” the editable command line; variable height.
      6. Completion вЂ” the tab-completion candidate list; one row per candidate.
      7. Status вЂ” a two-row footer showing the active model name and thinking level.

      The order is fixed at initialization and never changes at runtime.
    </layer-stack-composition>

    <visibility-rules order="2">
      Each layer's visibility predicate governs whether it appears in a given frame.

      <banner order="1">
        The banner is visible when an external toggle flag is set. It is shown at
        startup by default.
      </banner>

      <scrollback order="2">
        The scrollback layer is always visible. Its height may be zero when the
        conversation history is empty, but its visibility predicate always returns
        true.
      </scrollback>

      <spinner order="3">
        The spinner is visible when the active agent is waiting for an LLM response
        or executing a tool. It is hidden in all other agent states.
      </spinner>

      <separator order="4">
        The separator is always visible.
      </separator>

      <input-buffer order="5">
        The input buffer is visible when the active agent is idle вЂ” that is, when it
        is neither waiting for an LLM response nor executing a tool.
      </input-buffer>

      <completion order="6">
        The completion layer is visible when a tab-completion session is active.
        When no completion session exists, the layer is skipped entirely.
      </completion>

      <status order="7">
        The status layer is visible when an external toggle flag is set.
      </status>
    </visibility-rules>

    <rendering-loop order="3">
      A frame is produced by iterating over the seven layers from top to bottom,
      accumulating their visible content into a single output buffer.

      For each layer, in order:

      1. The visibility predicate is evaluated. If it returns false, the layer is
         skipped entirely вЂ” its height and render functions are not called.

      2. The height function is called with the current terminal width. The result
         is the layer's total height in document rows.

      3. The layer's position in the document is determined by summing the heights
         of all preceding visible layers. This gives the contiguous range of
         document rows the layer occupies.

      4. The intersection of that range with the visible viewport is computed. If
         the layer falls entirely outside the viewport вЂ” either above it or below
         it вЂ” the layer's render function is not called.

      5. If the layer intersects the viewport, clip parameters are derived: the
         first row of the layer that falls within the viewport (a zero-indexed
         offset into the layer's own row space), and the number of rows to render
         (trimmed at both the top and the bottom of the viewport as needed).

      6. The render function is called with the terminal width, the clipped first
         row, and the clipped row count. It appends exactly that many rows to the
         output buffer.

      The loop terminates early if the accumulated document rows reach the bottom
      of the viewport before all layers have been processed.
    </rendering-loop>

    <atomic-frame-write order="4">
      The final framebuffer is assembled from a fixed preamble, the accumulated
      layer content, and a fixed postamble, then written to the terminal file
      descriptor in a single write call.

      Preamble (prepended before layer content):
      - Hide cursor: `\x1b[?25l`
      - Move cursor to top-left home position: `\x1b[H`

      Postamble (appended after layer content):
      - Erase from cursor to end of screen: `\x1b[J`
      - Cursor visibility: `\x1b[?25h` (show) when the input buffer is visible,
        `\x1b[?25l` (hide) otherwise
      - Cursor position: `\x1b[<row>;<col>H` (1-indexed) at the computed input
        cursor location, placed immediately before the visibility sequence

      The write is not split into multiple calls; the entire framebuffer is
      transmitted atomically.

      <notable reason="trailing CRLF removed when content fills the terminal">
        If the total document height is greater than or equal to the terminal
        height, and the assembled layer content ends with a carriage-return
        followed by a line-feed (`\r\n`), that final two-byte sequence is
        removed before writing. A CRLF on the last terminal row causes the
        terminal to scroll the display up by one row, which misplaces the
        cursor. Removing the trailing CRLF prevents this artifact.
      </notable>
    </atomic-frame-write>

    <cursor-position-calculation order="5">
      The terminal cursor is positioned at the screen location corresponding to
      the input buffer's current byte cursor offset. The calculation scans the
      input buffer text from byte zero to the cursor offset, tracking row and
      column.

      For each character encountered:
      - A newline character resets the column to zero and increments the row,
        without consuming a display width.
      - An ANSI escape sequence (detected by the leading `\x1b[` introducer) is
        skipped in its entirety and contributes zero display width.
      - Any other character contributes its Unicode display width to the column:
        zero for combining characters, one for standard-width characters, and
        two for wide characters such as CJK ideographs.
      - When the column would exceed the terminal width, the row increments and
        the column resets to zero before applying the character's width.

      After scanning, if the column equals the terminal width exactly, the row
      increments and the column resets to zero (the cursor is at the start of
      the next line).

      The calculated row and column are relative to the start of the input buffer
      layer. They are offset by the document row at which the input buffer begins
      to produce absolute screen coordinates, then converted to 1-indexed values
      for the cursor-position escape sequence.

      <notable reason="cursor position is recalculated every frame">
        The cursor position is not maintained incrementally. On each frame, the
        entire input buffer from byte zero to the cursor offset is re-scanned.
      </notable>
    </cursor-position-calculation>

    <resize-handling order="6">
      When the terminal window is resized, the operating system delivers a SIGWINCH
      signal. The signal handler records the event by setting a flag (a
      `volatile sig_atomic_t`) and returns immediately, performing no other work.

      On each iteration of the REPL event loop, the flag is tested. When set, the
      flag is cleared and a resize procedure is invoked. The resize procedure
      queries the new terminal dimensions via an `ioctl` call, updates the stored
      terminal width and height, and triggers a full re-render at the new
      dimensions.

      <notable reason="resize is deferred to the event loop">
        The signal handler only sets a flag. Terminal queries, layout
        recalculation, and rendering occur in the event loop on the next
        iteration, avoiding the use of non-async-signal-safe functions inside
        the signal handler.
      </notable>
    </resize-handling>

    <per-layer-rendering order="7">
      Each layer type produces its rows by appending bytes to the output buffer.
      Every row, without exception, ends with an erase-to-end-of-line sequence
      (`\x1b[K`) followed by carriage-return and line-feed (`\r\n`), unless
      otherwise noted.

      <banner-rendering order="1">
        The banner is always exactly 6 rows.

        Row 0: A full-width horizontal border of double horizontal line characters
        (в•ђ, U+2550), drawn in a dim-gray 256-color foreground.

        Rows 1вЂ“4: An ASCII-art face composed of box-drawing characters for eye
        frames, filled with a cyan foreground for the frames and an amber-gold
        foreground for the pupils. A mouth on row 4 uses a coral-pink foreground.
        The application name, version string, and a tagline appear alongside the
        face in soft-blue and light-gray foregrounds respectively.

        Row 5: A second full-width border identical to row 0.

        All color is applied with 256-color SGR foreground sequences
        (`\x1b[38;5;<n>m`) and reset with `\x1b[0m`.
      </banner-rendering>

      <scrollback-rendering order="2">
        The scrollback layer maps the requested row range to logical text lines
        using the scrollback layout subsystem. For each text byte in range,
        newline characters are replaced with `\x1b[K\r\n`. Lines that end
        without a newline receive a trailing `\x1b[K\r\n` to complete the
        final row.
      </scrollback-rendering>

      <spinner-rendering order="3">
        The spinner renders one row: a single Braille animation frame character
        followed by a space and the fixed text "Waiting for response...".

        The animation cycles through ten Braille characters in order:
        в ‹ в ™ в № в ё в ј в ґ в ¦ в § в ‡ в Џ

        The active frame advances every 120 milliseconds and wraps back to the
        first character after the tenth.
      </spinner-rendering>

      <separator-rendering order="4">
        The separator renders one row of horizontal box-drawing characters
        (в”Ђ, U+2500) spanning the full terminal width.

        When navigation context is available (the current agent's position in the
        process tree), a navigation string is embedded in the separator. It
        contains abbreviated identifiers for the parent agent, previous sibling,
        current agent (bracketed), next sibling, and a child count, separated by
        directional arrow characters. The number of box-drawing characters is
        reduced to accommodate the embedded string, keeping the total visual
        width equal to the terminal width.

        When debug information is available, a debug string showing the render
        timing and viewport offsets is also embedded alongside the navigation
        string.

        The visual widths of embedded strings are measured by scanning their
        bytes and excluding all ANSI escape sequences, so that color codes do
        not distort the character count.

        Render timing in the debug string is displayed as an integer number of
        microseconds when below 1000 Вµs, and as a decimal number of milliseconds
        with one decimal place when 1000 Вµs or above.
      </separator-rendering>

      <input-buffer-rendering order="5">
        The input buffer layer renders the command text. Newline characters are
        replaced with `\x1b[K\r\n`. Text that does not end with a newline receives
        a trailing `\x1b[K\r\n`.

        <notable reason="empty input buffer occupies one row">
          When the input buffer contains no text, the layer height is 1, not 0.
          A single blank row (only `\x1b[K\r\n`) is rendered to preserve space
          for cursor placement.
        </notable>
      </input-buffer-rendering>

      <completion-rendering order="6">
        The completion layer renders one row per visible candidate. The currently
        selected candidate is highlighted with reverse video combined with bold
        (`\x1b[7;1m`) and the attributes are reset after the candidate text
        (`\x1b[0m`). All other candidates are rendered without highlighting.

        If the viewport clips the bottom of the completion list, only the
        candidates that fall within the clipped row count are rendered.
      </completion-rendering>

      <status-rendering order="7">
        The status layer is always exactly 2 rows.

        Row 0: A full-width separator of horizontal box-drawing characters
        (в”Ђ, U+2500), identical in style to the separator layer's rule but without
        any embedded text.

        Row 1: A robot emoji (рџ¤–) followed by the active model name and thinking
        level, separated by a slash, in a soft-blue 256-color foreground. If no
        model is configured, the text "(no model)" is shown instead.
      </status-rendering>

    </per-layer-rendering>

  </behavior>

</specification>
