<specification topic="Link Seam Wrappers">

  <topic-statement>
    The link-seam wrapper system exposes every external library call and selected
    internal call through a thin indirection layer that test builds can replace
    without modifying production code.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The MOCKABLE symbol attribute, the two-mode compilation strategy (inline in
      release, weak symbol in debug), the aggregation header that assembles all
      wrapper families into a single include, and the general contract that every
      wrapped call is a transparent passthrough unless a test overrides it.
    </in-scope>
    <boundary name="Individual wrapper families">
      The specific functions wrapped in each family (HTTP client, HTML parsing,
      internal application functions, POSIX, standard library, JSON, talloc) are
      documented separately. This specification covers only the mechanism that
      applies uniformly to all of them.
    </boundary>
    <boundary name="Test override mechanism">
      Tests replace wrapped functions by providing a strong-symbol definition of
      the same name. The linker resolves the strong definition over the weak one.
      The test framework conventions for doing this are outside scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="MOCKABLE attribute">
      <field name="release build" type="keyword" note="expands to 'static inline'; definition lives in the header; call is inlined at the call site with zero overhead" />
      <field name="debug/test build" type="keyword" note="expands to '__attribute__((weak))'; definition lives in the .c file; the symbol is a weak global that any translation unit can override" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <release-mode-dispatch order="1">
      In release builds (NDEBUG defined), each wrapper is defined as a static
      inline function directly in its header file. The compiler inlines the call
      at every use site, producing identical machine code to calling the underlying
      function directly. No wrapper symbol appears in the object file or binary.
      No runtime indirection exists.
    </release-mode-dispatch>

    <debug-mode-dispatch order="2">
      In debug and test builds (NDEBUG not defined), each wrapper is declared as a
      weak symbol in the header and defined as a weak symbol in a corresponding
      .c file. The weak definition calls through to the underlying function
      unchanged. Any translation unit may provide a strong-symbol definition of the
      same name; the linker selects the strong definition over the weak one,
      replacing the call everywhere in the binary without source modification.
    </debug-mode-dispatch>

    <transparent-passthrough order="3">
      When no test override is present, every wrapper forwards all arguments to the
      underlying function and returns its result unchanged. Arguments are not
      validated, logged, or transformed. The wrapper is behaviorally invisible.
    </transparent-passthrough>

    <aggregation-header order="4">
      A single umbrella header includes all wrapper family headers in one
      directive. Code that needs access to the full set of wrapped symbols includes
      only this umbrella. The umbrella itself contains no wrapper definitions; it
      is purely compositional.

      The families included are: talloc allocation, JSON library, HTTP client
      (curl), POSIX system calls, standard library, and internal application
      functions.

      <notable reason="web wrappers excluded from umbrella">
        The HTML parsing wrappers are not included in the umbrella header. Code
        that needs them must include the HTML wrapper header directly. This is the
        only wrapper family omitted from the umbrella.
      </notable>
    </aggregation-header>

    <variadic-limitation order="5">
      Some underlying functions are variadic (accept variable argument lists).
      Wrapping variadic functions requires special handling.

      In release builds, variadic functions that cannot be expressed as inline
      functions are wrapped using C preprocessor macros that expand directly to
      the underlying call, bypassing the wrapper mechanism entirely. These macros
      cannot be overridden by tests.

      In debug builds, variadic wrappers are defined as proper functions. They
      extract a single generic pointer argument from the variadic list and forward
      it to the underlying function. This means only the first variadic argument
      is forwarded; the wrapper does not support multiple variadic arguments.

      <notable reason="variadic extraction uses void pointer">
        The debug-mode variadic wrappers extract variadic arguments as a raw void
        pointer (va_arg with void* type) regardless of the actual type the
        underlying function expects. For integer or enum arguments this works by
        coincidence on platforms where pointer and integer registers align, but
        is not formally correct C.
      </notable>
    </variadic-limitation>

    <lcov-exclusion order="6">
      All wrapper definitions in debug/test builds are marked for exclusion from
      line coverage analysis. Because these functions only delegate to the real
      implementation, covering them adds no meaningful assurance and would inflate
      coverage accounting. Release builds have no symbols to exclude.
    </lcov-exclusion>

  </behavior>

</specification>
