<specification topic="Logger">

  <topic-statement>
    The logger writes structured JSON log records to a rotating file in a
    well-known directory, with thread-safe serialization and automatic log
    rotation on each initialization.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Log directory creation and path resolution, log file rotation on
      initialization, per-record formatting (level, ISO 8601 timestamp with
      milliseconds and timezone offset, payload), thread-safe file writes,
      and the two logger modes (global singleton and dependency-injected
      instance).
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Log Consumers">
      How log records are read, searched, or visualized is outside this scope.
      The logger only produces the log file.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Panic Handler">
      The panic handler accesses the log file descriptor directly to write
      a final record before terminating. That access path is outside this scope;
      this topic covers only normal write operations.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Log Record">
      <field name="level" type="string" note="severity label: debug, info, warn, or error" />
      <field name="timestamp" type="string" note="ISO 8601 format with millisecond precision and UTC offset; e.g. 2026-01-15T14:23:05.123+00:00" />
      <field name="logline" type="JSON value" note="the original structured payload passed by the caller" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <initialization order="1">
      Initialization resolves the log file path and opens the file for
      appending.

      <path-resolution order="1">
        If the environment variable IKIGAI_LOG_DIR is set, the log file is
        placed at that path appended with "/current.log". Otherwise, the log
        directory is ".ikigai/logs" relative to the supplied working directory,
        and the log file is "current.log" within that directory. The directory
        is created if it does not exist.

        If the resolved path exceeds the internal path buffer capacity, the
        process terminates via the panic handler.
      </path-resolution>

      <log-rotation order="2">
        If a file named "current.log" already exists at the resolved location,
        it is renamed to an archive file before the new log is opened. The
        archive filename is derived from the current local time formatted as
        an ISO 8601 datetime, with colon characters replaced by dashes to
        produce a filesystem-safe name. This rotation occurs on every
        initialization, so each process run begins with a fresh log file.
      </log-rotation>

      <file-open order="3">
        The log file is opened for writing. Failure to open the file terminates
        the process via the panic handler.
      </file-open>
    </initialization>

    <write-operation order="2">
      Each write composes a JSON object from the level string, a freshly
      captured timestamp, and the caller-supplied payload, then appends it
      to the log file as a single line followed by a newline character
      (JSON Lines format).

      <timestamp-capture order="1">
        The timestamp is captured at write time using the current wall clock.
        It includes both seconds and milliseconds. The UTC offset is formatted
        as "+HH:MM" (or "-HH:MM" for negative offsets).
      </timestamp-capture>

      <serialization order="2">
        The JSON object is serialized using a JSON library. The caller
        transfers ownership of the payload document to the logger; the document
        is freed after serialization whether or not the write succeeds.
      </serialization>

      <file-write order="3">
        The serialized string is written to the file. A mutex serializes all
        write operations so that concurrent callers from multiple threads do
        not interleave their output.
      </file-write>
    </write-operation>

    <logger-modes order="3">
      Two logger modes exist and operate independently.

      <global-singleton order="1">
        A single global logger is initialized once at startup via a dedicated
        initialization function and written to via a global write function. If
        the global logger was not initialized, write calls are silent no-ops.
        This mode is used by subsystems that predate the dependency-injected
        instance logger.
      </global-singleton>

      <instance-logger order="2">
        An instance logger is allocated as a talloc context and carries its
        own file handle and mutex. It is initialized with the same path
        resolution logic as the global logger. When the talloc context is
        freed, the file handle is closed and the mutex is destroyed. This mode
        is intended for components that receive their logger via dependency
        injection.

        If the instance logger's file handle is absent, write calls are silent
        no-ops.
      </instance-logger>
    </logger-modes>

    <error-behavior order="4">
      Directory creation failure (other than the directory already existing),
      path buffer overflow, and file open failure all terminate the process
      via the panic handler. These conditions are treated as unrecoverable.

      Write failures after initialization do not terminate the process.
    </error-behavior>

  </behavior>

</specification>
