<specification topic="Mail Storage">

  <topic-statement>
    The mail storage system persists, retrieves, and manages agent-to-agent
    messages in the database, enforcing session-scoped isolation and recipient
    ownership on deletion.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Message insertion, inbox retrieval (unfiltered and sender-filtered),
      mark-as-read, deletion with ownership validation, and session isolation
      semantics.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Inter-agent Messaging">
      How agents decide to send messages, wait for replies, or react to incoming
      mail is handled by the inter-agent messaging and wait synchronization
      subsystems. This topic covers only the storage operations.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database Notifications">
      Notifying a waiting agent that new mail has arrived is handled by the
      PostgreSQL notification layer. This topic does not emit notifications.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Mail Message">
      <field name="id" type="integer" note="database-assigned identifier; populated on insertion" />
      <field name="sender identifier" type="string" note="UUID of the sending agent" />
      <field name="recipient identifier" type="string" note="UUID of the receiving agent" />
      <field name="body" type="string" note="message content" />
      <field name="timestamp" type="integer" note="Unix timestamp supplied by the caller; not generated by the database" />
      <field name="read" type="boolean" note="false on insertion; set to true by the mark-as-read operation" />
      <field name="session identifier" type="integer" note="session scope; all operations filter by this value" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <session-isolation order="1">
      All storage operations are scoped to a session identifier. Messages are
      only visible within the session in which they were inserted. A message
      sent in one session is never returned by inbox queries in a different
      session, even if the sender and recipient identifiers match.

      <notable reason="caller controls the session scope">
        The session identifier is passed in by the caller on every operation.
        There is no enforcement that the caller provides a consistent or
        meaningful session identifier. Providing a mismatched identifier
        silently yields empty results.
      </notable>
    </session-isolation>

    <message-insertion order="2">
      A message is inserted into the mail table with the provided sender
      identifier, recipient identifier, body, timestamp, session identifier,
      and an initial read value of false.

      The timestamp value is supplied by the caller and inserted as given. The
      database does not generate or validate the timestamp.

      On successful insertion, the database-assigned identifier is written back
      to the caller's message structure.
    </message-insertion>

    <inbox-retrieval order="3">
      Two retrieval variants are supported:

      <unfiltered-inbox order="1">
        All messages addressed to the recipient within the current session are
        returned, regardless of sender. Messages are ordered so that unread
        messages appear before read messages, and within each group, newer
        messages appear before older ones.
      </unfiltered-inbox>

      <filtered-inbox order="2">
        Only messages from a specific sender addressed to the recipient within
        the current session are returned. The same ordering applies: unread
        before read, newest first within each group.
      </filtered-inbox>

      Both variants return an empty result set without error when no matching
      messages exist. The full result set is returned in a single operation;
      there is no pagination or limit.

      <notable reason="read messages are included in inbox results">
        Messages that have been marked as read remain in the inbox and continue
        to appear in retrieval results. Reading a message does not remove it.
        Only the explicit delete operation removes a message.
      </notable>
    </inbox-retrieval>

    <mark-as-read order="4">
      The mark-as-read operation updates a single message's read flag to true,
      identified by its database identifier. The operation succeeds even if the
      message identifier does not exist; no rows being updated is not treated
      as an error.
    </mark-as-read>

    <deletion order="5">
      The delete operation removes a single message identified by its database
      identifier, subject to a recipient ownership check. The deletion only
      succeeds if the message exists and the provided recipient identifier
      matches the message's recipient field.

      If no message matching both the identifier and recipient is found, an
      error is returned. This is the only operation that enforces recipient
      ownership.

      <notable reason="ownership enforcement is delete-only">
        Insertion and retrieval do not verify that the caller has any
        relationship to the sender or recipient identifiers. Any caller can
        insert a message with arbitrary sender and recipient values or retrieve
        any recipient's inbox within the session.
      </notable>
    </deletion>

  </behavior>

</specification>
