<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Marks">

  <topic-statement>
    The marks system creates named conversation checkpoints and restores the
    conversation to any checkpoint on demand, truncating messages and rebuilding
    the display from the retained history.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Mark creation, the mark data record, mark storage on the agent, the rewind
      operation (message truncation, mark pruning, scrollback reconstruction),
      database persistence of mark and rewind events, and the relationship between
      a mark's index and the live message array.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Scrollback rendering">
      How events are rendered into scrollback lines during scrollback reconstruction
      is handled by the event rendering subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database persistence">
      How events are written to and read from the database is managed by the
      database layer and is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Mark">
      <field name="message index" type="non-negative integer" note="the number of messages in the agent's message array at the time the mark was created; this becomes the truncation point on rewind" />
      <field name="label" type="text or null" note="optional human-readable name for the mark; null if no label was supplied" />
      <field name="timestamp" type="timestamp" note="wall-clock time when the mark was created" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <mark-creation order="1">
      A mark is created when the user runs the `/mark` command, optionally
      followed by a label string. The mark records the current size of the
      agent's in-memory message array as its message index and the current
      wall-clock time as its timestamp. The label, if provided, is stored
      verbatim; if omitted, the label is null.

      The new mark is appended to the agent's dynamic mark array, which grows
      as needed. A mark creation event is persisted to the database. Persistence
      is best-effort: a failure is logged but does not prevent the mark from
      existing in memory.
    </mark-creation>

    <rewind-operation order="2">
      Rewinding to a mark restores the conversation to the state it was in when
      that mark was created. The operation proceeds in four steps:

      <message-truncation order="1">
        The agent's in-memory message array is truncated to the mark's message
        index. All messages at and beyond that index are discarded. Messages
        before the index are retained unchanged.
      </message-truncation>

      <mark-pruning order="2">
        All marks whose message index is greater than the target mark's message
        index are removed from the agent's mark array. The target mark itself
        is retained, allowing the user to rewind to the same point again.
      </mark-pruning>

      <scrollback-reconstruction order="3">
        The scrollback display buffer is cleared and rebuilt by replaying all
        database events from the beginning of the conversation through the now-
        truncated message history. Each retained event is passed through the
        event renderer in chronological order to reconstruct the visible display.
      </scrollback-reconstruction>

      <rewind-persistence order="4">
        A rewind event is persisted to the database recording that a rewind
        occurred. Persistence is best-effort.
      </rewind-persistence>

      <notable reason="target mark is kept after rewind">
        The mark that was rewound to is not removed from the mark array.
        Subsequent rewinds to the same mark are therefore possible without
        recreating it.
      </notable>
    </rewind-operation>

    <mark-array-storage order="3">
      Marks are stored in a dynamically sized pointer array on the agent. The
      array grows by reallocation when a new mark would exceed the current
      capacity. Each array slot holds a pointer to an individually allocated
      mark record. The array is owned by the agent and freed with it.
    </mark-array-storage>

    <database-record-kinds order="4">
      Two database event kinds relate to marks:

      - **mark**: written when a mark is created; stores the optional label in
        the data payload.
      - **rewind**: written when a rewind is performed; identifies the target
        mark in the data payload.

      Both are metadata records and are not rendered to the scrollback display.
      During session replay, the rewind record signals the replay system to
      truncate the replayed event stream at the corresponding point.
    </database-record-kinds>

    <message-index-semantics order="5">
      A mark's message index equals the number of messages present when the mark
      was created, not a zero-based index into any particular message. Rewinding
      to a mark truncates the array to exactly that count, preserving exactly
      the messages that existed before the mark was placed.

      <notable reason="mark captures a count, not a message reference">
        If messages are added after a mark is created and the conversation is
        then rewound, the mark's message index correctly identifies the
        truncation boundary regardless of how many messages were added in between.
      </notable>
    </message-index-semantics>

  </behavior>

</specification>
