<specification topic="Model Selection Command">

  <topic-statement>
    The model selection command updates the active agent's LLM model,
    inferred provider, and thinking level with validation and database
    persistence.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Parsing the model/thinking-level syntax, inferring the provider from
      the model name, validating thinking level compatibility for Google
      models, updating in-memory agent state, invalidating the provider
      instance and token cache, persisting changes to the database, and
      displaying a confirmation with provider-specific thinking details.
      Also includes the /system command for setting the global system message.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Provider Inference">
      The mapping from model name to provider name is performed by an external
      function. This topic receives either the provider name or an error.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Google Thinking Validation">
      Thinking level compatibility checks and budget/level lookups for Google
      models are performed by external functions. This topic invokes them and
      handles their results.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Token Cache">
      Cache invalidation and re-pruning with the new provider's token counters
      are performed by external operations. This topic calls them in sequence.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database">
      The agents table is updated via an external helper. Errors are logged
      and do not block the command from completing.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input Syntax">
      <field name="model_name" type="text" required="true" />
      <field name="thinking_level" type="text" required="false"
             note="appended after '/' separator; one of: min, low, med, high" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Database Update (agents table)">
      <field name="provider" type="text" note="inferred from model name" />
      <field name="model" type="text" />
      <field name="thinking_level" type="text"
             note="stored as string: min, low, med, or high" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Thinking Level Strings">
      <field name="min" type="text" note="minimum thinking" />
      <field name="low" type="text" note="low thinking" />
      <field name="med" type="text" note="medium thinking (also accepted as input)" />
      <field name="high" type="text" note="high thinking" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <model-command order="1">

      <argument-validation order="1">
        If no argument is provided, an error is returned. If the agent is
        currently in WAITING_FOR_LLM state, an error is returned (model cannot
        be switched mid-request).
      </argument-validation>

      <syntax-parsing order="2">
        The argument is parsed for an optional '/' separator:
        - If no '/' is present: the entire argument is the model name;
          thinking level is absent (will use current).
        - If '/' is present with nothing after it: an error is returned
          ("trailing '/' with no thinking level").
        - If '/' is present with an empty model name (slash at position 0):
          an error is returned ("empty model name").
        - Otherwise: the portion before '/' is the model name and the
          portion after is the thinking level string.
      </syntax-parsing>

      <provider-inference order="3">
        The model name is mapped to a provider name. Models beginning with
        "gpt-", "o1", "o3", or "o4" map to "openai"; models beginning with
        "claude-" map to "anthropic"; models beginning with "gemini-" map to
        "google". Unrecognized models cause an error.
      </provider-inference>

      <thinking-level-resolution order="4">
        If a thinking level string was provided in the argument, it is
        converted to the internal enum value ("min" → MIN, "low" → LOW,
        "med" → MED, "high" → HIGH). An unrecognized string causes an error.
        If no thinking level was provided, the agent's current thinking level
        is used unchanged.
      </thinking-level-resolution>

      <google-model-validation order="5">
        For Google models only: the thinking level is validated against the
        model's capabilities. If the level is unsupported, an error is
        returned. For Gemini 2.5 models specifically, the model must also
        appear in the thinking budget lookup table; if it does not, an error
        is returned.
      </google-model-validation>

      <in-memory-state-update order="6">
        The agent's previous provider string and model string are freed and
        replaced with newly allocated copies of the inferred provider and
        parsed model name. The agent's thinking level field is updated to the
        resolved enum value.
      </in-memory-state-update>

      <cache-invalidation order="7">
        The agent's provider instance is invalidated so the next request
        creates a fresh instance with the new model. The token cache is fully
        invalidated and immediately re-pruned using the new provider's token
        counters.
      </cache-invalidation>

      <database-persistence order="8">
        If a database context is present, the agents table is updated with
        the new provider, model, and thinking level (stored as a string).
        If the update fails, the error is logged via JSONL and freed; the
        in-memory state remains authoritative.
      </database-persistence>

      <user-feedback order="9">
        A confirmation message is appended to the scrollback. The message
        includes the provider name, model name, and thinking level details:

        - Anthropic models with adaptive thinking: shows the effort string
          ("low", "medium", or "high").
        - Anthropic models with budget thinking: shows the token budget with
          a "K" suffix for values over 1024.
        - Google Gemini 2.5 models: shows the token budget.
        - Google Gemini 3 models: shows the level string ("minimal", "low",
          "medium", or "high").
        - OpenAI models: shows the effort string ("low", "medium", or "high").
      </user-feedback>

    </model-command>

    <system-command order="2">
      The /system command sets or clears the global system message.

      <clearing order="1">
        If no argument is provided, the current system message is freed and
        the field is set to null. A "System message cleared" confirmation is
        appended to the scrollback.
      </clearing>

      <setting order="2">
        If an argument is provided, the current system message is freed and
        replaced with a copy of the argument string. A "System message set
        to: …" confirmation is appended to the scrollback.

        <notable reason="global config, not per-agent">
          The system message is stored in the global configuration object,
          not on the agent. It affects all future requests regardless of
          which agent submits them.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="no database persistence">
          The system message is not persisted to the database and is lost
          when the process restarts.
        </notable>
      </setting>
    </system-command>

  </behavior>

</specification>
