<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Model Capability Registry">

  <topic-statement>
    The model capability registry maps each known model identifier to its
    provider affiliation and thinking-capability metadata, and provides
    lookup operations for inferring providers and querying thinking support.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The hardcoded table of supported models with their thinking support
      flags and budget values, the provider-inference operation that maps
      model name prefixes to provider names, and the lookup operations for
      querying thinking support and budget by model identifier.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Provider factory">
      How provider instances are created from a provider name and API
      credential is out of scope; this specification covers only the
      registry data and lookup behavior.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Thinking configuration">
      How thinking levels are translated into per-provider API parameters
      (budget tokens, effort strings, level strings) is covered by provider-
      specific thinking specifications.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Model capability entry">
      <field name="model identifier" type="text" note="exact string used in API requests" />
      <field name="thinking supported" type="boolean" />
      <field name="thinking budget" type="integer" note="maximum thinking token budget; 0 for effort-based or unsupported models" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <registry-contents order="1">
      The registry contains exactly 29 model entries, organized by provider:

      <anthropic-models order="1">
        Five Claude models are registered, all with thinking support:

        - `claude-haiku-4-5`: thinking supported, maximum budget 32,768 tokens
        - `claude-sonnet-4-5`: thinking supported, maximum budget 65,536 tokens
        - `claude-opus-4-5`: thinking supported, maximum budget 65,536 tokens
        - `claude-sonnet-4-6`: thinking supported, maximum budget 65,536 tokens
        - `claude-opus-4-6`: thinking supported, budget 0 (effort-based, not
          budget-based; the 0 value signals that effort strings rather than
          token counts are used to control thinking depth)
      </anthropic-models>

      <openai-models order="2">
        Sixteen OpenAI models are registered across two groups:

        Standard and GPT-5 models with thinking support (all effort-based,
        budget 0):
        - `gpt-5`, `gpt-5-mini`, `gpt-5-nano`, `gpt-5-pro`
        - `gpt-5.1`, `gpt-5.1-chat-latest`, `gpt-5.1-codex`
        - `gpt-5.2`, `gpt-5.2-chat-latest`, `gpt-5.2-codex`
        - `o1`, `o1-mini`, `o1-preview`, `o3`, `o3-mini`

        Legacy models without thinking support (budget 0):
        - `gpt-4`, `gpt-4-turbo`, `gpt-4o`, `gpt-4o-mini`

        <notable reason="budget value overloaded">
          Budget 0 is used to signal two different situations: effort-based
          thinking (not budget-based) for models that do support thinking,
          and the absence of thinking support entirely for legacy models. The
          thinking support boolean flag distinguishes these two cases.
        </notable>
      </openai-models>

      <google-models order="3">
        Eight Google Gemini models are registered across two groups:

        Gemini 3 models with thinking support (all level-based, budget 0):
        - `gemini-3-flash-preview`
        - `gemini-3-pro-preview`
        - `gemini-3.1-pro-preview`

        Gemini 2.5 models with budget-based thinking:
        - `gemini-2.5-pro`: maximum budget 32,768 tokens
        - `gemini-2.5-flash`: maximum budget 24,576 tokens
        - `gemini-2.5-flash-lite`: maximum budget 24,576 tokens

        Legacy Gemini models without thinking support (budget 0):
        - `gemini-flash-1.5`
        - `gemini-pro-1.5`
      </google-models>
    </registry-contents>

    <provider-inference order="2">
      A provider name can be inferred from a model identifier by matching
      the model name against a fixed set of prefixes. The lookup is
      case-sensitive and uses prefix matching:

      - Names beginning with `gpt-` → `openai`
      - Names beginning with `o1`, `o1-` → `openai`
      - Names beginning with `o3`, `o3-` → `openai`
      - Names beginning with `o4`, `o4-` → `openai`
      - Names beginning with `claude-` → `anthropic`
      - Names beginning with `gemini-` → `google`

      If no prefix matches, the inference returns nothing. This operation
      is separate from the registry table lookup and does not require the
      model to be present in the registry.

      <notable reason="reasoning model prefixes checked individually">
        The `o1`, `o3`, and `o4` prefixes are checked explicitly alongside
        the longer `o1-`, `o3-`, and `o4-` prefixes, meaning both `o3` and
        `o3-mini` correctly infer `openai` as their provider.
      </notable>
    </provider-inference>

    <thinking-support-lookup order="3">
      Given an exact model identifier string, the registry returns whether
      that model supports thinking. Lookup is by exact string match; no
      prefix or pattern matching is applied. If the model identifier is
      absent from the registry, the operation returns an error rather than
      a default value.
    </thinking-support-lookup>

    <thinking-budget-lookup order="4">
      Given an exact model identifier string, the registry returns the
      model's maximum thinking budget token count. For models that support
      thinking via effort strings rather than budgets, this value is 0.
      For models that do not support thinking, this value is also 0. Lookup
      is by exact string match; if the identifier is absent, the operation
      returns an error.
    </thinking-budget-lookup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
