<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Model Selection">

  <topic-statement>
    The model selection subsystem configures which LLM model, provider, and
    thinking level an agent uses, with changes taking effect on the next request.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The /model command (model name, thinking level parsing, provider
      inference), the /system command (system prompt override), state changes
      on model switch (provider invalidation, token cache reprune), and
      persistence of model configuration.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Provider serialization">
      How the selected model and thinking level are encoded into provider-specific
      API request bodies is covered by the provider serialization specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Credential loading">
      How API keys are resolved for the inferred provider is covered by the
      credential loading specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Model configuration">
      <field name="model name" type="text" note="provider-specific model identifier (e.g., claude-opus-4-6)" />
      <field name="provider" type="text" note="inferred from the model name; one of: anthropic, openai, google" />
      <field name="thinking level" type="enumeration" note="one of: min (disabled), low, med, high; defaults to min" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <model-command order="1">
      The `/model` command accepts an argument of the form `<model_name>` or
      `<model_name>/<thinking_level>`. The forward slash separates the model
      name from the optional thinking level.

      1. **Argument parsing**: the argument is split at the first `/`. If no
         `/` is present, the thinking level defaults to minimum (disabled).
      2. **Provider inference**: the provider is determined from the model name
         by recognizing provider-specific name patterns. The three recognized
         providers are Anthropic (Claude models), Google (Gemini models), and
         OpenAI (all other models).
      3. **Thinking level validation**: the level string must be one of `min`,
         `low`, `med`, or `high`. An unrecognized string is an error.
      4. **Guard**: the command cannot execute while an LLM request is in
         progress. If the agent is not idle, an error is returned.
      5. **State update**: the agent's provider name, model name, and thinking
         level are updated in memory. The cached provider instance is
         invalidated so a fresh one is created on the next request. The token
         cache is reprune to account for the new model's token counting behavior.
      6. **Persistence**: the new configuration is written to the agent's
         database record. Persistence failures are logged as warnings; memory
         is authoritative.

      Calling `/model` without an argument is an error.
    </model-command>

    <system-command order="2">
      The `/system` command sets a session-level system prompt override that
      supplements or replaces the system prompt sources used during LLM request
      assembly:

      - With a text argument: the argument string is stored as the override
        system message. No length or content validation is applied.
      - Without an argument: any existing override is cleared.

      The system message override is stored in the shared configuration context,
      not on the individual agent. It applies globally to all agents in the
      session.

      <notable reason="system override is not persisted to the database">
        Unlike model changes, the system message override set via `/system` is
        not persisted to the database. It is lost when the session ends.
      </notable>
    </system-command>

    <provider-invalidation order="3">
      When the model or provider changes, the cached provider instance (which
      holds the configured API endpoint, authentication, and model parameters)
      is destroyed. The next LLM request will instantiate a new provider
      instance with the updated configuration. This ensures that no stale
      provider configuration is used after a model switch.
    </provider-invalidation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
