<specification topic="Panic Handler">

  <topic-statement>
    The panic handler performs emergency process termination by restoring terminal
    state, emitting a fatal log entry, writing a diagnostic message to stderr, and
    aborting the process to generate a core dump.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Terminal restoration on panic, logger write on panic, stderr diagnostic output
      on panic, process termination via abort, and the talloc error handler that
      delegates to the panic path.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Terminal">
      The panic handler accesses a global terminal context set during startup. If
      the context is present and has a valid file descriptor, terminal escape
      sequences are written to that descriptor and terminal attributes are restored.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Logger">
      The panic handler accesses a global logger set during startup. If the logger
      is present and has a valid file descriptor, a JSON log entry is written to
      that descriptor.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <panic order="1">
      A panic is triggered by providing an error message string, a source file name
      string, and a line number. Either string may be absent. The following steps
      execute in order:

      <terminal-restoration order="1">
        If the global terminal context is present and its file descriptor is valid,
        a reset sequence is written directly to the file descriptor. The sequence
        shows the cursor (ESC[?25h), resets text attributes (ESC[0m), and exits the
        alternate screen buffer (ESC[?1049l), as a single 18-byte write. The original
        terminal attributes are then restored immediately using a direct system call.

        <notable reason="not fully async-signal-safe">
          The terminal attribute restore call is not async-signal-safe per POSIX.
          It is used here anyway because it is necessary for the terminal to be
          usable after the process terminates. The escape sequence write is
          async-signal-safe.
        </notable>
      </terminal-restoration>

      <logger-write order="2">
        If the global logger is present and its file descriptor is valid, a JSON
        object is formatted and written to that descriptor. The object contains:
        - "level": "fatal"
        - "event": "panic"
        - "message": the message string (empty string if absent)
        - "file": the file string (empty string if absent)
        - "line": the line number as a decimal integer

        The formatted string is followed by a newline. If the formatted length
        would exceed 511 bytes, nothing is written.

        <notable reason="not async-signal-safe">
          The string formatting function used here is not async-signal-safe.
          The log write uses a direct write call, which is async-signal-safe,
          but the formatting is not.
        </notable>
      </logger-write>

      <stderr-output order="3">
        A diagnostic message is written to standard error using only the direct
        write system call. The format is:

          FATAL: &lt;message&gt;\n  at &lt;file&gt;:&lt;line&gt;\n

        If the message string is absent, that portion is empty. If the file string
        is absent, that portion is empty. The line number is converted to a decimal
        string using a custom integer-to-string routine that avoids all non-signal-safe
        functions.

        <notable reason="INT32_MIN overflow">
          The integer-to-string conversion negates negative input values to obtain
          absolute digits. If the line number is exactly the minimum signed 32-bit
          integer value (-2147483648), negating it produces signed integer overflow,
          which is undefined behavior. Line numbers in practice are always positive,
          making this unreachable.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="truncation on long numbers">
          The integer-to-string buffer is 15 characters. Numbers requiring more
          than 15 digits are silently truncated. This is unreachable for line
          numbers within any realistic source file.
        </notable>
      </stderr-output>

      <process-termination order="4">
        The process is terminated by calling abort, which raises SIGABRT and
        generates a core dump if the system is configured to do so.
      </process-termination>

    </panic>

    <talloc-abort-handler order="2">
      When the memory management library detects an internal error (such as a double
      free or heap corruption), it calls this handler with a reason string. If the
      reason string is present, it is passed as the panic message. If the reason
      string is absent, the message "talloc abort" is used. The file is recorded as
      "&lt;talloc&gt;" and the line number as zero. The panic sequence then executes as
      described above.
    </talloc-abort-handler>

    <coverage-exclusion order="3">
      <notable reason="excluded from coverage">
        The entire panic handler is excluded from code coverage measurement. Because
        every execution path through the handler ends with process termination via
        abort, no test can observe a return and coverage cannot be collected.
      </notable>
    </coverage-exclusion>

  </behavior>

</specification>
