<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Pinned Documents">

  <topic-statement>
    Pinned documents are filesystem paths attached to an agent that are loaded
    and concatenated in order to form the agent's system prompt on every LLM
    request.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The pinned document list (storage, ordering, add, remove), the /pin and
      /unpin commands, validation behavior on add, duplicate detection, and
      database persistence of pin and unpin events.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Document cache">
      How file contents are read from the filesystem and cached in memory is
      covered by the document cache specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="System prompt assembly">
      How the pinned document list is consumed to assemble the system prompt on
      each request is covered by the LLM request specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <storage order="1">
      Each agent holds a dynamically sized array of path strings representing
      its pinned documents. Documents are stored in insertion (FIFO) order.
      The array grows by reallocation when a new pin would exceed capacity.
      On unpin, the removed entry's memory is freed and subsequent entries are
      shifted to fill the gap; the array is reallocated to the new exact size.
    </storage>

    <pin-command order="2">
      The `/pin` command with a path argument adds that path to the pinned list:

      1. If the path is already in the pinned list, the command reports that the
         document is already pinned and does nothing further (idempotent).
      2. If the document cache is available, the file is loaded to validate that
         it can be read. If the file cannot be found, a warning is displayed,
         but the path is pinned anyway. This allows pinning documents that do
         not yet exist on disk.
      3. The path is appended to the pinned array.
      4. A pin event is persisted to the database.

      The `/pin` command with no arguments displays the current pinned document
      list and takes no other action.

      <notable reason="missing files are pinned with a warning, not rejected">
        A path that does not exist at pin time is accepted and stored. The
        warning is informational only. The missing document will be silently
        skipped during system prompt assembly on subsequent requests.
      </notable>
    </pin-command>

    <unpin-command order="3">
      The `/unpin` command requires a path argument. It performs an exact string
      match against the pinned list. If the path is not found, a "not pinned"
      message is displayed and the command returns without error. If found, the
      entry is removed and the array is compacted. A corresponding unpin event
      is persisted to the database.

      Failing to provide a path argument is an error.
    </unpin-command>

    <persistence order="4">
      Pin and unpin events are recorded in the database as command events with
      a JSON payload containing the command name and the path argument. These
      records are replayed during session restoration to reconstruct the pinned
      document list. Persistence failures are logged as warnings; the in-memory
      state is authoritative.
    </persistence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
