<specification topic="PostgreSQL Notifications">

  <topic-statement>
    The PostgreSQL notification subsystem subscribes to and unsubscribes from
    named channels, sends notifications to channels, and non-blockingly
    consumes incoming notifications delivered to the connection.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      LISTEN and UNLISTEN command execution, NOTIFY command execution,
      connection socket file descriptor access for select()-based monitoring,
      and non-blocking notification consumption with callback dispatch.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Database Connection">
      The underlying PostgreSQL connection is managed by the database
      connection module. This topic uses that connection but does not manage
      its lifecycle.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <listen order="1">
      Subscribes the connection to a named notification channel by executing
      a LISTEN statement. The channel name is double-quoted in the SQL text.
      If the query fails, an IO error is returned. On success, the connection
      will receive notifications published on that channel.
    </listen>

    <unlisten order="2">
      Unsubscribes the connection from a named channel by executing an
      UNLISTEN statement. Identical error handling to the listen operation.
      After a successful unlisten, no further notifications from that channel
      are delivered to the connection.
    </unlisten>

    <notify order="3">
      Sends a notification on a named channel with a payload string by
      executing a NOTIFY statement. The channel name is double-quoted and
      the payload is single-quoted in the SQL text. If the query fails, an IO
      error is returned.

      <notable reason="no-payload-escaping">
        The payload is inserted into the SQL string with single quotes but
        without escaping. A payload containing a single quote or other special
        SQL characters will produce a malformed query.
      </notable>
    </notify>

    <socket-file-descriptor order="4">
      Returns the integer file descriptor of the underlying PostgreSQL
      connection socket. This allows the caller to include the connection in
      a select() or poll() call, enabling event-driven detection of incoming
      notifications without busy-polling.
    </socket-file-descriptor>

    <consume-notifications order="5">
      Processes all pending notifications on the connection in a non-blocking
      manner:

      1. Reads any available data from the connection socket without blocking.
         If this read fails, an IO error is returned immediately.
      2. Dequeues pending notifications one at a time. For each notification,
         the caller-supplied callback is invoked with the channel name and
         payload string as arguments. The notification is freed after the
         callback returns.
      3. Continues until no further notifications are queued.

      Returns the count of notifications processed as an unsigned integer in
      the OK result value.

      <notable reason="non-blocking">
        The consume operation does not block waiting for new notifications.
        It only processes notifications that have already arrived on the
        connection socket. Callers must include the connection file descriptor
        in a select() or equivalent before calling this function to avoid
        busy-polling.
      </notable>
    </consume-notifications>

  </behavior>

</specification>
