<specification topic="PostgreSQL Wrapper Seams">

  <topic-statement>
    The PostgreSQL wrapper seam layer provides build-mode-controlled substitution
    points for seven libpq operations, enabling test code to replace any operation
    with a controlled implementation without modifying production call sites.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The seven wrapped libpq operations, the dual-build mechanism that selects
      between inlined and overridable implementations, the weak-symbol override
      protocol for test code, and coverage exclusion for the debug-build bodies.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Database Connection">
      The actual PostgreSQL connection lifecycle, schema migration, transaction
      control, and teardown are covered by the Database Connection specification.
      This specification covers only the wrapper seam mechanism.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="PostgreSQL Client Library">
      The behavior of the seven underlying libpq functions — query execution,
      result inspection, socket access, input consumption, and notification polling
      — is defined entirely by the PostgreSQL client library. The wrapper seam
      adds no logic; it either delegates unconditionally (debug) or is eliminated
      entirely (release).
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Test Override Implementations">
      What test-supplied override functions do with their arguments, what values
      they return, and how they interact with the rest of a test are concerns of
      individual tests. This specification covers only the seam mechanism that
      makes overriding possible.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>

    <contract name="Wrapped Operations">
      The seven wrapped operations and their pass-through signatures:

      <field name="execute-command" type="query handle → result handle"
             note="executes a literal SQL command string on a connection" />
      <field name="execute-params" type="query handle + command + params → result handle"
             note="executes a parameterized SQL command; accepts parameter type OIDs, values, lengths, formats, and a result format selector" />
      <field name="get-cell-value" type="result handle + row index + column index → string"
             note="retrieves the text value of a single result cell" />
      <field name="get-result-status" type="result handle → status enum"
             note="retrieves the execution status code of a completed result" />
      <field name="get-socket" type="connection handle → file descriptor integer"
             note="retrieves the file descriptor of the underlying connection socket" />
      <field name="consume-input" type="connection handle → integer"
             note="processes any pending input available on the connection" />
      <field name="get-notifications" type="connection handle → notification handle or null"
             note="dequeues the next pending asynchronous NOTIFY notification, or null if none" />
    </contract>

  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <release-build-inlining order="1">
      When the project is compiled with the NDEBUG flag set, all seven wrappers
      are defined as static inline functions directly in the header. Each wrapper
      body is a single unconditional delegation to the corresponding libpq function,
      passing all arguments through without modification and returning the result
      unchanged. Because the functions are inline, the compiler eliminates them
      entirely; production binaries contain no wrapper call overhead and no
      additional symbol for any of the seven operations.

      <notable reason="header defines function bodies in release mode">
        In release builds the header file contains the complete function bodies,
        not just declarations. This is intentional: the inline keyword requires
        the definition to be visible at each call site. No separate compilation
        unit is involved for release builds.
      </notable>
    </release-build-inlining>

    <debug-build-weak-symbols order="2">
      When NDEBUG is not set (debug and test builds), the seven wrappers are
      compiled as weak symbols from a dedicated compilation unit. The header
      exposes only declarations in this mode. Weak symbols allow a linker to
      accept a strong-symbol override from any other translation unit linked
      into the same binary. If no override is present, the linker uses the weak
      definition, which delegates unconditionally to the corresponding libpq
      function, identical in behavior to the release inline.

      The weak-symbol approach is chosen over function pointers or dependency
      injection structs because it requires no changes at call sites and imposes
      no runtime overhead in builds where overrides are absent.

      <notable reason="override replaces the entire function, not a pointer">
        Test overrides work by providing a strong-symbol definition of the same
        name in the test translation unit. The linker selects the strong symbol
        over the weak one at link time. This means overrides are per-binary, not
        per-call-site, and a single override applies to all callers within the
        linked test binary.
      </notable>
    </debug-build-weak-symbols>

    <coverage-exclusion order="3">
      The debug-build compilation unit is bracketed by coverage exclusion markers.
      The seven function bodies inside it are excluded from line coverage
      measurement. Because each body is a trivial single-line delegation with no
      branches, including them would inflate denominator counts without providing
      meaningful coverage signal. All meaningful coverage data for these operations
      comes from the call sites and from override implementations in test files,
      which are not excluded.
    </coverage-exclusion>

    <override-protocol order="4">
      A test that needs to control one of the seven operations provides a
      strong-symbol function definition with the identical name and signature
      as the wrapped operation. No registration, configuration, or pointer
      assignment is required. The override is active for the entire duration
      of the test binary's execution; there is no mechanism to swap overrides
      between individual test cases within the same binary.

      Overrides may return synthetic result handles, error codes, or any
      other value appropriate to the scenario being tested. Because the
      underlying libpq is never called when an override is present, no
      database connection is required to exercise error handling paths that
      depend on these operations.

      <notable reason="some tests override the unwrapped libpq symbol directly">
        Certain libpq functions that are not themselves in the wrapper set —
        such as the error-message retrieval function, the result-clearing
        function, the row-count function, and the null-check function — are
        overridden by test code using strong-symbol definitions of the libpq
        names themselves rather than wrapper names. These functions were not
        included in the wrapper set, so tests that need to control them bypass
        the wrapper layer entirely and override the library symbol. This is
        a distinct override strategy from the one used for the seven wrapped
        operations.
      </notable>
    </override-protocol>

    <unsafe-function-ban order="5">
      The debug-build compilation unit includes a compile-time enforcement header
      as its final include. This header poisons a set of unsafe C standard library
      and string functions via a compiler pragma, causing any use of those banned
      symbols within the unit to be a compile error. None of the seven wrapper
      bodies use any banned function; the inclusion is a project-wide discipline
      applied uniformly to all implementation units.
    </unsafe-function-ban>

  </behavior>

</specification>
