<specification topic="Pretty-Printing Helpers">

  <topic-statement>
    The pretty-printing helpers append consistently formatted representations
    of typed values to a format buffer, producing human-readable indented
    output for debugging and testing.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Six output operations: structure header, pointer, size_t, uint32_t,
      string (with character escaping), and boolean.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Format Buffer">
      Output is appended to a format buffer. Buffer management, allocation,
      and write failure handling (panic on OOM) are covered by the format
      buffer specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <indentation order="1">
      Every output operation begins by appending a number of space characters
      equal to the indent level, producing the visual nesting of fields.
      An indent level of zero produces no leading spaces.
    </indentation>

    <structure-header order="2">
      A header line labels the start of a pretty-printed structure. It outputs
      the type name followed by the memory address of the structure in
      hexadecimal, on a single line.

      Format: `<type> @ 0x<address>`
    </structure-header>

    <pointer-field order="3">
      A pointer field displays a named pointer value. A null pointer is
      rendered as the literal token "NULL". A non-null pointer is rendered
      as its hexadecimal memory address.

      Formats:
      - `<name>: NULL`
      - `<name>: 0x<address>`
    </pointer-field>

    <size-t-field order="4">
      A size_t field displays a named unsigned size value in decimal.

      Format: `<name>: <decimal>`
    </size-t-field>

    <uint32-field order="5">
      A uint32_t field displays a named 32-bit unsigned integer in decimal
      using a portable format specifier.

      Format: `<name>: <decimal>`
    </uint32-field>

    <string-field order="6">
      A string field displays a named string value enclosed in double quotes,
      with non-printable and special characters escaped. A null string pointer
      is rendered as the literal token "NULL" without quotes.

      The string is iterated byte-by-byte for the specified length. Each byte
      is rendered as follows:

      - `\n` → the two-character sequence `\n`
      - `\r` → the two-character sequence `\r`
      - `\t` → the two-character sequence `\t`
      - `\` → the two-character sequence `\\`
      - `"` → the two-character sequence `\"`
      - Control characters (0x00–0x1F) and DEL (0x7F) → `\x` followed by
        two hexadecimal digits
      - All other bytes → the literal byte character

      Formats:
      - `<name>: NULL`
      - `<name>: "<escaped content>"`

      <notable reason="byte-oriented-not-utf8-aware">
        Escaping operates byte-by-byte. Multi-byte UTF-8 sequences are not
        treated specially; each byte is examined and escaped independently.
      </notable>
    </string-field>

    <bool-field order="7">
      A boolean field displays a named boolean value as either the literal
      token "true" or "false".

      Formats:
      - `<name>: true`
      - `<name>: false`
    </bool-field>

  </behavior>

</specification>
