<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Provider HTTP Lifecycle">

  <topic-statement>
    The provider HTTP lifecycle system manages the asynchronous HTTP request pipeline
    for streaming and non-streaming LLM API calls across all three providers, including
    socket readiness queries, transfer progress, timeout retrieval, completion detection,
    and request cancellation.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The vtable operations common to all three providers — socket file-descriptor set
      population, transfer progress driving, timeout retrieval, completed-transfer
      processing, streaming request initiation, non-streaming request initiation, and
      cancellation. Provider construction, including base URL resolution and API key
      handling. The distinction between providers that handle completion locally versus
      those that delegate entirely to the HTTP multi layer.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="HTTP multi handle internals">
      The underlying multi-handle that manages actual socket I/O, transfer state, and
      completion callbacks is an opaque subsystem. This specification covers only how
      providers interact with it through its public interface, not how it operates
      internally.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="SSE parsing">
      Raw bytes arriving over the wire are fed into an SSE parser. The parser's framing
      and event-extraction logic is out of scope; this specification covers only that the
      write callback feeds data to the parser and processes the resulting events.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Request serialization">
      The construction of request JSON bodies and URL paths is performed by
      provider-specific serialization modules. This specification records that
      serialization occurs as a step of streaming and non-streaming initiation, not how
      the body is constructed.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Response building">
      Assembling a final LLM response from accumulated streaming state is delegated to
      per-provider response modules and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Stream event processing">
      Provider-specific stream event handlers that interpret SSE event types and data
      payloads into typed stream events are out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Provider construction inputs">
      <field name="API key" type="string" note="copied into provider context; OpenAI additionally validates non-empty at construction time and returns an error if empty; Anthropic and Google do not validate emptiness at construction" />
      <field name="base URL" type="string" note="read from an environment variable at construction time; falls back to a hardcoded default if the variable is absent; Anthropic default is https://api.anthropic.com; OpenAI default is the hardcoded OpenAI endpoint constant; Google default is https://generativelanguage.googleapis.com/v1beta" />
      <field name="use_responses_api flag (OpenAI only)" type="boolean" note="when true, forces use of the Responses API regardless of model; OpenAI exposes a simple constructor that sets this to false and an extended constructor that accepts it explicitly" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Active stream context">
      <field name="SSE parser" type="opaque handle" note="created at stream start; receives raw bytes from the write callback" />
      <field name="stream context" type="opaque handle" note="created at stream start; holds per-provider accumulated streaming state passed to event handlers" />
      <field name="completion callback" type="function pointer" note="invoked exactly once when the transfer completes; carries success flag, HTTP status, response, error category, and error message" />
      <field name="completion flag" type="boolean" note="set to true by the HTTP-level completion callback when the transfer ends; read by info_read to trigger response building and callback invocation" />
      <field name="HTTP status code" type="integer" note="recorded by the HTTP-level completion callback; used in info_read to determine success and map error category" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Provider completion record">
      <field name="success" type="boolean" note="true when HTTP status is 200–299" />
      <field name="http_status" type="integer" note="raw HTTP status code from the completed transfer" />
      <field name="response" type="optional object" note="non-null only on success; built from accumulated streaming context; null when stream context is absent" />
      <field name="error_category" type="enumeration" note="AUTH for 401/403; RATE_LIMIT for 429; SERVER for 500+; UNKNOWN for all other non-success statuses; always UNKNOWN on success" />
      <field name="error_message" type="optional string" note="formatted as 'HTTP N' where N is the status code; null on success; allocated transiently and freed immediately after the callback returns" />
      <field name="retry_after_ms" type="integer" note="always -1 at this layer; retry-after header parsing is not performed here" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <provider-construction order="1">
      Each provider is instantiated by supplying a talloc parent context and an API key.
      Construction allocates a provider structure and an implementation context as a
      talloc child of that structure, copies the API key, resolves the base URL from the
      environment with a hardcoded fallback, and creates an HTTP multi-handle as a child
      of the implementation context.

      OpenAI construction validates that the API key is non-empty before allocating
      anything; an empty key causes an immediate error return. OpenAI also exposes a
      second constructor variant that accepts a boolean flag selecting between the Chat
      API and the Responses API.

      Anthropic and Google do not validate key emptiness at construction time.

      Google passes the API key in the request URL rather than in a header; this is
      reflected in request construction but not in the provider context layout.

      All three providers set the active stream slot to null at construction time.
      The active stream slot holds at most one in-flight streaming context at any moment.
    </provider-construction>

    <fdset order="2">
      The fdset operation populates read, write, and exception file-descriptor sets from
      the HTTP multi-handle and updates the caller's maximum file-descriptor value. All
      three providers implement this identically by delegating unconditionally to the
      multi-handle.
    </fdset>

    <perform order="3">
      The perform operation drives the HTTP multi-handle to make progress on all active
      transfers, updating the count of still-running handles. All three providers
      implement this identically by delegating unconditionally to the multi-handle.
    </perform>

    <timeout order="4">
      The timeout operation retrieves the multi-handle's recommended select timeout in
      milliseconds. All three providers implement this identically by delegating
      unconditionally to the multi-handle.
    </timeout>

    <info-read order="5">
      The info_read operation polls for completed transfers and processes any that have
      finished. Providers differ in whether they handle completion locally or delegate
      entirely to the multi-handle.

      <anthropic-info-read order="1">
        Anthropic calls the multi-handle's info_read through a mockable internal wrapper,
        then separately inspects the active stream slot. If the active stream exists and
        its completion flag is set, Anthropic performs local completion handling:

        1. A completion record is assembled. If the HTTP status is 200–299, success is
           true and the response is built from the accumulated streaming context (or null
           if no streaming context exists). If the status is outside 200–299, success is
           false, the response is null, the error category is mapped from the status code
           (401/403 → AUTH; 429 → RATE_LIMIT; 500+ → SERVER; else → UNKNOWN), and an
           error message is formatted as "HTTP N".

        2. The completion callback is invoked with the assembled record.

        3. The error message string, if allocated, is freed immediately after the
           callback returns.

        4. The active stream is freed and the active stream slot is set to null.
      </anthropic-info-read>

      <google-info-read order="2">
        Google follows an identical pattern to Anthropic: it calls the multi-handle's
        info_read directly (not through the mockable wrapper), then inspects the active
        stream slot, performs the same HTTP-status-to-error-category mapping, invokes
        the completion callback, frees the error message if present, frees the active
        stream, and clears the active stream slot.
      </google-info-read>

      <openai-info-read order="3">
        OpenAI delegates entirely to the multi-handle's info_read and performs no local
        completion handling. There is no active stream slot and no post-call inspection.
        Completion callbacks are registered directly with the multi-handle at request
        submission time and are invoked by the multi-handle itself when transfers complete.

        <notable reason="OpenAI completion is fully handled by the multi-handle">
          Because OpenAI registers its completion handlers with the multi-handle at
          request submission time, the multi-handle dispatches them directly without
          any provider-level interception. This differs from Anthropic and Google, which
          use a two-phase approach: the HTTP-level callback records the status and sets
          a completion flag, and the provider-level info_read then builds the response
          and invokes the application-level callback.
        </notable>
      </openai-info-read>

      <notable reason="HTTP status to error category mapping is uniform across Anthropic and Google">
        Both Anthropic and Google apply the same mapping: 401 or 403 → AUTH; 429 →
        RATE_LIMIT; 500 or above → SERVER; any other non-success status → UNKNOWN. This
        mapping is not applied for OpenAI at this layer.
      </notable>
    </info-read>

    <write-callback order="6">
      When streaming is active, the HTTP layer delivers incoming bytes to a write
      callback registered at stream start. The callback feeds the raw bytes into the SSE
      parser, then drains all complete events from the parser in a loop. For each event,
      the event type and data fields are extracted (defaulting to empty strings if
      absent) and passed to the provider's stream event processor. The event is freed
      after processing. The callback always reports that it consumed all bytes, even if
      the stream context or parser is absent.

      Google does not use the event type field; only the data field is passed to its
      stream event processor.

      The HTTP-level completion callback is separate from the write callback. It records
      the HTTP status code and sets the completion flag on the active stream when the
      transfer ends.
    </write-callback>

    <start-stream order="7">
      Initiating a streaming request follows this sequence:

      1. An active stream context is allocated as a talloc child of the provider
         implementation context.

      2. A provider-specific streaming context (holding accumulated event state) is
         created as a child of the active stream.

      3. An SSE parser is created as a child of the active stream.

      4. The completion callback, completion context, and HTTP status/completion fields
         are initialized on the active stream.

      5. The request URL is constructed from the base URL. For Google, the model name
         and API key are embedded as URL parameters. For Anthropic, the path is
         `/v1/messages`. For OpenAI, the path depends on the API mode (Chat or
         Responses) as determined by a per-model routing check.

      6. The request body JSON is serialized with streaming enabled.

      7. Request headers are assembled. Anthropic includes `Content-Type: application/json`,
         `anthropic-version: 2023-06-01`, an `x-api-key` header carrying the API key, and
         `Accept: text/event-stream`. Google includes only `Content-Type: application/json`
         and `Accept: text/event-stream` (no authorization header; the API key is in the
         URL). OpenAI headers are assembled by a shared header builder.

      8. The active stream is stored in the provider context.

      9. The HTTP request is submitted to the multi-handle with the write callback and
         HTTP-level completion callback both pointing to the active stream context.

      If URL construction or body serialization fails, the active stream is freed and the
      slot is cleared before returning the error.

      <notable reason="active stream lifetime spans from start_stream through info_read">
        The active stream is created during stream initiation and freed during
        info_read after the completion callback returns. It is not freed in the
        write callback or completion callback themselves.
      </notable>
    </start-stream>

    <start-request order="8">
      Non-streaming request initiation follows the same URL construction, body
      serialization, and header assembly steps as streaming initiation, but no write
      callback is registered with the multi-handle. The response body is received
      atomically rather than incrementally.

      For Anthropic and Google, non-streaming initiation is fully delegated to
      provider-specific request modules. For OpenAI, the request context is created
      inline, the API mode is selected, and the request is submitted with a completion
      handler that is called by the multi-handle upon transfer completion.

      <notable reason="OpenAI non-streaming uses the same completion delegation model as streaming">
        Both streaming and non-streaming OpenAI requests register their completion
        handlers directly with the multi-handle. The provider-level info_read is a
        pure delegation in both cases.
      </notable>
    </start-request>

    <cancel order="9">
      Cancellation removes all active requests from the multi-handle. For Anthropic and
      Google, cancellation additionally sets the active stream's completion flag to true
      if an active stream exists. This causes the next info_read call to process the
      stream as completed and invoke the completion callback with whatever partial state
      was accumulated.

      For OpenAI, cancellation only removes requests from the multi-handle. There is no
      active stream slot and no additional flag to set.

      <notable reason="cancel does not immediately free the active stream">
        After cancellation, the active stream for Anthropic and Google is not freed
        immediately. It persists until the next info_read call observes the completed
        flag and performs normal completion processing.
      </notable>
    </cancel>

    <internal-wrapping order="10">
      OpenAI exposes a set of internal wrapper functions for request serialization, URL
      construction, and header building. In debug builds, these wrappers are thin
      pass-throughs to the real implementations; in release builds, the real functions
      are called directly. This dual-build pattern allows tests to substitute mock
      implementations for the internal wrappers without affecting production behavior.

      Anthropic similarly wraps the multi-handle info_read call through a mockable
      internal seam, distinct from the non-wrapped version used by OpenAI and Google.
    </internal-wrapping>

  </behavior>

</specification>
