<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Provider Factory">

  <topic-statement>
    The provider factory validates a provider name, resolves its API credential,
    and returns an initialized LLM provider instance ready for use.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Provider name validation, credential resolution, dispatch to
      provider-specific constructors, per-agent instance caching, and cache
      invalidation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Credential loading">
      Credential resolution delegates to the credential loading subsystem with
      a null path (triggering default path discovery). This specification
      records what credential name is requested and what value is received —
      the credential loading internals are out of scope.

      <shared topic="Credential Loading">
        Credentials are loaded from `~/.config/ikigai/credentials.json` (or
        `$IKIGAI_CONFIG_DIR/credentials.json` if that variable is set),
        with environment variables applied as overrides. Only non-empty string
        values are accepted from either source. A missing file is not an error.
        JSON parse failures are silently ignored; in that case only environment
        variables contribute.
      </shared>
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Provider-specific construction">
      After credential validation, an OpenAI-, Anthropic-, or Google-specific
      constructor is called with the resolved API key. Whether that constructor
      succeeds, and what it allocates internally, is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Supported providers">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="one of exactly three values: 'openai', 'anthropic', 'google'; comparison is case-sensitive" />
      <field name="credential environment variable name" type="text" note="'OPENAI_API_KEY', 'ANTHROPIC_API_KEY', or 'GOOGLE_API_KEY' respectively" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <provider-creation order="1">
      A provider instance is created by supplying a provider name string. The
      following steps execute in strict order; the first failure stops processing
      and returns an error.

      <name-validation order="1">
        The name is checked against the list of three supported provider names:
        `openai`, `anthropic`, and `google`. Comparison is case-sensitive.
        If the name does not match any of the three, an invalid-argument error
        is returned immediately. No allocations have been made at this point,
        so no cleanup is required.

        <notable reason="case sensitivity">
          `OpenAI`, `ANTHROPIC`, and `Google` are not valid provider names.
          Only lowercase forms are accepted.
        </notable>
      </name-validation>

      <credential-resolution order="2">
        The credential loading subsystem is invoked to load all credentials.
        If loading fails (for example, because `HOME` is not set and the
        default path requires tilde expansion), that error is returned
        immediately.

        The provider name is mapped to its corresponding environment variable
        name, and the credential value for that name is retrieved from the
        loaded credentials. If the value is absent (neither the file nor the
        environment variable provided a non-empty value for this provider),
        an error is returned with a message naming the environment variable
        and the credentials file that should be used to supply the key.

        <shared topic="Credential Loading">
          Credential values are sourced first from the JSON configuration file
          and then overridden by environment variables. Empty environment
          variable values are treated as absent and do not override file values.
          Only non-empty string values from either source are accepted.
        </shared>
      </credential-resolution>

      <provider-dispatch order="3">
        The resolved API key is passed to the provider-specific constructor
        for the validated provider name. If that constructor fails, its error
        is returned to the caller. If it succeeds, the resulting provider
        instance is returned.
      </provider-dispatch>
    </provider-creation>

    <per-agent-caching order="2">
      Each agent holds at most one provider instance. The instance is
      created on the first request and cached for all subsequent requests
      within that agent's lifetime.

      <first-request order="1">
        When a provider instance is first requested for an agent, the agent's
        configured provider name is passed to the provider creation procedure
        above. If the agent has no provider configured, an error is returned.
        On success, the resulting instance is stored in the agent and returned.
      </first-request>

      <subsequent-requests order="2">
        When a provider instance is requested and one is already cached, the
        cached instance is returned immediately. No credential loading, no
        name validation, and no provider construction occurs.
      </subsequent-requests>

      <notable reason="provider instances are not shared between agents">
        Each agent creates its own independent provider instance. Two agents
        configured with the same provider name each hold separate instances
        with separate internal state and separate HTTP sessions.
      </notable>
    </per-agent-caching>

    <cache-invalidation order="3">
      The cached provider instance can be explicitly released. When released,
      the instance is freed and the cache slot is cleared. The next request
      for a provider instance triggers the full creation procedure again,
      including credential loading.

      Releasing the cache when no instance is cached is a no-op.

      <notable reason="invalidation is used when the provider changes">
        Invalidation is triggered when the agent's provider or model
        configuration changes at runtime, ensuring the next request creates
        a fresh instance with the new configuration.
      </notable>
    </cache-invalidation>

    <provider-enumeration order="4">
      The list of supported provider names can be retrieved as a null-terminated
      array of strings. The array is static and its contents never change at
      runtime.
    </provider-enumeration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
