<specification topic="Pthread Thread Wrapper">
  <topic-statement>Interceptable delegating wrappers over the two thread lifecycle primitives — creation and joining — that enable test-time failure injection without changing production behavior.</topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>Thread creation and thread join operations as interceptable seams</in-scope>
    <in-scope>Build-mode selection between zero-overhead inlining and weak-symbol overridability</in-scope>
    <boundary name="Thread semantics">The actual scheduling, stack allocation, and synchronization behaviors of the underlying thread primitives; this module delegates unconditionally and adds nothing</boundary>
    <boundary name="Thread consumers">Tool execution workers, wait-command workers, and REPL shutdown logic all use these wrappers but are described elsewhere</boundary>
    <boundary name="Mutex wrappers">Mutex primitives are a separate wrapper set described in the pthread mutex wrapper spec</boundary>
    <boundary name="Test mocking">Override of these seams in test code; this module only provides the seam, not the override</boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="ThreadCreateArgs">
      <field name="thread" type="pointer to platform thread handle, written on success" />
      <field name="attr" type="pointer to platform thread attribute object, or null for defaults" />
      <field name="start_routine" type="function pointer accepting a void pointer and returning void pointer" />
      <field name="arg" type="void pointer passed to start_routine" />
      <field name="return" type="int, zero on success, nonzero on failure" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="ThreadJoinArgs">
      <field name="thread" type="platform thread handle identifying the thread to join" />
      <field name="retval" type="pointer to void pointer to receive the thread's return value, or null to discard" />
      <field name="return" type="int, zero on success, nonzero on failure" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>
    <build-mode-dispatch order="1">
      In release builds (NDEBUG defined), both thread wrappers are compiled as static inline functions directly in the header. Each wrapper expands to a single call to the corresponding platform primitive with no overhead. No object file is produced for these wrappers in release mode.

      In debug and test builds (NDEBUG not defined), both thread wrappers are compiled as weak symbols in a separate translation unit. The header provides only forward declarations. Because weak symbols can be overridden by a strong symbol with the same name in another translation unit, test code can replace either wrapper with a custom implementation without modifying production sources.
      <notable reason="The header itself contains full inline bodies inside the NDEBUG guard — the .c file duplicates those bodies under the opposite guard. The two copies must remain identical; there is no compile-time check that they match.">In release builds the .c file compiles to an empty translation unit (every definition is inside the NDEBUG-false guard), producing no object code at all.</notable>
    </build-mode-dispatch>

    <thread-create-delegation order="2">
      The creation wrapper accepts a pointer to a thread handle, an optional attribute pointer, a start function, and an opaque argument pointer. It delegates immediately to the platform thread creation primitive, passing all four arguments unchanged. The platform's return code is returned directly; zero indicates the thread was created and its handle written to the output parameter. A nonzero return leaves the output handle in an unspecified state.

      The wrapper introduces no default attribute; passing null for the attribute parameter causes the platform primitive to apply its own defaults (detach state, stack size, scheduling policy, etc.).

      Callers always pass null for the attribute parameter, accepting platform defaults for all thread attributes.
    </thread-create-delegation>

    <thread-join-delegation order="3">
      The join wrapper accepts a thread handle and an optional pointer for receiving the thread's return value. It delegates immediately to the platform blocking-join primitive. The call blocks until the target thread terminates. The platform result code is returned unchanged.

      All callers in the codebase pass null for the return-value pointer, discarding the thread's return value. The wrapper does not enforce this; a non-null pointer is passed through to the platform.

      Join is called in three distinct contexts:
      — Normal tool completion: called after the completion flag is observed to be true, then the mutex-protected running and complete flags are cleared to false.
      — Interrupted tool completion: called after the interrupt flag is cleared, before discarding the result, then the same flag cleanup follows.
      — REPL shutdown: called if the tool thread is still marked running at the time the REPL context is destroyed, ensuring the thread is not orphaned at process teardown.
      <notable reason="The REPL destructor performs a non-mutex-protected read of the running flag before deciding to join. This is a potential data race if the worker thread is modifying that flag concurrently. The comment in the code acknowledges this as a known limitation (no pthread_cancel, deliberate wait).">There is no timeout on the join call at shutdown; if a background subprocess is permanently blocked, the process will hang indefinitely waiting for the thread.</notable>
    </thread-join-delegation>

    <coverage-exclusion order="4">
      In debug builds the entire implementation is marked for coverage exclusion. Because the wrappers are replaced by test-provided overrides during testing, the weak-symbol bodies are never executed under test and produce no coverage data.
      <notable reason="This is the intended pattern: the seam bodies exist only for production use, not for direct test exercise.">All lines of each thread wrapper body are excluded from coverage measurement even though they are compiled.</notable>
    </coverage-exclusion>
  </behavior>
</specification>
