<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Rendering Context">

  <topic-statement>
    The rendering context manages the terminal output buffer, converts logical
    text and cursor positions into ANSI escape sequences, and serializes the
    resulting framebuffer to the terminal (or, in headless mode, to a JSON
    representation for remote inspection).
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Output buffer management and growth strategy, newline-to-CRLF conversion,
      cursor position calculation from a byte offset (accounting for UTF-8
      width, ANSI sequences, and line wrapping), atomic rendering to the
      terminal, and headless framebuffer serialization to structured JSON.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer composition">
      How the seven display layers are stacked and clipped before being written
      into the output buffer is covered by the layer rendering specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="TTY setup">
      How the terminal is switched to raw mode and the alternate screen is
      managed is handled by the terminal subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Rendering context">
      <field name="terminal width" type="positive integer" note="terminal width in columns; fixed at context creation" />
      <field name="terminal height" type="positive integer" note="terminal height in rows; fixed at context creation" />
      <field name="terminal file descriptor" type="file descriptor" note="the TTY to write to; -1 in headless mode" />
      <field name="output buffer" type="dynamic byte array" note="accumulates ANSI escape sequences and text before the atomic write; never shrinks" />
      <field name="buffer used" type="non-negative integer" note="bytes currently occupied in the output buffer" />
      <field name="buffer capacity" type="positive integer" note="total allocated bytes in the output buffer; grows by 1.5× or to required size, whichever is larger" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <output-buffer-management order="1">
      All rendered content is accumulated in a dynamically growing byte array
      before being written to the terminal. When an append would exceed the
      current capacity, the buffer is reallocated to the larger of 1.5× the
      current capacity or the exact size required. The buffer never shrinks
      during a session.

      Rendering is atomic: a single render pass assembles all content into the
      buffer, then writes it to the terminal in one system call. This prevents
      visual flicker and partial-frame display.
    </output-buffer-management>

    <newline-conversion order="2">
      When text is appended to the output buffer, embedded newline characters
      (`\n`) are converted to carriage-return-plus-newline pairs (`\r\n`).
      This conversion is necessary for raw-mode terminals where the kernel no
      longer performs CR/LF translation. The required buffer space is
      pre-calculated by counting newlines before the append.
    </newline-conversion>

    <cursor-position-calculation order="3">
      Given a byte offset into a text string, the rendering context calculates
      the terminal row and column where the cursor should be positioned. The
      calculation iterates from the start of the text, maintaining a running
      column count and row count:

      - Newline characters reset the column to zero and increment the row.
      - ANSI CSI escape sequences (detected via the ANSI parser) are skipped
        without advancing the column.
      - Each UTF-8 codepoint is decoded and its display width (0, 1, or 2
        columns) is added to the column count.
      - When the column count reaches the terminal width, it wraps to zero and
        the row increments (to account for soft line-wrapping).

      The resulting row and column are converted to a 1-based ANSI cursor
      positioning sequence (`\x1b[row;colH`) and written to the output buffer.
    </cursor-position-calculation>

    <atomic-render-sequence order="4">
      A complete render to the terminal follows this sequence:

      1. The cursor is hidden (`\x1b[?25l`).
      2. The cursor is moved to the home position (`\x1b[H`).
      3. All layer content (already assembled by the compositor) is written
         to the output buffer.
      4. The cursor is repositioned to the calculated input cursor location.
      5. The cursor is made visible (`\x1b[?25h`).
      6. The entire output buffer is written to the terminal file descriptor
         in a single call.
      7. The buffer used counter is reset to zero for the next frame.
    </atomic-render-sequence>

    <headless-framebuffer-serialization order="5">
      In headless mode (no TTY attached), the output buffer is serialized to
      structured JSON instead of being written to a file descriptor. The
      serializer:

      1. Parses the ANSI escape sequences in the buffer to extract per-character
         styling attributes (foreground color, bold, dim, reverse video).
      2. Groups consecutive characters that share the same styling into spans.
      3. Reconstructs line structure by detecting carriage-return-plus-newline
         sequences.
      4. Extracts the cursor position from the ANSI cursor positioning sequence.
      5. Emits a JSON object containing an array of rows (each row being an
         array of styled spans) and the cursor position.

      This JSON representation is what the control socket client reads when a
      remote process calls the read-framebuffer operation.
    </headless-framebuffer-serialization>

    <last-row-handling order="6">
      When the last rendered row of content exactly fills the terminal's last
      physical row, writing a trailing CRLF would cause the terminal to scroll.
      This is detected and suppressed: the CRLF that would follow the final row
      is omitted, preventing unintended scrolling of the terminal display.
    </last-row-handling>

  </behavior>

</specification>
