<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="REPL Tool Execution">

  <topic-statement>
    The REPL tool execution system runs tool calls requested by the REPL
    (synchronously) or by the LLM (asynchronously on a worker thread), persisting
    both the tool call and its result to the conversation history and scrollback.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Synchronous REPL-driven tool execution, asynchronous LLM-driven tool
      execution (thread start, worker logic, and completion harvest), thinking
      block preservation in tool call messages, the on-complete hook lifecycle,
      and thread state cleanup.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool dispatch and result wrapping">
      How the tool registry is consulted, how an external tool is forked and
      executed, and how the raw result is wrapped in a standard envelope are
      handled by the tool execution and tool wrapper subsystems and are out of
      scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent state machine">
      The transitions between idle, waiting-for-LLM, and executing-tool states
      are handled by the agent state machine and are out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="LLM response handling">
      How the LLM streaming response is parsed to detect a tool call and how
      thinking blocks are accumulated during streaming are out of scope here.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool loop continuation">
      How the conversation is resubmitted to the LLM after a tool result is
      recorded is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Pending tool call">
      <field name="id" type="text" note="provider-assigned tool call identifier" />
      <field name="name" type="text" note="the tool's callable name" />
      <field name="arguments" type="text" note="JSON-encoded argument object" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool thread context">
      <field name="tool name" type="text"
             note="deep-copied from pending tool call at thread start; owned by the thread context" />
      <field name="arguments" type="text"
             note="deep-copied from pending tool call at thread start; owned by the thread context" />
      <field name="agent reference" type="pointer"
             note="live pointer to the agent context; used by internal tool handlers" />
      <field name="registry reference" type="pointer"
             note="live pointer to the shared tool registry" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <synchronous-execution order="1">
      When the REPL itself drives a tool call (as opposed to an LLM response),
      execution is performed synchronously on the main thread without spawning
      a worker.

      The pending tool call is retrieved from the agent. The tool is dispatched
      directly to the external execution path (no registry lookup for internal
      tools occurs in this path). The result is returned immediately.

      A tool call message is created from the pending call's identifier, name,
      and arguments, with no thinking blocks. The message is appended to the
      conversation.

      A tool result message is created from the identifier and the result
      output. It is appended to the conversation.

      Both messages are rendered to the scrollback buffer and persisted to the
      database. The data payload stored alongside the tool call record contains
      no thinking blocks.

      The pending tool call is freed and cleared after persistence.

      <notable reason="no thinking blocks in synchronous path">
        The synchronous path always creates the tool call message without
        thinking or redacted-thinking blocks. Thinking accumulation only occurs
        during LLM streaming, which does not apply to REPL-driven tool calls.
      </notable>
    </synchronous-execution>

    <async-start order="2">
      When an LLM response requests a tool call, asynchronous execution is
      initiated on the current agent.

      Before the thread is created, the on-complete hook for the requested tool
      is looked up in the registry and stored on the agent. If the tool is not
      found in the registry or the registry is absent, the on-complete hook is
      set to null.

      A thread-owned allocation context is created. Within it, the tool name
      and arguments are deep-copied from the pending tool call so that the
      worker thread has stable, immutable access to its inputs for its entire
      lifetime.

      The completion flag is set to false and the running flag is set to true
      under the mutex before the thread is spawned. The agent is then
      transitioned to the executing-tool state.

      If thread creation fails, the running flag is cleared under the mutex and
      the application panics.

      <notable reason="on-complete hook is stashed before thread creation">
        The hook lookup happens once at thread start, not at completion time.
        This ensures the hook stored on the agent matches the tool that was
        actually launched, even if the registry were modified concurrently.
      </notable>
    </async-start>

    <worker-thread order="3">
      The worker thread runs concurrently with the main event loop.

      The tool name is looked up in the registry. If an internal tool is found,
      its handler is called directly with the thread-owned allocation context,
      the agent context, and the argument string. The handler must return a
      non-null JSON result string; if it returns null, a failure envelope is
      produced instead.

      If no internal tool is found, the tool name is dispatched to the external
      execution path, which forks and execs the tool process.

      After the result is obtained by either path, it is stored in a shared
      field on the agent. The completion flag is then set to true under the
      mutex, signaling the main loop.

      <notable reason="result is stored in a shared agent field">
        The worker thread writes the result pointer directly to a field on the
        agent context. Ownership of this allocation is transferred to the main
        thread when the thread is joined during the completion phase.
      </notable>
    </worker-thread>

    <async-complete order="4">
      Completion is performed on the main thread after the main loop detects
      that the worker thread's completion flag is set.

      The worker thread is joined. The result stored in the shared agent field
      is moved into a locally owned allocation before any further processing.

      A tool call message is created that includes any thinking content
      accumulated during the LLM streaming phase: the thinking text, the
      thinking signature, the redacted-thinking data, and the tool-call-specific
      thought signature are all incorporated into the message. After the message
      is created, each of these thinking fields on the agent is freed and cleared.

      The tool call and tool result messages are persisted to the database
      before being appended to the in-memory conversation array. Both messages
      are then rendered to the scrollback buffer.

      After persistence and rendering, the pending tool call is freed and
      cleared.

      The thread-owned allocation context is freed and cleared unless an
      on-complete hook is set. If a hook is set, the thread context is left
      intact because the hook may reference data allocated within it (such as a
      newly created child agent object). The hook is responsible for managing
      the lifetime of that data.

      Thread state fields on the agent (running flag, completion flag, result
      pointer, child process identifier) are all cleared under the mutex. The
      agent is then transitioned out of the executing-tool state.

      <notable reason="thinking blocks are preserved in the async tool call message">
        The tool call message for an LLM-driven tool includes the full thinking
        content from the preceding LLM response turn. This preserves the
        provider's thinking trace in the conversation record so it can be
        replayed and resubmitted on future turns.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="persistence precedes conversation append">
        Database persistence of both the tool call and tool result messages
        occurs before the messages are added to the in-memory conversation
        array. This ordering ensures the database record exists even if the
        in-memory append were to fail.
      </notable>

      <notable reason="thread context is not freed when an on-complete hook is registered">
        Freeing the thread context while the hook still holds references into
        it would produce dangling pointers. The thread context survives until
        after the hook has finished executing.
      </notable>
    </async-complete>

  </behavior>

</specification>
