<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="REPL Initialization">

  <topic-statement>
    The REPL initialization subsystem sets up all resources required for the
    interactive session — signal handlers, agent array, input infrastructure,
    and database session — in a fixed order, and tears them down on exit.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The ordered initialization sequence, per-step error handling, the
      headless-mode difference, and the shutdown sequence including tool-thread
      join.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Agent session restoration">
      How previously running agents are reconstructed from the database is
      covered by the agent session restoration specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Configuration loading">
      How the application configuration record is assembled is covered by the
      configuration loading specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Terminal setup">
      How the terminal is switched to raw mode and the alternate screen is
      managed is handled by the shared context and terminal subsystems.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <initialization-sequence order="1">
      Initialization proceeds in the following fixed order:

      <signal-handlers order="1">
        Signal handlers for terminal resize, user interrupt, and termination are
        installed before any other resource is allocated. This ensures that
        signals delivered during initialization are handled correctly.
      </signal-handlers>

      <repl-context order="2">
        The REPL context is allocated. A destructor is registered on the context
        to run the shutdown sequence when the context is freed.
      </repl-context>

      <agent-array order="3">
        The agent array is initialized as empty. The root agent context is
        created and added to the array as the first and current agent.
      </agent-array>

      <input-infrastructure order="4">
        Three independent resources are created:

        1. The input parser (decodes raw bytes into semantic input actions).
        2. The scroll detector (identifies mouse scroll events).
        3. The key injection buffer (holds programmatically injected keystrokes).
      </input-infrastructure>

      <database-session order="5">
        If a database connection is configured:

        1. An active session is retrieved or created. The session ID is stored
           in the shared context for use by all subsequent database writes.
        2. Dead agents from previous sessions are reaped from the database.
        3. The root agent's database record is verified or created.
        4. All agents previously marked as running are restored from the
           database into the agent array.

        If any database step fails, initialization aborts and returns an error.
      </database-session>
    </initialization-sequence>

    <headless-mode order="2">
      In headless mode, a headless terminal context is created before the shared
      context is initialized and passed into it. The headless terminal context
      accepts terminal writes without a real TTY, enabling the application to
      run without an attached terminal and be driven programmatically via the
      control socket.

      All other initialization steps are identical to normal mode.
    </headless-mode>

    <error-handling order="3">
      Different failure modes are handled differently:

      - **Memory allocation failures**: cause an immediate process abort (panic).
        There is no recovery path.
      - **Missing environment variables** (required path configuration): an
        error message is written to standard error and initialization returns
        a failure result.
      - **Configuration or credential load failures**: logged and returned as
        failure results.
      - **Database failures**: logged and returned as failure results; the
        terminal is explicitly cleaned up before the error propagates.

      On any failure result, the caller (the application entry point) exits
      with a non-zero status.
    </error-handling>

    <shutdown-sequence order="4">
      Shutdown is triggered when the REPL context is freed (either by normal
      loop exit or by an error path). The registered destructor:

      1. Checks whether a tool execution thread is currently running on the
         current agent.
      2. If a thread is running, waits for it to complete before proceeding.
         This prevents the tool thread from accessing freed memory.
      3. All other resources (agent array, input parser, scroll detector, key
         injection buffer) are freed implicitly by the talloc hierarchy when
         the REPL context is released.

      Terminal cleanup is handled separately by the shared context destructor,
      not by the REPL destructor, to avoid double-cleanup.

      <notable reason="tool thread is joined synchronously on exit">
        If a tool is executing when the user exits, shutdown blocks until the
        tool finishes. There is no timeout on this join; a tool that does not
        terminate will prevent clean shutdown indefinitely.
      </notable>
    </shutdown-sequence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
