<specification topic="REPL Event Handlers">

  <topic-statement>
    The REPL event handler system drives the select-based event loop by
    processing terminal input, HTTP completion events, and timer events to
    advance agent state and update the display.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Select timeout calculation, file descriptor set population, terminal
      byte reading and action dispatch, HTTP completion event processing per
      agent (including success, error, and interrupt paths), assistant message
      persistence, tool loop continuation, select timeout handling for scroll
      detector flushing, and minimum curl timeout calculation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Input Action Dispatcher">
      Terminal bytes are parsed and dispatched by calling the action
      dispatcher. Action handling behavior is external to this topic.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Provider vtable">
      HTTP I/O is driven by calling the provider's perform, info_read, fdset,
      and timeout operations. Stream and completion callbacks registered
      earlier fire during info_read. The internal mechanics are external to
      this topic.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database">
      Agent idle flag, message persistence, and LISTEN/NOTIFY broadcasts
      are performed via database helpers. Errors are silently ignored.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Response Helpers">
      Rendering individual scrollback events, storing response metadata,
      rendering usage events, and extracting tool calls are handled by
      external helpers called during request success processing.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <select-timeout-calculation order="1">
      The minimum positive timeout in milliseconds is chosen from:
      - 80 ms if the current agent's spinner is visible
      - 50 ms if any agent is in EXECUTING_TOOL state (agent states read atomically)
      - The scroll detector's pending-flush window (if a scroll detector exists)
      - The caller-supplied curl recommended timeout

      If all candidate values are negative (none applicable), 1000 ms is used.
      Agent states are read atomically to avoid data races.
    </select-timeout-calculation>

    <fd-set-population order="2">
      All three fd_sets (read, write, except) are zeroed. The terminal file
      descriptor is added to the read set if it is non-negative. The control
      socket adds its own descriptors via its own helper. For each agent with
      an active provider, that provider's fdset operation populates the sets.
      The highest file descriptor number seen is reported. If any provider's
      fdset operation returns an error, the function returns that error without
      processing remaining agents.
    </fd-set-population>

    <terminal-input-handling order="3">
      One byte is read from the terminal file descriptor. If the read is
      interrupted by a signal (EINTR), the function returns success. If the
      read returns zero or a negative value not due to a signal, the exit flag
      is set to true and the function returns success (signaling normal
      shutdown).

      On a successful byte read, the current CLOCK_MONOTONIC time is recorded
      as the render start timestamp. The byte is fed to the input parser to
      produce an action. The action is dispatched. If the action type is not
      unknown, a full frame render is triggered.
    </terminal-input-handling>

    <curl-event-processing order="4">
      For each agent in the agents array, HTTP completion events are processed.
      After processing the array, the current agent is processed again (to
      handle cases where it may not be in the array).

      <per-agent-http-processing order="1">
        If the agent has no active HTTP request or no provider, processing is
        skipped.

        The previous in-flight count is saved, then the provider's perform
        operation drives HTTP I/O and updates the in-flight count. The
        provider's info_read operation processes any completed transfers
        (invoking the registered completion callback for each).

        If the in-flight count is still positive or it was already zero before
        the call, no request has just completed — the function returns.

        If the agent's state is not WAITING_FOR_LLM (read atomically), the
        function returns without handling the completion.
      </per-agent-http-processing>

      <interrupt-path order="2">
        If the agent's interrupt-requested flag is true, interrupted LLM
        completion handling runs:
        - The interrupt flag is cleared.
        - Any partial assistant response and error message are freed.
        - The message array is scanned backward to find the most recent
          user message. All messages from that point forward are marked as
          interrupted.
        - The scrollback is cleared and rebuilt by re-rendering every message
          in order.
        - An "interrupted" record is persisted to the database.
        - The agent transitions to IDLE and the idle notification is broadcast.
        - If the agent is the current agent, a frame render is triggered.
      </interrupt-path>

      <error-path order="3">
        If an HTTP error message is present on the agent, it is prepended with
        "Error: " and appended to the scrollback as a single line. Both the
        error message and any partial assistant response are freed and set to
        null. Error messages are not persisted to the database.
      </error-path>

      <success-path order="4">
        If no error message is present:

        <assistant-message-storage order="1">
          If the agent has a non-empty assistant response string, a text
          message with assistant role is created and added to the in-memory
          conversation. The response is then persisted to the database as an
          "assistant" message with metadata (provider, model, thinking level,
          finish reason). If token counts are positive, a "usage" record is
          also persisted. Database errors are silently ignored.
        </assistant-message-storage>

        <response-buffer-free order="2">
          The assistant response string is freed and set to null.
        </response-buffer-free>

        <tool-call-branch order="3">
          If a pending tool call exists on the agent, tool execution is started
          and processing returns without continuing to the tool-loop check.
        </tool-call-branch>

        <tool-loop-continuation order="4">
          If the tool loop should continue (checked against max iterations and
          finish reason), the tool iteration counter is incremented and a
          continuation request is submitted to the provider.
        </tool-loop-continuation>
      </success-path>

      <post-completion-state-transition order="5">
        If the agent's state is still WAITING_FOR_LLM after success or error
        handling:
        - Token counts are recorded and the cache is pruned (on success only).
        - The agent transitions to IDLE.
        - The idle flag is updated in the database and the idle notification
          is broadcast.
        If the agent is the current agent, a frame render is triggered.
      </post-completion-state-transition>
    </curl-event-processing>

    <select-timeout-event-handling order="5">
      If a scroll detector exists, the current CLOCK_MONOTONIC time is read.
      The scroll detector's timeout check is called. If the result is a
      pending arrow-up, the arrow-up viewport action is triggered and a frame
      render follows. If the result is a pending arrow-down, the same for
      arrow-down.
    </select-timeout-event-handling>

    <curl-timeout-calculation order="6">
      All agents with active providers are queried for their recommended HTTP
      timeout. The minimum non-negative value across all agents is returned.
      If no agents have active providers, -1 is returned (no timeout needed).
    </curl-timeout-calculation>

    <idle-notification order="7">
      After any completion (success, error, or interrupt), if a database
      context is present, the agent's idle flag is set to true in the database
      and a notification is broadcast on the channel "agent_event_{uuid}"
      with the payload "idle". Errors are silently ignored.
    </idle-notification>

  </behavior>

</specification>
