<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="REPL Event Loop">

  <topic-statement>
    The REPL event loop multiplexes terminal input, LLM HTTP responses, control socket
    commands, and timed animations on a single thread using a unified select call with
    a dynamically calculated timeout.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The main loop structure, event source priority ordering, timeout calculation,
      frame rendering integration, signal handling integration, key injection draining,
      headless mode, and loop termination.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Frame rendering">
      What each frame render produces — layer composition, output buffer assembly, atomic
      TTY write — is covered by the layer rendering specification. This specification
      covers only when a render is triggered.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Key injection">
      The buffer that stores programmatically injected bytes and the byte-draining
      protocol are covered by the key injection specification. This specification
      covers only how the loop integrates with that buffer.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Individual event handlers">
      What happens when a terminal byte is parsed, an LLM response arrives, or a
      control socket command is processed is covered by the input parser, provider,
      and control socket specifications respectively.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Shared context">
      <field name="terminal context" type="reference" note="holds the TTY file descriptor and terminal dimensions; tty_fd is -1 in headless mode" />
      <field name="database context" type="reference or null" note="primary database connection; null if database is not configured" />
      <field name="command history" type="reference" note="in-memory history structure shared across all agents" />
      <field name="tool registry" type="reference" note="registered tools available to all agents" />
      <field name="fork pending" type="atomic boolean" note="true while a fork operation is in progress; prevents concurrent forks" />
      <field name="session id" type="64-bit integer" note="database session identifier; 0 if no database" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Output buffer">
      <field name="data" type="byte array" note="accumulated rendered content; grows on demand" />
      <field name="size" type="non-negative integer" note="bytes currently used" />
      <field name="capacity" type="positive integer" note="allocated bytes; doubles when an append would exceed it" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <loop-structure order="1">
      The loop runs until one of the termination conditions is met. Each iteration
      executes the following phases in strict order:

      1. Signal check: pending resize and quit signals are checked and handled
         before any blocking.

      2. Key injection drain: if the key injection buffer contains pending bytes,
         one byte is drained, fed to the input parser, an action is dispatched, and
         a frame is rendered if the action was recognized. The iteration then
         restarts immediately (skipping the select call) until the buffer is empty.

      3. Timeout calculation: the minimum of all active per-source timeouts is
         computed. See timeout calculation.

      4. I/O multiplexing: `select` blocks on the TTY file descriptor, the control
         socket file descriptors, and all in-flight LLM HTTP connection descriptors
         (registered by the provider) until one or more become ready or the timeout
         expires.

      5. If `select` returns with an error code of `EINTR`, signals are re-checked
         and the loop restarts; any other error breaks the loop.

      6. If `select` times out (ready count is zero), the scroll detector timeout
         handler is invoked.

      7. If the TTY file descriptor is ready and is a valid descriptor (not −1),
         one byte is read and processed through the input parser.

      8. Control socket events are dispatched to the control socket handler.

      9. LLM HTTP events are processed for all agents regardless of the ready
         count from `select`.

      10. If the current agent's spinner is visible, the monotonic clock is checked
          and the spinner frame is advanced if the interval has elapsed; if the
          frame advanced, a frame is rendered.

      11. All agents are polled for completed tool execution threads.

      12. All agents are checked for deferred fork prompts; any found are dispatched
          to the LLM.
    </loop-structure>

    <timeout-calculation order="2">
      The timeout passed to `select` is the minimum of all active per-source
      timeouts. A source contributes its timeout only when it is active; inactive
      sources are excluded from the minimum.

      - **Spinner animation**: 80 ms when the current agent's spinner is visible.
      - **Tool execution polling**: 50 ms when any agent is in the executing-tool
        state.
      - **LLM HTTP**: the minimum timeout requested by all active provider HTTP
        sessions (varies by provider and network conditions).
      - **Scroll detector**: a variable timeout managed by the scroll detector
        subsystem.

      If no source is active, the default timeout is 1000 ms. The loop never blocks
      indefinitely when any time-sensitive source is active.
    </timeout-calculation>

    <event-source-priority order="3">
      Event sources are handled in the following priority order within each
      iteration:

      1. Signals (SIGWINCH, SIGINT, SIGTERM) — checked synchronously before blocking.
      2. Key injection buffer — drained before `select` if bytes are pending; each
         byte triggers a full restart of the loop.
      3. Terminal TTY input — processed after `select` returns.
      4. Control socket — processed after terminal input.
      5. LLM HTTP (curl_multi) — processed after control socket, for all agents.
      6. Spinner animation timer — polled after LLM HTTP processing.
      7. Tool completion polling — polled after spinner check.
      8. Deferred fork prompts — polled last.

      <notable reason="curl events are processed regardless of select ready count">
        The ready count returned by `select` is ignored when processing LLM HTTP
        events. The provider's `perform` function is called for every agent on every
        iteration. The provider handles the case where no work is available.
      </notable>
    </event-source-priority>

    <frame-rendering-triggers order="4">
      A frame is rendered only in response to specific events, not on every
      iteration. The events that trigger a render are:

      - A key injection byte produces a recognized input action.
      - A terminal input byte produces a recognized input action.
      - The spinner frame advances.
      - An LLM response chunk is received for the current agent.
      - A tool execution completes for any agent.
      - A control socket scroll command is received.
      - A scroll detector timeout fires.
      - A SIGWINCH resize is handled.
    </frame-rendering-triggers>

    <headless-mode order="5">
      In headless mode the application runs without a terminal. The terminal context
      is initialized with a fixed size of 100 columns by 50 rows and a TTY file
      descriptor of −1.

      The differences from normal mode are:

      - The TTY file descriptor is never added to the `select` read set, so terminal
        input is never processed from a physical terminal.
      - Write errors when rendering frames are silently ignored (writing to −1 fails
        by definition but is expected).
      - Standard output and standard error are not redirected to `/dev/null`
        (unlike normal mode, where they are redirected to suppress interference with
        the alternate terminal screen).
      - The control socket is the only interactive I/O channel.

      The framebuffer is still assembled and stored on every render, making it
      available to the control socket `read_framebuffer` command.

      <notable reason="frame rendering still occurs in headless mode">
        Despite no physical terminal, every event that normally triggers a render
        still assembles a framebuffer. The write attempt fails silently. This ensures
        the framebuffer stored for control socket reads reflects the current state.
      </notable>
    </headless-mode>

    <signal-handling-integration order="6">
      Signal handlers set global volatile flags and return immediately. The loop
      polls these flags at the start of each iteration and after `select` returns
      `EINTR`.

      - SIGWINCH: the resize flag is cleared, terminal dimensions are re-queried
        via an ioctl, the stored dimensions are updated, and a frame is rendered.
      - SIGINT and SIGTERM: the quit flag is cleared, all cached provider instances
        are released, and the quit flag on the REPL context is set to trigger loop
        termination.

      <shared topic="Resize Handling">
        SIGWINCH sets a volatile flag. On the next loop iteration the flag is
        cleared, new dimensions are queried, and a re-render is triggered. This
        defers non-async-signal-safe operations out of the signal handler.
      </shared>
    </signal-handling-integration>

    <termination order="7">
      The loop exits when any of the following conditions becomes true:

      - The REPL quit flag is set (by a quit signal or a control socket exit command).
      - A terminal read returns zero bytes (EOF — terminal closed) or a non-`EINTR`
        error.
      - A fatal error is returned by `select`.

      On exit, the control socket is destroyed. A talloc destructor on the REPL
      context waits for any running tool execution thread to complete before
      releasing resources.
    </termination>

    <framebuffer-storage order="8">
      After each render, the assembled framebuffer (the complete sequence of terminal
      escape codes and text content that was written to the TTY) is stored on the
      REPL context, replacing the previous framebuffer. The cursor row and column at
      the time of the render are also stored. The control socket `read_framebuffer`
      command returns this stored buffer.
    </framebuffer-storage>

  </behavior>

</specification>
