<specification topic="Restore Toolset Replay">

  <topic-statement>
    The restore toolset replay reconstructs an agent's toolset filter from
    the database during session restoration, applying a priority cascade
    that checks for explicit toolset commands before falling back to fork
    event inheritance.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The two-step toolset reconstruction priority cascade (explicit command
      takes precedence over fork inheritance), string tokenization of the
      stored argument string, and JSON array extraction from the fork event
      snapshot.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Toolset Filter">
      The /toolset command that sets the filter during a live session, and
      how the filter is applied to tool registry entries in requests, are
      covered by the toolset filter specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent Restoration">
      The broader agent restoration orchestration is covered by the agent
      restore specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <priority-cascade order="1">
      Toolset replay queries the database for the agent's most recently
      created explicit toolset command. If found, that command's argument
      string is used to reconstruct the filter. If no such command exists
      and the agent has a parent UUID, the fork event snapshot is queried
      to inherit the toolset. If neither source exists, the toolset filter
      remains null (all tools allowed).

      <notable reason="most-recent-explicit-command-wins">
        Only the single most recent toolset command (by creation order)
        is replayed. Earlier toolset commands in the same session have no
        effect on the restored state. An explicit command always takes
        precedence over a fork event snapshot.
      </notable>
    </priority-cascade>

    <command-tokenization order="2">
      When an explicit toolset command is found, its stored argument string
      is tokenized using both spaces and commas as delimiters. Each non-empty
      token becomes one entry in the reconstructed toolset filter array. The
      array starts with capacity 16 and doubles when exhausted.
    </command-tokenization>

    <fork-event-inheritance order="3">
      When no explicit toolset command exists and the agent was forked (has
      a parent UUID), the oldest fork event for this agent is queried. The
      toolset_filter field in the event's data JSON, if present and a valid
      array, is iterated. Each string element is appended to the agent's
      toolset filter array.

      <notable reason="oldest-fork-event">
        The fork event lookup selects the oldest event by creation order,
        using ascending sort with a limit of one. This is the event
        corresponding to the agent's creation, not any subsequent events.
      </notable>
    </fork-event-inheritance>

    <boundary-independence order="4">
      Toolset replay is not bounded by /clear events. The most recent explicit
      toolset command is found across the agent's entire history, including
      commands issued before any conversation clear. This ensures the toolset
      filter persists across clears.
    </boundary-independence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
