<specification topic="Restore Command Side-Effect Replay">

  <topic-statement>
    The restore command side-effect replay applies the observable consequences
    of model-change and fork events to in-memory agent state during scrollback
    reconstruction, keeping provider configuration and pinned documents
    synchronized with the replayed display output.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Model command effect application (provider and model field update,
      provider instance invalidation) and fork event pin/toolset extraction
      during scrollback replay.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Agent Restoration">
      The broader agent restoration orchestration — including pin replay,
      toolset replay, mark restoration, and token cache pruning — is covered
      by the agent restore specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Restore Pin Replay">
      The full pin replay pass (replaying all pin/unpin command events from
      the database across clear boundaries) is covered by the restore pin
      replay specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <invocation order="1">
      This replay step is invoked for each event in the scrollback
      reconstruction pass. Only two event kinds trigger side effects:
      "command" events of type "model" and "fork" events with role "child".
      All other event kinds are ignored.
    </invocation>

    <model-command-effect order="2">
      When a model-change command event is encountered, the effect is
      applied to the agent's in-memory configuration:

      1. The stored argument string is extracted from the event's data JSON.
      2. The provider is inferred from the model name in the argument string.
      3. The agent's provider field is updated to the inferred provider.
      4. The agent's model field is updated to the model name.
      5. The provider instance is invalidated (set to null) so a fresh
         connection will be created on the next LLM request.

      If the event's data JSON cannot be parsed or the argument field is
      absent, no side effect is applied and the event is silently skipped.
    </model-command-effect>

    <fork-event-effect order="3">
      When a child-role fork event is encountered, the agent's pinned
      document list and toolset filter are rebuilt from the event's snapshot:

      1. The pinned_paths JSON array is extracted from the event data.
      2. Any existing pinned document list on the agent is cleared.
      3. Each string in the pinned_paths array is appended to the agent's
         pinned list.
      4. The toolset_filter JSON array is extracted from the event data.
      5. Each string in the toolset_filter array is appended to the agent's
         toolset filter.

      If the event's data JSON cannot be parsed, no changes are applied
      and the event is silently skipped.

      <notable reason="fork-event-overwrites-earlier-state">
        Each fork event encountered during replay completely replaces the
        agent's pinned documents and toolset filter. Because events are
        replayed in chronological order, only the effects of the most recent
        fork event survive when the replay pass is complete.
      </notable>
    </fork-event-effect>

  </behavior>

</specification>
