<specification topic="Restore Pin Replay">

  <topic-statement>
    The restore pin replay reconstructs an agent's pinned document list from
    database events during session restoration, starting from the fork
    snapshot and then replaying all subsequent pin and unpin commands in
    chronological order.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Fork event pinned-path snapshot loading, chronological pin/unpin
      command replay, duplicate detection on pin, compaction on unpin, and
      the independence of pin replay from conversation clear boundaries.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Pinned Documents">
      The /pin and /unpin commands that modify the list during a live session,
      and how the pinned list is used to assemble the system prompt, are
      covered by the pinned documents specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent Restoration">
      The broader agent restoration orchestration is covered by the agent
      restore specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <fork-snapshot-load order="1">
      Before replaying individual pin/unpin commands, the agent's fork event
      is queried to obtain the initial pinned document snapshot. This snapshot
      represents the parent's pinned list at the moment of forking. Each path
      in the fork event's pinned_paths JSON array is appended to the agent's
      pinned list.

      For the root agent, the fork event contains the default initial pinned
      paths established at database initialization. For forked agents, it
      reflects the parent's state at fork time.
    </fork-snapshot-load>

    <command-replay order="2">
      All pin and unpin command events for the agent are queried and sorted
      in chronological order. Each event is processed in turn:

      <pin-event order="1">
        A pin command event adds the stored path to the pinned list. Before
        adding, the existing list is searched for an exact match. If the
        path is already present (due to fork snapshot or an earlier pin
        command), it is not added again. If absent, it is appended and the
        array reallocated to exact size.
      </pin-event>

      <unpin-event order="2">
        An unpin command event removes the stored path from the pinned list.
        A linear search by exact string match locates the entry. If found,
        the entry is freed, subsequent entries are shifted to fill the gap,
        and the array is reallocated to the new exact size. If not found,
        the event is silently ignored.
      </unpin-event>
    </command-replay>

    <boundary-independence order="3">
      Pin and unpin commands are replayed across the agent's entire event
      history, regardless of any /clear events that may have occurred. This
      makes the pinned document list persistent across conversation clears
      and session restarts.

      <notable reason="cross-clear-persistence">
        Unlike conversation messages (which are bounded by the most recent
        /clear), pinned document state accumulates all pin and unpin commands
        ever issued for the agent. A document pinned before a /clear remains
        pinned after the /clear.
      </notable>
    </boundary-independence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
