<specification topic="Scrollback Byte Ranges">

  <topic-statement>
    The scrollback byte-range system calculates the byte offsets within a stored
    text line that correspond to a requested span of terminal display rows.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Computing the start byte offset, end byte offset, and end-of-line flag for a
      given contiguous range of terminal rows within a single scrollback line, taking
      into account line wrapping and embedded newlines (segments).
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Scrollback Buffer">
      This topic reads line text, byte length, and layout metadata (segment widths,
      physical row count, terminal width) from the scrollback buffer. It does not
      modify any stored data.

      <shared topic="Scrollback Layout">
        A line's physical row count is the sum of segment row counts. Each segment
        row count is the ceiling division of that segment's display width by the
        terminal width, with a minimum of one row. The display width is measured in
        terminal columns accounting for ANSI sequences (skipped) and wide Unicode
        characters (counted by their column width). A zero-width segment still occupies
        one row.
      </shared>
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Byte-Offset Lookup">
      This topic delegates conversion from a display-column offset to a byte offset
      within the text to a shared byte-offset lookup operation. If that lookup fails,
      this topic treats the failure as a zero-byte offset.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Range Request">
      <field name="scrollback line" type="line reference" />
      <field name="terminal width" type="integer" note="columns; used for wrap calculation" />
      <field name="start row offset" type="integer" note="zero-based offset from the line's first display row" />
      <field name="row count" type="integer" note="number of display rows to include" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Range Result">
      <field name="start byte" type="integer" note="byte index into the line's text where rendering begins" />
      <field name="end byte" type="integer" note="byte index into the line's text where rendering ends (exclusive)" />
      <field name="is line end" type="boolean" note="true if the range extends to the final row of the line" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <computing-the-start-byte order="1">
      If the start row offset is zero, the start byte is zero — rendering begins at
      the first byte of the line's text.

      Otherwise, the calculation locates the byte within the text that corresponds
      to the beginning of the requested row. The line's layout is consulted to
      determine how many display rows each segment occupies (each segment is a
      newline-delimited portion of the text). Each segment's row count is the ceiling
      of its display width divided by the terminal width, with a minimum of one.

      Segments are consumed in order until enough rows have been accounted for. If
      the target row falls within a segment, the display columns advanced within that
      segment are computed (how many full terminal-width rows of that segment are
      skipped multiplied by the terminal width). A byte-offset lookup converts those
      display columns to a byte position within the segment's text.

      If the target row crosses multiple segment boundaries, the byte position of the
      start is located by counting newline characters in the text starting from the
      byte found by the lookup. The position immediately after the Nth newline (where
      N is the number of additional segment boundaries crossed) is the start byte.

      If the byte-offset lookup fails, the start byte is treated as zero.
    </computing-the-start-byte>

    <computing-the-end-byte order="2">
      If the end row offset (start row offset plus row count minus one) is at or
      beyond the last display row of the line, the end byte is the total byte length
      of the line's text. The is-line-end flag is set to true.

      Otherwise, the end byte is calculated using the same segment-walking logic as
      the start byte, but accumulating rows inclusively through the end row. The
      is-line-end flag is set to false.

      If the byte-offset lookup fails during end-byte calculation, the end byte is
      treated as zero.
    </computing-the-end-byte>

    <combined-range-calculation order="3">
      When a range is requested, the start and end bytes are computed separately and
      independently. The end row offset passed to the end-byte calculation is the sum
      of the start row offset and row count minus one.

      All three output values (start byte, end byte, is-line-end flag) are produced
      by a single call that internally delegates to the start and end calculations.
    </combined-range-calculation>

    <notable reason="zero-on-lookup-failure">
      If the underlying byte-offset lookup reports an error (e.g., the display column
      is out of range), the affected start or end byte is silently set to zero rather
      than propagating the error. This may produce incorrect render ranges without
      any indication of failure.
    </notable>

  </behavior>

</specification>
