<specification topic="Scrollback Text Utilities">

  <topic-statement>
    The scrollback text utilities measure the visible display width of text
    by excluding ANSI control sequences and applying Unicode character widths.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Display width calculation with ANSI sequence exclusion, newline counting,
      trailing whitespace trimming, and warning-formatted string construction.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="ANSI Parsing">
      Detection of CSI escape sequence boundaries is delegated to the ANSI
      parsing subsystem. This topic uses that detection but does not implement it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Scrollback Buffer">
      Where and how the returned widths and formatted strings are used in
      display layout is handled by the scrollback buffer and layout subsystems.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <display-width-calculation order="1">
      The visible display width of a text string is measured by walking the
      string byte by byte and applying the following logic at each position:

      1. If the current position begins an ANSI CSI escape sequence, the
         entire sequence is skipped. No width is counted for it. Scanning
         resumes after the sequence ends.
      2. Otherwise, the Unicode codepoint at the current position is decoded
         from its UTF-8 encoding. The codepoint's display width is added to
         the running total:
         - Combining characters and other zero-width codepoints contribute 0.
         - Narrow characters contribute 1.
         - Wide characters (such as CJK ideographs and many emoji) contribute 2.
         - Newline characters are explicitly excluded and contribute 0.
      3. If a byte sequence is not valid UTF-8, the invalid portion is treated
         as a single character of width 1, and scanning advances by one byte.

      The result is the sum of all per-codepoint widths, excluding ANSI
      sequences and newlines.

      <notable reason="ANSI sequences are completely invisible to width calculation">
        Terminal color and formatting codes embedded in the text do not
        affect the measured width. The display width reflects only the
        printable characters a terminal would render.
      </notable>
    </display-width-calculation>

    <newline-counting order="2">
      The number of newline characters in a string is counted by a separate
      pass that applies the same ANSI-skipping logic. CSI sequences are skipped
      before codepoint decoding, so escape sequences that happen to contain
      bytes with the value of a newline are not counted as newlines.

      Only the literal newline character is counted. Carriage returns and other
      line-ending variants are not counted.
    </newline-counting>

    <trailing-whitespace-trimming order="3">
      Trailing whitespace is removed from a string by scanning backward from
      the end and removing space, tab, newline, and carriage return characters.
      The scan stops at the first character that is not one of these four byte
      values.

      If the input is null or empty, an empty string is returned. The operation
      affects only the trailing portion of the string; leading whitespace and
      internal whitespace are preserved.
    </trailing-whitespace-trimming>

    <warning-formatting order="4">
      A warning string is constructed by prepending a warning symbol and a
      space to the provided text. If color output is enabled and a color code
      has been configured, the result is wrapped in ANSI 256-color terminal
      escape sequences using the configured color, with a reset sequence
      appended. If color output is disabled or no color code is configured,
      the plain symbol-prefixed string is returned without escape sequences.

      The warning symbol is the Unicode warning sign character (⚠). The
      input text must not be null.
    </warning-formatting>

  </behavior>

</specification>
