<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Scrollback Buffer">

  <topic-statement>
    The scrollback buffer stores an unbounded sequence of logical text lines in a
    single contiguous byte array and maintains pre-computed display layout data for
    each line to support efficient rendering and terminal-width reflow.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Text storage layout, line indexing, dynamic growth strategy, append operation,
      layout computation on append, O(n)-arithmetic reflow on terminal-width change,
      physical-row lookup by row number, and all utility operations on stored lines.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Scrollback layout computation">
      The per-line layout calculation — segment widths, physical row counts, display
      widths — is performed by the scrollback layout subsystem. This specification
      covers when layout is triggered and what the result is stored as, not the
      internal calculation.

      <shared topic="Scrollback Layout">
        The layout subsystem computes a segment-width array for a line by splitting
        the text at newline characters and measuring the display width of each
        segment in terminal columns. It uses this to compute the number of physical
        rows the line occupies at a given terminal width.
      </shared>
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Rendering">
      How stored lines are rendered to the terminal output buffer is handled by the
      layer rendering pipeline and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Scrollback buffer">
      <field name="text buffer" type="contiguous byte array" note="all lines stored end-to-end; each line's bytes followed by a null terminator; never shrinks" />
      <field name="text offsets" type="array of non-negative integers" note="byte offset in text buffer where each line's text begins; one entry per logical line" />
      <field name="text lengths" type="array of non-negative integers" note="byte length of each line's text, not including the null terminator; one entry per logical line" />
      <field name="layouts" type="array of layout records" note="pre-computed layout for each line; one entry per logical line" />
      <field name="line count" type="non-negative integer" note="number of logical lines currently stored" />
      <field name="line capacity" type="positive integer" note="allocated slots in the offset, length, and layout arrays; doubles when count would exceed it" />
      <field name="buffer used" type="non-negative integer" note="bytes currently occupied in the text buffer, including null terminators" />
      <field name="buffer capacity" type="positive integer" note="total allocated bytes in the text buffer; doubles when an append would exceed it" />
      <field name="cached width" type="integer" note="terminal width in columns used for the most recent layout calculation; -1 or 0 before first calculation" />
      <field name="total physical lines" type="non-negative integer" note="sum of physical_lines across all stored logical lines; updated on append and reflow" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Line layout record">
      <field name="display width" type="non-negative integer" note="total display width of the line in terminal columns, excluding ANSI escape sequences and newline characters" />
      <field name="physical lines" type="positive integer" note="number of terminal rows the line occupies at the cached terminal width" />
      <field name="newline count" type="non-negative integer" note="number of newline characters embedded in the line text" />
      <field name="segment widths" type="array of non-negative integers" note="display width of each segment between (or after) newlines; length is newline_count + 1" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <initialization order="1">
      A new scrollback buffer is created with an initial line capacity of 16 and an
      initial text buffer capacity of 1024 bytes. All counts start at zero. The
      cached width is set to indicate that no layout has been calculated.
    </initialization>

    <append order="2">
      A logical line is appended by supplying its text bytes and length. The
      following steps execute in order:

      <line-array-growth order="1">
        If the current line count equals the line capacity, the capacity is doubled
        and the three parallel arrays (text offsets, text lengths, layouts) are each
        reallocated to the new capacity. If any reallocation fails, an out-of-memory
        error is returned and no state is modified.
      </line-array-growth>

      <text-buffer-growth order="2">
        If the current buffer usage plus the incoming length plus one (for the null
        terminator) would exceed the buffer capacity, the capacity is doubled
        repeatedly until it is sufficient. If the reallocation fails, an
        out-of-memory error is returned.
      </text-buffer-growth>

      <text-copy order="3">
        The text bytes are copied into the text buffer at the current write position
        (buffer used). A null terminator byte is written immediately after. The text
        offset for the new line is set to the write position before the copy. The
        text length for the new line is set to the supplied length. Buffer used is
        advanced by length plus one (for the null terminator).
      </text-copy>

      <layout-on-append order="4">
        The layout subsystem is invoked to compute the layout record for the new
        line at the current cached terminal width. The computed layout is stored in
        the layouts array at the new line's index. The total physical lines counter
        is increased by the new line's physical lines count.
      </layout-on-append>

      <line-count-advance order="5">
        The line count is incremented. The operation returns success.
      </line-count-advance>

      <notable reason="null-terminated but length does not include terminator">
        Each line's text in the buffer is null-terminated for safe use as a C string,
        but the stored text length excludes the terminator. The pointer returned by
        the line-text accessor points directly into the buffer and is valid until the
        next modification.
      </notable>
    </append>

    <layout-reflow order="3">
      When the terminal width changes, physical row counts must be recalculated.
      The reflow operation iterates over all stored lines and, for each line,
      recomputes its physical row count using only the existing segment-width array
      and the new terminal width: each segment's physical rows is the ceiling of its
      display width divided by the terminal width, with a minimum of one row per
      segment. No UTF-8 scanning or newline counting is performed. The total
      physical lines counter is recomputed from the new per-line counts. The cached
      width is updated.

      If the cached width already equals the requested width, the operation is a
      no-op.

      <notable reason="reflow is O(n) in line count, not in text size">
        Because segment widths are pre-computed at append time, a resize requires
        only arithmetic over the stored integers. The text buffer is not scanned
        during reflow.
      </notable>
    </layout-reflow>

    <physical-row-lookup order="4">
      Given a physical row number (zero-indexed across the entire scrollback), the
      corresponding logical line index and the row offset within that line are found
      by scanning the layout array from the first line, accumulating physical row
      counts, until the target row falls within a line's range. The output is the
      logical line index and the row offset (how many rows into that line the target
      row falls).

      <notable reason="linear scan">
        Lookup is O(n) in the number of logical lines. There is no index structure
        for random access by physical row.
      </notable>
    </physical-row-lookup>

    <clear order="5">
      Clearing the buffer resets the line count, buffer-used, and total physical
      lines counter to zero. The segment-width arrays owned by each layout record
      are freed. The text buffer capacity and line array capacity are preserved; no
      memory is released. The buffer is ready to accept new lines immediately.
    </clear>

    <copy order="6">
      Copying from a source scrollback to a destination scrollback appends each
      source line to the destination in order by calling the append operation. The
      destination's cached width determines the layout of the copied lines, which
      may differ from the source's layout if the two have different cached widths.
    </copy>

    <line-text-retrieval order="7">
      A line's text is retrieved by supplying its zero-indexed line number. The
      operation returns a pointer directly into the text buffer and the line's
      byte length. The pointer is valid until the next append, clear, or copy
      operation on the same buffer. The caller must not free the pointer.
    </line-text-retrieval>

    <display-column-to-byte-offset order="8">
      Given a logical line index and a target display column, the byte offset within
      that line's text at which the target column begins is computed by walking the
      UTF-8 text, tracking the display column while skipping ANSI escape sequences.
      The walk stops when the column count reaches the target. If the target column
      exceeds the line's total display width, the byte offset of the end of the text
      is returned.
    </display-column-to-byte-offset>

    <no-capacity-limit order="9">
      There is no configured maximum for the number of lines or total bytes. The
      buffer grows without bound as lines are appended, limited only by available
      memory. An allocation failure during growth returns an error to the caller; the
      buffer remains in its pre-growth state.
    </no-capacity-limit>

  </behavior>

</specification>
