<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Scrollback Layout">

  <topic-statement>
    The scrollback layout system computes and maintains the terminal row count
    for each stored text line, recalculating that count arithmetically — without
    rescanning text — when the terminal width changes.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Buffer initialization, line appending with layout computation, terminal
      resize reflow, logical-line-to-physical-row lookup, and line text retrieval.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Text rendering">
      This specification covers which physical rows a line occupies. The
      computation of which bytes of a line correspond to a specific physical
      row — used when rendering a partial line during scrolling — is a
      separate concern.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Memory management">
      Allocation failure causes the process to abort immediately. No error is
      returned to the caller.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Scrollback buffer">
      <field name="lines" type="ordered list of logical lines" />
      <field name="terminal width" type="positive integer" note="cached value of the last width used for layout computation; used to detect when reflow is needed" />
      <field name="total physical rows" type="non-negative integer" note="cached sum of all stored lines' physical row counts" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Line layout">
      <field name="segment widths" type="array of non-negative integers" note="one entry per newline-delimited segment; entry count equals newline count plus one; immutable after initial computation" />
      <field name="display width" type="non-negative integer" note="sum of all segment widths; immutable after initial computation" />
      <field name="physical row count" type="positive integer" note="recalculated when terminal width changes; always at least one" />
      <field name="newline count" type="non-negative integer" note="count of embedded newline characters; immutable after initial computation" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <buffer-initialization order="1">
      A new scrollback buffer is created with an initial capacity for 16 lines
      and 1024 bytes of text storage. No lines are stored. The supplied terminal
      width is recorded as the current width. The cached total physical row count
      is zero.
    </buffer-initialization>

    <line-appending order="2">
      A logical line is added by supplying its text as a byte sequence. The
      text is stored verbatim, then a layout is computed for the line.

      <text-storage order="1">
        The text bytes are appended to a contiguous text store. If the store
        cannot hold the incoming bytes plus a null terminator, its capacity is
        doubled repeatedly until it can. An offset into the text store and a
        byte length are recorded for the new line.

        <notable reason="capacity never shrinks">
          Once grown, the text store never releases that capacity, even after
          lines are removed.
        </notable>
      </text-storage>

      <layout-computation order="2">
        A single pass over the text is performed to compute the line's layout.
        The text is divided into segments at each embedded newline character.
        For each segment, the display width is computed as the sum of the
        display widths of its characters.

        <display-width-rules order="1">
          ANSI CSI escape sequences are detected and consumed entirely without
          contributing any display width. Newline characters serve as segment
          boundaries and contribute no display width to any segment. Each
          valid Unicode codepoint contributes the number of display columns
          defined by the Unicode character width tables for that codepoint.
          Each invalid UTF-8 byte contributes exactly one display column.
        </display-width-rules>

        <segment-width-storage order="2">
          The display width of each segment is stored in an array. The array
          has exactly one more entry than the line's newline count. The stored
          segment widths are immutable and never modified after this initial
          computation. The sum of all segment widths is also stored as the
          line's total display width.
        </segment-width-storage>

        <physical-row-calculation order="3">
          The number of physical terminal rows the line occupies is derived
          from the segment widths and the current terminal width.

          For each segment whose display width is greater than zero, the row
          count for that segment is the smallest integer greater than or equal
          to the segment's display width divided by the terminal width (ceiling
          division).

          For each segment whose display width is zero, the row count for that
          segment is exactly one.

          The line's total physical row count is the sum of the row counts for
          all segments.

          <notable reason="empty line occupies one row">
            A line with no text has one segment with zero display width. That
            segment contributes one row, so an empty line always occupies
            exactly one physical row.
          </notable>

          <notable reason="trailing newline produces an extra row">
            A line ending with a newline character has an empty trailing
            segment with zero display width. That segment contributes one row.
            The text "hello\n" therefore occupies two physical rows at any
            terminal width wide enough to hold "hello" on a single row.
          </notable>

          <notable reason="each embedded newline adds at least one row">
            Every empty segment between consecutive newlines contributes one
            row. The text "A\n\nB" produces three segments — "A", "", and "B"
            — and occupies three physical rows at any terminal width of at
            least one column.
          </notable>
        </physical-row-calculation>

        <total-update order="4">
          The new line's physical row count is added to the buffer's cached
          total physical row count.
        </total-update>
      </layout-computation>

      <line-array-growth order="3">
        If the line array is at capacity, it is doubled before storing the
        new entry. The text offset and length arrays are grown in parallel
        to maintain the same capacity.
      </line-array-growth>
    </line-appending>

    <terminal-resize order="3">
      When a terminal width is supplied to ensure the layout is current, the
      supplied width is compared to the cached terminal width.

      <no-change-early-exit order="1">
        If the supplied width equals the cached width, the operation returns
        immediately. No computation is performed.
      </no-change-early-exit>

      <reflow order="2">
        When the supplied width differs from the cached width, the physical row
        count of every stored line is recalculated using its stored segment
        widths and the new terminal width. The same rules apply: zero-width
        segments contribute one row; positive-width segments contribute the
        ceiling of their display width divided by the new terminal width.

        The text bytes are not read during reflow. Only the stored, immutable
        segment widths are used.

        The cached total physical row count and the cached terminal width are
        updated to reflect the new values.

        <notable reason="reflow requires no text parsing">
          No Unicode decoding or ANSI sequence detection occurs during
          terminal resize. All per-segment display widths were captured at
          append time. Reflow performs only integer arithmetic on those
          stored values.
        </notable>
      </reflow>
    </terminal-resize>

    <physical-row-lookup order="4">
      A physical row number (zero-based from the top of the buffer) is mapped
      to a logical line index and a row offset within that line.

      The buffer is scanned from the first line. For each line, its physical
      row count is accumulated into a running total. When the running total
      first exceeds the requested physical row number, that line is the result.
      The row offset within the line is the requested row number minus the
      accumulated total of all preceding lines.

      If the requested physical row number is greater than or equal to the
      buffer's total physical row count, the lookup fails.
    </physical-row-lookup>

    <line-text-retrieval order="5">
      A logical line's stored text is retrieved by its zero-based line index.
      The operation returns a pointer into the text store at the line's recorded
      offset, along with the line's recorded byte length. The returned pointer
      remains valid until the buffer is next modified.

      If the supplied index equals or exceeds the number of stored lines, the
      retrieval fails.
    </line-text-retrieval>

    <buffer-clear order="6">
      All stored lines and their layout data are discarded. The line count,
      text byte usage, and total physical row count are reset to zero. The
      allocated capacity of the line arrays and the text store is preserved
      and not released.
    </buffer-clear>

    <buffer-copy order="7">
      All lines from a source buffer are appended to a destination buffer one
      by one in order. Each line undergoes a full layout computation against
      the destination buffer's current terminal width. The source buffer is
      not modified.
    </buffer-copy>

  </behavior>

</specification>
