<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Scroll Detector">

  <topic-statement>
    The scroll detector classifies arrow-key events as either mouse-wheel
    scroll events or keyboard arrow-key events using a timed state machine.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Detector creation, arrow-event classification, timeout computation,
      timeout-triggered flushing, and immediate flushing.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Event source">
      The caller delivers arrow events (up or down) paired with millisecond
      timestamps. The detector never reads the clock itself. The source of
      timestamps — system clock, event loop, or test harness — is outside scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Event consumer">
      The caller receives a classification result for each operation and
      decides what to do with it. How scroll and arrow events are acted upon
      is outside scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Arrow direction">
      <field name="direction" type="enumeration" note="two values: up or down" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Classification result">
      <field name="result" type="enumeration" note="one of: none, absorbed, scroll-up, scroll-down, arrow-up, arrow-down" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Timeout">
      <field name="milliseconds" type="signed 64-bit integer" note="-1 means no timeout needed; 0 means already expired; positive means milliseconds until flush" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <detector-creation order="1">
      A new detector is created. Its state is set to idle. The burst
      threshold is set to 5 milliseconds. The internal timer is initialized
      to zero. The pending direction is set to up as an arbitrary placeholder;
      this value is meaningless while the detector is idle.

      If the parent context is null, the process aborts before any allocation
      is attempted. If memory allocation fails, the process aborts immediately.

      <notable reason="comment contradicts implementation">
        The struct field storing the burst threshold carries the comment
        "Timer duration (20ms)," but the value assigned during creation is
        5 milliseconds.
      </notable>
    </detector-creation>

    <arrow-processing order="2">
      An arrow direction and a millisecond timestamp are submitted. The
      detector computes the elapsed time as the difference between the
      provided timestamp and the timestamp recorded when the current timer
      was last started.

      The detector's response depends on its current state and the elapsed
      time.

      <from-idle order="1">
        When idle, the detector records the arrow direction as the pending
        direction, records the current timestamp as the timer start, transitions
        to the waiting state, and returns none. The arrow is buffered; no
        classification is emitted.
      </from-idle>

      <from-waiting order="2">
        <second-arrow-within-threshold order="1">
          When waiting and the elapsed time is less than or equal to 5
          milliseconds, a mouse-wheel burst is detected. The detector emits
          a scroll-up result if the pending direction (the first arrow's
          direction) is up, or a scroll-down result if the pending direction
          is down. The timer start is reset to the current timestamp. The
          detector transitions to the absorbing state.

          <notable reason="direction based on first arrow, not second">
            The scroll direction is determined by the pending direction, which
            is the direction of the first arrow in the burst. The direction of
            the second arrow that triggered burst detection is not used and has
            no effect on the emitted result.
          </notable>
        </second-arrow-within-threshold>

        <timer-expired-new-arrow-arrives order="2">
          When waiting and the elapsed time exceeds 5 milliseconds, the
          pending arrow is treated as a keyboard arrow. The detector emits
          an arrow-up result if the pending direction is up, or arrow-down
          if the pending direction is down. The arriving arrow then replaces
          the pending direction, and the timer start is reset to the current
          timestamp. The detector remains in the waiting state.

          <notable reason="state stays waiting, not idle">
            The old pending event is flushed and the new arrow is immediately
            buffered in a single operation. The state never transitions through
            idle; it stays in waiting for the newly buffered arrow.
          </notable>
        </timer-expired-new-arrow-arrives>
      </from-waiting>

      <from-absorbing order="3">
        <additional-arrow-within-threshold order="1">
          When absorbing and the elapsed time is less than or equal to 5
          milliseconds, the arriving arrow is part of the ongoing burst. The
          timer start is reset to the current timestamp. The detector returns
          absorbed and remains in the absorbing state.
        </additional-arrow-within-threshold>

        <timer-expired-new-arrow-arrives order="2">
          When absorbing and the elapsed time exceeds 5 milliseconds, the
          burst has ended. The arriving arrow is recorded as the new pending
          direction. The timer start is reset to the current timestamp. The
          detector transitions to the waiting state and returns none.
        </timer-expired-new-arrow-arrives>
      </from-absorbing>

    </arrow-processing>

    <timeout-checking order="3">
      A millisecond timestamp is submitted. The detector checks whether a
      buffered event has been waiting longer than the burst threshold.

      <idle-check order="1">
        When idle, none is returned immediately. No elapsed time is computed.
      </idle-check>

      <within-threshold order="2">
        When waiting or absorbing, and the elapsed time is less than or equal
        to 5 milliseconds, none is returned. The timer has not expired.
      </within-threshold>

      <expired-from-waiting order="3">
        When waiting and the elapsed time exceeds 5 milliseconds, the single
        buffered arrow is classified as a keyboard event. The detector emits
        arrow-up if the pending direction is up, or arrow-down if the pending
        direction is down. The detector transitions to idle.
      </expired-from-waiting>

      <expired-from-absorbing order="4">
        When absorbing and the elapsed time exceeds 5 milliseconds, the burst
        window has closed. The detector transitions to idle and returns none.
        No event is emitted because the scroll event was already emitted when
        the burst was first detected.
      </expired-from-absorbing>
    </timeout-checking>

    <timeout-computation order="4">
      A millisecond timestamp is submitted. The detector reports how many
      milliseconds remain until a flush is required.

      <idle-computation order="1">
        When idle, -1 is returned. No timeout is needed.
      </idle-computation>

      <active-computation order="2">
        When waiting or absorbing, the remaining time is computed as the
        burst threshold minus the elapsed time.

        If the remaining time is negative, 0 is returned to indicate that
        the timer has already expired.

        If the remaining time is zero or positive, that value is returned
        as the number of milliseconds until the timeout fires.

        <notable reason="inconsistency with threshold boundary">
          When the elapsed time equals exactly 5 milliseconds, the remaining
          time is zero, and this operation returns 0 (indicating already
          expired). However, arrow-processing and timeout-checking both treat
          an elapsed time of exactly 5 milliseconds as within the burst window
          (their comparisons are inclusive). A caller that observes a return
          value of 0 here and immediately invokes timeout-checking with the
          same timestamp will receive none rather than a flushed event.
        </notable>
      </active-computation>
    </timeout-computation>

    <immediate-flush order="5">
      The detector is instructed to flush any pending buffered event
      immediately, regardless of the timer.

      <flush-from-waiting order="1">
        When waiting, the buffered pending arrow is emitted as a keyboard
        event: arrow-up if the pending direction is up, arrow-down if the
        pending direction is down. The detector transitions to idle.
      </flush-from-waiting>

      <flush-from-idle-or-absorbing order="2">
        When idle or absorbing, none is returned. The detector transitions to
        idle regardless of which of these two states it was in.

        <notable reason="absorbing flush discards burst state silently">
          When the detector is in the absorbing state, flushing transitions
          it to idle and returns none, without any indication that an
          in-progress burst was interrupted. The scroll event was already
          emitted when the burst was first detected, so no additional event
          is needed; however, any remaining arrows in the burst that have not
          yet been absorbed will begin a new detection cycle.
        </notable>
      </flush-from-idle-or-absorbing>
    </immediate-flush>

  </behavior>

  <state-transitions>
    <transition trigger="arrow received while idle">
      Idle → Waiting
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="second arrow within 5ms while waiting">
      Waiting → Absorbing (emits scroll event)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="arrow received after 5ms while waiting">
      Waiting → Waiting (emits keyboard arrow for old pending; new arrow becomes pending)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="timeout fires while waiting (check-timeout)">
      Waiting → Idle (emits keyboard arrow)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="flush called while waiting">
      Waiting → Idle (emits keyboard arrow)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="arrow received within 5ms while absorbing">
      Absorbing → Absorbing (returns absorbed)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="arrow received after 5ms while absorbing">
      Absorbing → Waiting (new arrow becomes pending; returns none)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="timeout fires while absorbing (check-timeout)">
      Absorbing → Idle (returns none)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="flush called while absorbing">
      Absorbing → Idle (returns none)
    </transition>
  </state-transitions>

</specification>
