<specification topic="Send Command">

  <topic-statement>
    The send command delivers a text message to a named agent's mailbox and
    wakes the recipient via a best-effort PostgreSQL notification.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Argument parsing, message body size enforcement, in-memory recipient
      validation, database recipient status validation, mail insertion, and
      conditional notification.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Mail Storage">
      How the message is persisted in the database is handled by the mail
      storage subsystem. This topic invokes insertion but does not implement it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database Notifications">
      The PostgreSQL NOTIFY mechanism is used to wake a waiting recipient. The
      notification channel semantics and consumption are out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Send Command Arguments">
      <field name="recipient identifier" type="string" note="agent UUID or unique prefix; extracted from command arguments" />
      <field name="message body" type="string" note="quoted string; maximum 4095 bytes" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <argument-parsing order="1">
      The command arguments are parsed in the form: a recipient identifier
      followed by a double-quoted message body. Leading and trailing whitespace
      between the two parts is skipped.

      The message body must be enclosed in double quotes. If the opening or
      closing quote is absent, a usage error is appended to the scrollback and
      the command completes without sending.

      The message body is extracted verbatim from between the quotes. If the
      body length reaches 4095 bytes (not counting the closing quote), a size
      error is appended to the scrollback and the command completes without
      sending.

      <notable reason="4095-byte hard limit">
        The maximum body length is enforced by a fixed-size stack buffer. A
        body of exactly 4095 characters is the maximum accepted; a body of
        4096 or more bytes is rejected.
      </notable>
    </argument-parsing>

    <in-memory-recipient-lookup order="2">
      The recipient identifier is looked up in the current REPL's loaded
      agent list. If no matching agent is found, an error is appended to the
      scrollback and the command completes.

      <notable reason="in-memory lookup does not filter by session">
        Agents from other sessions that are currently loaded in the REPL are
        eligible recipients. The in-memory lookup is not session-scoped.
      </notable>
    </in-memory-recipient-lookup>

    <database-recipient-validation order="3">
      The recipient agent's record is retrieved from the database. If the
      agent does not exist in the database, an error is returned. If the
      agent's status is not "running", delivery is refused with a "recipient
      is dead" error. Only running agents may receive mail.
    </database-recipient-validation>

    <message-body-validation order="4">
      An empty message body (zero bytes after parsing) is rejected. An error
      is returned without inserting any database record.
    </message-body-validation>

    <mail-insertion order="5">
      A mail message is created with the sender's identifier, the recipient's
      identifier, the body text, and a timestamp set to the current Unix time.
      The message is inserted into the mail storage. If insertion fails, an
      error is returned.
    </mail-insertion>

    <recipient-notification order="6">
      After successful insertion, a PostgreSQL NOTIFY is sent on the channel
      named for the recipient agent, using the payload "mail". This wakes any
      recipient that is blocking in a wait operation.

      The NOTIFY is sent only when the database connection is not currently
      inside a transaction. If the connection is in a transaction, the
      notification is silently skipped.

      If the NOTIFY itself fails, the error is silently discarded. Message
      delivery via the mailbox is considered successful regardless of whether
      the notification was sent.

      <notable reason="notification is best-effort">
        A recipient blocked in a wait operation discovers the message on its
        next polling interval (up to 50 milliseconds) if the notification was
        not delivered. No retry of the notification is attempted.
      </notable>
    </recipient-notification>

  </behavior>

</specification>
