<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Separator Layer Rendering">

  <topic-statement>
    The separator layer renders a single-row horizontal dividing line with optional
    embedded navigation context and optional embedded debug information.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Separator layer creation, visibility determination, height reporting, the rendering
      algorithm including baseline line characters, navigation context formatting,
      debug information formatting, visual-width-aware layout, and the post-line terminal
      sequence.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer protocol">
      The separator participates in the general layer rendering pipeline through the
      standard visibility, height, and render callbacks. How the pipeline invokes those
      callbacks and assembles the overall frame is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Display width calculation">
      Computing the number of terminal columns occupied by a byte sequence, excluding
      ANSI escape sequences, is performed by the scrollback display-width utility. This
      specification records that the utility is used to measure navigation and debug
      string widths, not how the utility operates.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Navigation context sourcing">
      The parent, sibling, and current agent UUIDs and child count are supplied by the
      caller through a post-creation configuration step. How those values are determined
      (agent registry lookups, tree traversal) is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Separator layer state">
      <field name="visible flag" type="pointer to boolean" note="raw pointer; visibility is determined by dereferencing this pointer at render time, not at creation time" />
      <field name="debug info" type="five optional pointers" note="scroll offset, first visible row, terminal height, document height (all size_t pointers), and render elapsed time (uint64_t pointer); all default to null at creation; all must be set together via a dedicated configuration call to enable debug display" />
      <field name="navigation context" type="struct of optional strings and count" note="parent UUID, previous sibling UUID, current UUID, next sibling UUID (all const char pointers, nullable), and child count (size_t); all default to null/zero at creation; set via a dedicated configuration call" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Navigation string elements">
      <field name="parent indicator" type="string" note="upward arrow followed by first 6 characters of parent UUID followed by '...' when parent UUID is non-null; dim upward arrow followed by '-' (ANSI reset after) when parent UUID is null" />
      <field name="previous sibling indicator" type="string" note="leftward arrow followed by first 6 characters of previous sibling UUID followed by '...' when non-null; dim leftward arrow followed by '-' (ANSI reset after) when null" />
      <field name="current agent" type="string" note="'[' followed by first 6 characters of current UUID followed by '...]'" />
      <field name="next sibling indicator" type="string" note="rightward arrow followed by first 6 characters of next sibling UUID followed by '...' when non-null; dim rightward arrow followed by '-' (ANSI reset after) when null" />
      <field name="child count indicator" type="string" note="downward arrow followed by the decimal child count when count is greater than zero; dim downward arrow followed by '-' (ANSI reset after) when count is zero" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Debug string format">
      <field name="off" type="integer" note="current scroll offset; the viewport_offset pointer value, or 0 if pointer is null" />
      <field name="row" type="integer" note="first visible row; the viewport_row pointer value, or 0 if pointer is null" />
      <field name="h" type="integer" note="terminal height in rows; the viewport_height pointer value, or 0 if pointer is null" />
      <field name="doc" type="integer" note="total document height; the document_height pointer value, or 0 if pointer is null" />
      <field name="sb" type="integer" note="scrollback rows; computed as document_height minus 3 when document_height is at least 3, otherwise 0; the subtracted 3 accounts for the separator, input, and status layers" />
      <field name="t" type="string" note="render elapsed time: formatted as an integer followed by 'us' when elapsed is below 1000 microseconds; formatted as a decimal with one decimal place followed by 'ms' when elapsed is 1000 microseconds or above" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      The separator layer is created with a name string and a pointer to an external
      boolean visibility flag. Debug info pointers are all initialized to null. Navigation
      context strings are all initialized to null and child count to zero. The layer
      registers three callbacks: visibility check, height query, and render.
    </creation>

    <visibility order="2">
      The visibility predicate dereferences the stored boolean pointer and returns its
      value. The flag is not copied at creation; changes to the pointed-to boolean are
      reflected immediately at the next render.
    </visibility>

    <height order="3">
      The separator always reports a height of exactly one row regardless of terminal
      width or content.
    </height>

    <rendering order="4">
      Rendering produces exactly one row by the following algorithm:

      <navigation-string-assembly order="1">
        If the current agent UUID is non-null, a navigation string is assembled by
        formatting all five navigation elements (parent indicator, previous sibling
        indicator, current agent, next sibling indicator, child count indicator) with
        single spaces separating them and a leading and trailing space, in that order.
        The resulting string is stored in a fixed 256-byte buffer.

        If the current agent UUID is null, no navigation string is produced and the
        navigation string has zero length.
      </navigation-string-assembly>

      <debug-string-assembly order="2">
        If the debug scroll-offset pointer is non-null, a debug string is assembled
        containing all six fields in the format described in the data contracts section.
        The time threshold for switching from microsecond to millisecond display is
        exactly 1000 microseconds (values of 999 and below use the microsecond form;
        values of 1000 and above use the millisecond form). The debug string is stored
        in a fixed 128-byte buffer with a leading and trailing space.

        If the debug scroll-offset pointer is null, no debug string is produced and the
        debug string has zero length.
      </debug-string-assembly>

      <line-character-count order="3">
        The visual widths of the navigation and debug strings are computed by scanning
        their bytes and excluding all ANSI escape code sequences. The total number of
        horizontal box-drawing characters to emit is the terminal width minus the sum
        of both visual widths. If the sum of visual widths is zero or equals or exceeds
        the terminal width, the full terminal width of box-drawing characters is emitted.

        <notable reason="visual width excludes ANSI codes">
          Navigation strings contain ANSI dim and reset sequences for absent-slot
          indicators. These sequences consume bytes but occupy no terminal columns.
          Using display-width calculation rather than byte length ensures the total
          rendered row width matches the terminal width exactly.
        </notable>
      </line-character-count>

      <output-assembly order="4">
        The row is assembled by appending to the output buffer in this order:

        1. The computed number of horizontal box-drawing characters (Unicode U+2500,
           three bytes each in UTF-8), one at a time.
        2. The navigation string, if non-empty.
        3. The debug string, if non-empty.
        4. A clear-to-end-of-line sequence followed by carriage return and line feed.
      </output-assembly>
    </rendering>

    <post-creation-configuration order="5">
      Two separate post-creation operations update the layer's state:

      The debug configuration operation accepts five pointers and stores all of them,
      replacing any previously stored pointers. All five are expected to be set together;
      the debug display is gated solely on whether the scroll-offset pointer is non-null.

      The navigation context configuration operation accepts four UUID string pointers
      and a child count value, storing them directly as raw pointers. The stored pointers
      alias the caller's strings and are not copied. Any or all UUID pointers may be null.

      <notable reason="stored pointers are not owned by the layer">
        Both debug pointers and navigation UUID pointers are raw aliases to memory owned
        elsewhere. The layer does not copy or free them. Callers must ensure the pointed-to
        data remains valid for the layer's lifetime.
      </notable>
    </post-creation-configuration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
