<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Session Startup">

  <topic-statement>
    The session startup sequence initializes all subsystems in a defined
    order, establishes two independent memory roots for the application and
    the logger, and installs handlers that enable cleanup on panic and
    abort.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The command-line argument processing, random seed initialization,
      the two-root memory architecture, the ordered subsystem initialization
      (paths, config, credentials, shared context, REPL), the panic and
      abort handler installation, the main event loop invocation, and the
      ordered cleanup and exit.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Paths initialization">
      What environment variables are required and how directories are
      resolved is covered by the paths specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Config loading">
      How configuration is read and parsed is covered by the configuration
      specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Credential loading">
      How credentials are sourced from file and environment is covered by
      the credential loading specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="REPL initialization">
      What the REPL setup entails — database connection, agent restore,
      terminal setup — is covered by the REPL initialization specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="REPL event loop">
      What happens during the main event loop is covered by the REPL event
      loop specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <argument-processing order="1">
      The only recognized command-line argument is `--headless`. When this
      flag is present, the application creates a virtual terminal context
      that accepts input and produces output without requiring a real
      terminal device. When the flag is absent, the application expects to
      run attached to a real terminal.

      All other arguments are silently ignored.
    </argument-processing>

    <random-seed-initialization order="2">
      The random number generator is seeded with a value derived from the
      current time combined with the process identifier. This reduces the
      probability of UUID collisions when multiple instances start at the
      same wall-clock second.
    </random-seed-initialization>

    <two-root-memory-architecture order="3">
      Two independent talloc memory roots are created and managed separately
      throughout the lifetime of the process:

      <logger-root order="1">
        The logger is allocated on its own root and initialized before any
        other subsystem. The logger root outlives the application root —
        it is freed last, after the session end event has been written. This
        ensures logging remains available during and after all application
        cleanup.

        Immediately after creation, a global panic logging pointer is set to
        the logger. This pointer allows crash handlers to write events even
        when no talloc context is available.
      </logger-root>

      <application-root order="2">
        All application state (paths, config, credentials, shared context,
        REPL, agents) is allocated under a separate root. When the main
        event loop completes, this root is freed first, releasing all
        application resources before the logger is touched.
      </application-root>

      <notable reason="logger is intentionally the last thing freed">
        The two-root design ensures that a crash during application cleanup
        can still produce a log entry. Freeing the application root first
        means the logger remains valid at the point where the final session
        end event is written.
      </notable>
    </two-root-memory-architecture>

    <subsystem-initialization-sequence order="4">
      Subsystems are initialized in strict order. Each failure stops the
      sequence, writes an error event to the log, frees both roots, and
      exits with failure status.

      <paths-init order="1">
        The paths subsystem validates that four environment variables are
        set and resolves the directories they name. Failure produces a
        message on the standard error stream in addition to the log event.
      </paths-init>

      <config-load order="2">
        The configuration is loaded using the resolved paths. Failure
        produces a log event and exits.
      </config-load>

      <credentials-load order="3">
        The credentials are loaded from the default path (derived from the
        config directory). Failure produces a log event and exits.
      </credentials-load>

      <shared-context-init order="4">
        The shared context is initialized with the config, credentials,
        paths, logger, and (if `--headless` was specified) a virtual
        terminal. Failure produces a log event and exits.
      </shared-context-init>

      <repl-init order="5">
        The REPL is initialized. If this step fails, the terminal is
        explicitly cleaned up before writing the log event and exiting. The
        terminal pointer on the shared context is also cleared to prevent
        a second cleanup during subsequent root teardown.

        <notable reason="terminal cleanup is ordered before root teardown on REPL failure">
          All other subsystem failures free the application root directly,
          allowing talloc destructors to clean up in order. REPL init is the
          only step that explicitly calls terminal cleanup first and clears the
          pointer, because the terminal must restore the primary screen buffer
          even if talloc destructors have not yet run.
        </notable>
      </repl-init>
    </subsystem-initialization-sequence>

    <panic-handler-installation order="5">
      After the REPL is initialized, two crash handlers are installed:

      <terminal-abort-handler order="1">
        A global pointer to the terminal context is stored. If an unhandled
        abort signal occurs, this pointer allows the abort handler to
        restore the primary terminal screen buffer before the process
        terminates, preventing the alternate screen from remaining visible
        in the user's terminal.
      </terminal-abort-handler>

      <talloc-abort-handler order="2">
        The talloc library's abort function is replaced with a custom handler.
        This intercepts allocation failures that talloc would otherwise handle
        by calling abort() directly, allowing the custom handler to write a
        panic log event and restore the terminal before the process ends.
      </talloc-abort-handler>
    </panic-handler-installation>

    <event-loop-execution order="6">
      The REPL event loop runs until it returns. Both success and error
      returns are handled: on success the exit code is zero; on error the
      exit code is non-zero and an error event is written to the log before
      cleanup begins.
    </event-loop-execution>

    <cleanup-and-exit order="7">
      Cleanup proceeds in the following order:

      1. The application root is freed, releasing all agent, REPL, shared
         context, config, credential, and path state. This triggers talloc
         destructors including terminal cleanup.
      2. The exit code is determined (success or failure).
      3. A session end event is written to the log with the exit code.
      4. The global panic logger pointer is cleared to prevent any subsequent
         crash from writing to a freed logger.
      5. The logger root is freed.
      6. The process exits with the determined exit code.

      <notable reason="session end event is written before logger root is freed">
        This ordering guarantees that the final log entry is durable before
        the logger is torn down.
      </notable>
    </cleanup-and-exit>

    <logging order="8">
      The logger records a session start event (with the working directory)
      at the beginning and a session end event (with the exit code) at the
      end. Error events are written for each failed initialization step and
      for any error from the REPL event loop. All events are written in JSONL
      format.

      <shared topic="Logger">
        Log entries are written as JSON lines to a rotating log file. The
        logger is a singleton with a global pointer used by panic handlers,
        and a per-context pointer used by normal application code.
      </shared>
    </logging>

  </behavior>

</specification>
