<specification topic="Shared Context Initialization">

  <topic-statement>
    The shared context initialization system sets up the terminal, dual
    database connections, tool registry, and command history in a fixed
    sequence, with graceful degradation at each optional step.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Terminal initialization (interactive and headless modes), stdout and
      stderr redirection, render system initialization, dual database
      connection setup, session identifier placeholder, command history
      loading, tool discovery and registration, internal tool registration
      ordering, and memory-managed cleanup registration.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Discovery">
      How tool executables are found in the filesystem and registered is
      handled by the tool discovery subsystem. This topic invokes discovery
      and provides the directory paths.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Database Connection">
      How each PostgreSQL connection is established and migrated is handled
      by the database connection subsystem. This topic provides the connection
      string and receives connection handles.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Terminal">
      How raw mode and the alternate screen buffer are configured is handled
      by the terminal subsystem. This topic initiates terminal setup.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <terminal-initialization order="1">
      Two paths are taken depending on whether a pre-created terminal is
      provided:

      <headless-path order="1">
        If a pre-created terminal handle is supplied, it is adopted as-is.
        Stdout and stderr are not redirected. This path is used when running
        without a real TTY, allowing the caller to supply a controlled
        terminal substitute.
      </headless-path>

      <interactive-path order="2">
        If no terminal handle is supplied, a new terminal is initialized,
        putting the TTY into raw mode and entering the alternate screen
        buffer. If terminal initialization fails, the shared context is
        released and an error is returned.

        After successful terminal initialization, stdout (file descriptor 1)
        and stderr (file descriptor 2) are both redirected to /dev/null. This
        prevents any library or system output from bypassing the alternate
        screen buffer and corrupting the display. The redirection is permanent
        for the process lifetime.

        <notable reason="stdio redirection is interactive-only">
          Stdout and stderr are only redirected when running interactively.
          Headless mode leaves the original file descriptors intact, making
          logging and debugging output visible to callers.
        </notable>
      </interactive-path>
    </terminal-initialization>

    <render-initialization order="2">
      The render system is initialized using the terminal's screen dimensions
      and TTY file descriptor. If initialization fails, the terminal is
      cleaned up and an error is returned.
    </render-initialization>

    <dual-database-connections order="3">
      Database connection is optional. If the configuration does not specify
      a host, database name, and user, both connection handles are set to null
      and no connection is attempted.

      If the configuration is complete, a connection string is constructed and
      two separate connections are established:

      <main-connection order="1">
        The first connection is the main database context used for all
        agent-specific operations: inserting messages, updating agent state,
        persisting events, and running schema migrations. If this connection
        fails, the shared context is released and an error is returned.
      </main-connection>

      <worker-connection order="2">
        The second connection is reserved for the wait synchronization system,
        which runs LISTEN/NOTIFY polling in a background thread. Having a
        separate connection prevents the blocking poll loop from interfering
        with main-thread database operations. If this connection fails, the
        shared context is released and an error is returned.

        <notable reason="both connections use identical parameters">
          Both connections are established with the same connection string,
          connecting to the same database. They differ only in which subsystem
          uses them, not in credentials or database.
        </notable>
      </worker-connection>
    </dual-database-connections>

    <command-history-loading order="4">
      The command history buffer is created and populated from the history
      file on disk. If loading fails, a warning is logged and initialization
      continues with an empty history. History loading failure does not abort
      startup.
    </command-history-loading>

    <tool-registration order="5">
      Tools are registered in three phases:

      <external-discovery order="1">
        Executable tool files are discovered from three directories in order:
        the system tools directory, the user tools directory, and the project
        tools directory. All discovered tools are registered in the tool
        registry. If discovery fails, a warning is logged and initialization
        continues with whatever tools were registered before the failure.
      </external-discovery>

      <internal-registration order="2">
        Built-in internal tools are registered after external discovery
        completes. Because registration overwrites any existing entry with
        the same name, internal tools take precedence over any external tool
        with the same name.

        <notable reason="internal tools shadow external tools">
          The registration order is intentional. An external tool file named
          the same as a built-in internal tool will be replaced by the
          internal implementation.
        </notable>
      </internal-registration>

      <registry-sort order="3">
        After all tools are registered, the registry is sorted alphabetically
        by tool name. This ordering is preserved for all subsequent lookups
        and display.
      </registry-sort>
    </tool-registration>

    <session-identifier order="6">
      The session identifier is initialized to zero. The actual session
      record is created later during REPL initialization, after the shared
      context is fully set up.
    </session-identifier>

    <cleanup-registration order="7">
      A cleanup function is registered with the memory management system.
      When the shared context is released, the cleanup function terminates
      the terminal session (restoring the original screen buffer and terminal
      mode) if one was established.
    </cleanup-registration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
