<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Signal Handling">

  <topic-statement>
    The signal handling subsystem intercepts terminal resize and process
    termination signals via atomic flags, deferring all consequential work
    to safe points in the event loop.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The three handled signals, the self-pipe-style atomic flag mechanism,
      the resize handling path (dimension query and redraw), the quit handling
      path (provider shutdown and loop exit), and event-loop integration.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="REPL event loop">
      The structure of the select-based event loop and how it processes other
      I/O events is covered by the REPL event loop specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Provider shutdown">
      How providers terminate in-flight HTTP connections is handled by the
      provider subsystem and is out of scope here.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <signal-disposition order="1">
      Three signals are intercepted:

      - **Terminal resize (SIGWINCH)**: signals that the terminal dimensions
        have changed.
      - **User interrupt (SIGINT)**: signals that the user pressed Ctrl+C at
        the terminal.
      - **Termination (SIGTERM)**: signals that an external process has
        requested shutdown.

      All three use the same mechanism: the signal handler is a minimal
      function that sets an atomic flag and returns immediately. No complex
      work is performed inside the handler.
    </signal-disposition>

    <atomic-flag-mechanism order="2">
      Each signal has a dedicated `volatile sig_atomic_t` flag. Setting this
      type is guaranteed to be atomic on the target architecture, making it
      safe to write from a signal handler and read from the main thread without
      locks.

      The flags are only written by signal handlers; they are read and cleared
      exclusively by the event loop at designated check points. This separation
      ensures that all consequential state changes occur in the event loop
      context, where it is safe to call arbitrary functions.
    </atomic-flag-mechanism>

    <resize-handling order="3">
      At the start of each event loop iteration, the resize flag is checked.
      If set, the flag is cleared and the terminal's current dimensions are
      queried from the kernel. The cached terminal dimensions are updated, and
      a full screen redraw is performed to reflow the display at the new width.

      <notable reason="SIGWINCH may fire multiple times during a resize drag">
        Terminals may deliver SIGWINCH repeatedly as the user drags the window.
        Each delivery sets the flag, but the event loop coalesces rapid
        deliveries into a single redraw because the flag is level-triggered
        (set-then-cleared), not edge-triggered.
      </notable>
    </resize-handling>

    <quit-handling order="4">
      Near the end of each event loop iteration, the quit flag is checked. If
      set (by either SIGINT or SIGTERM), the flag is cleared and the shutdown
      sequence runs:

      1. All active agents are iterated.
      2. For each agent, the provider instance (if initialized) is invalidated,
         which terminates any in-flight HTTP connections.
      3. The event loop's exit condition is set, causing the loop to terminate
         after the current iteration completes.

      <notable reason="Ctrl+C in the action dispatcher also sets the quit flag">
        The quit flag is also set by the action dispatcher when the user presses
        Ctrl+C while the REPL has keyboard focus. Both paths share the same
        flag and the same shutdown sequence.
      </notable>
    </quit-handling>

    <test-instrumentation order="5">
      Signal handler functions are excluded from code coverage instrumentation.
      OS signal delivery cannot be reliably triggered in unit tests, so
      coverage of these handlers is accepted as a structural gap.
    </test-instrumentation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
