<specification topic="Spinner Layer">

  <topic-statement>
    The spinner layer renders an animated single-row braille character
    indicator that advances on a time-based schedule while the agent awaits
    a response.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Spinner frame management, time-based frame advancement, visibility
      control, single-row rendering, and integration with the REPL event loop
      for animation timing.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer Cake">
      This topic provides three callbacks: visibility, height, and render.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent State">
      This topic reads and writes a spinner state record owned by the agent.
      The agent's state machine (IDLE / WAITING_FOR_LLM / EXECUTING_TOOL /
      dead) controls the visibility flag within that record.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="REPL Event Loop">
      The event loop reads CLOCK_MONOTONIC time and calls the time-based
      advance operation after each select() iteration. If advance occurs,
      the loop triggers a full frame re-render externally.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Spinner State">
      <field name="frame_index" type="numeric"
             note="current animation frame, 0–9" />
      <field name="visible" type="boolean" />
      <field name="last_advance_ms" type="int64"
             note="CLOCK_MONOTONIC timestamp in milliseconds of last advance" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Animation Frames (in order)">
      <field name="0" type="text" note="⠋" />
      <field name="1" type="text" note="⠙" />
      <field name="2" type="text" note="⠹" />
      <field name="3" type="text" note="⠸" />
      <field name="4" type="text" note="⠼" />
      <field name="5" type="text" note="⠴" />
      <field name="6" type="text" note="⠦" />
      <field name="7" type="text" note="⠧" />
      <field name="8" type="text" note="⠇" />
      <field name="9" type="text" note="⠏" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <frame-retrieval order="1">
      Returns the braille character at position (frame_index modulo 10) in
      the frame sequence. The modulo ensures the index is always valid
      regardless of the raw frame_index value.
    </frame-retrieval>

    <manual-frame-advance order="2">
      Increments frame_index by 1, then applies modulo 10. Frame 9 wraps
      back to frame 0.
    </manual-frame-advance>

    <time-based-frame-advance order="3">
      Computes elapsed time as (now_ms − last_advance_ms). If elapsed is
      greater than or equal to 120, the frame is advanced and last_advance_ms
      is updated to now_ms; the operation returns true. Otherwise no state
      change occurs and the operation returns false.

      <notable reason="backward clock">
        If now_ms is less than last_advance_ms (e.g., after a clock
        adjustment), elapsed is negative and no advance occurs. The spinner
        stalls until the clock catches up.
      </notable>
    </time-based-frame-advance>

    <visibility-check order="4">
      Returns the boolean visible flag from the spinner state.

      Visibility is set to true when the agent transitions from IDLE to
      WAITING_FOR_LLM. It is set to false when the agent transitions back to
      IDLE. During frame rendering, if the agent is dead, the visible flag is
      forced to false regardless of the stored value. If the agent is in
      WAITING_FOR_LLM or EXECUTING_TOOL state, it is forced to true.
    </visibility-check>

    <height-reporting order="5">
      Always returns 1. The spinner occupies exactly one terminal row.
    </height-reporting>

    <rendering order="6">
      The width, start_row, and row_count parameters are ignored.

      The current braille frame character (3 bytes UTF-8) is appended,
      followed by the literal text " Waiting for response..." (24 bytes),
      followed by an ANSI erase-to-end-of-line sequence and CRLF (5 bytes).
      No color sequences are applied. The content is the same for every frame
      except the leading braille character.
    </rendering>

    <animation-loop-integration order="7">
      When the spinner is visible, the REPL event loop's select() call times
      out after 80 milliseconds. After each iteration, the current
      CLOCK_MONOTONIC time is read in milliseconds and passed to the
      time-based advance operation. If the operation returns true (at least
      120 milliseconds have elapsed since the last advance), a full frame
      re-render is triggered. This produces approximately 8 animation frames
      per second.

      <notable reason="decoupled threshold">
        The select() timeout (80 ms) is shorter than the advance threshold
        (120 ms). The spinner does not advance on every timeout; it advances
        only when the 120 ms threshold is crossed. The shorter timeout
        provides timely checking without causing spurious advances.
      </notable>
    </animation-loop-integration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
