<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="SSE Parser">

  <topic-statement>
    The SSE parser processes a stream of raw byte chunks into discrete, parsed
    Server-Sent Events.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Parser creation, data accumulation, event extraction, and done-marker
      detection.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Streaming data source">
      The caller delivers raw byte chunks of any size, in any order, at any
      time. The parser makes no assumptions about chunk boundaries. The source
      of those bytes — HTTP response body, file, pipe — is outside scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Event consumer">
      The caller receives extracted events and decides what to do with them.
      How events are interpreted, routed, or acted upon is outside scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Parser state">
      <field name="buffer" type="byte array" note="accumulates all fed data; null-terminated; grows but never shrinks" />
      <field name="current length" type="unsigned integer" note="number of valid bytes in the buffer" />
      <field name="capacity" type="unsigned integer" note="total allocated size of the buffer" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Event">
      <field name="event type" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="null when no event: field appeared in the event block" />
      <field name="data" type="text" required="false" nullable="true" note="null when no data: field appeared in the event block" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <parser-creation order="1">
      A new parser is created with an internal buffer pre-allocated at 4096
      bytes. The buffer is zeroed, the current length is set to zero, and the
      buffer is null-terminated. The capacity is recorded as 4096.

      If memory allocation fails at any point during creation, the process
      aborts immediately. No error is returned.
    </parser-creation>

    <data-accumulation order="2">
      Raw byte data of a specified length is appended to the parser's internal
      buffer.

      <zero-length-feed order="1">
        If the specified length is zero, the operation completes immediately
        with no change to the buffer, regardless of what the data pointer
        contains.
      </zero-length-feed>

      <buffer-growth order="2">
        Before appending, the parser checks whether the current buffer can hold
        the incoming data plus a null terminator. If not, the capacity is
        doubled repeatedly until the buffer is large enough. The buffer is then
        reallocated at the new capacity. If reallocation fails, the process
        aborts immediately. The buffer never shrinks — capacity only increases.
      </buffer-growth>

      <byte-copy order="3">
        The incoming bytes are copied verbatim into the buffer immediately
        after any existing data. The current length is increased by the number
        of bytes fed. A null terminator is written at the new end position,
        maintaining the buffer as a valid C string even though the content may
        contain arbitrary bytes.
      </byte-copy>
    </data-accumulation>

    <event-extraction order="3">
      The parser scans its buffer for the earliest event-terminating delimiter
      and, when one is found, extracts and returns a parsed event. If no
      complete event is available, nothing is returned.

      <delimiter-detection order="1">
        Two delimiter forms are recognized: a pair of line feeds (`\n\n`,
        consuming 2 bytes) and a pair of CRLF sequences (`\r\n\r\n`,
        consuming 4 bytes). The parser searches for both simultaneously.

        The delimiter that appears earliest in the buffer is used. When only
        one form is present, that form is used. When both are present, the one
        at a lower byte offset wins. If neither delimiter is present, nothing
        is returned and the buffer is unchanged.

        <notable reason="CRLF cannot be confused with LF">
          The two-byte sequence `\r\n\r\n` does not contain `\n\n` as a
          substring, because the character at offset 2 within `\r\n\r\n` is
          `\r`, not `\n`. The two searches are therefore always independent and
          never refer to overlapping positions.
        </notable>
      </delimiter-detection>

      <buffer-consumption order="2">
        Once a delimiter is chosen, the event text is defined as all bytes
        before the delimiter's starting position. The consumed region — event
        text plus delimiter — is removed from the buffer. Any bytes that
        follow the delimiter are shifted to the beginning of the buffer, and
        the current length is updated accordingly. Capacity is not changed.
      </buffer-consumption>

      <line-parsing order="3">
        The event text is split into lines by scanning for `\n` characters
        only. Each line is classified by its prefix:

        <event-field-line order="1">
          A line at least 6 characters long that begins with the literal text
          `event:` causes the event type field to be set. The characters
          immediately after `event:` form the value. If the first of those
          characters is a space, exactly one space is stripped. All remaining
          characters up to the end of the line become the event type value. If
          the event block contains multiple `event:` lines, each one replaces
          the previous value; the last `event:` line in the block determines
          the final event type.

          <notable reason="carriage return included in value">
            Line splitting uses only `\n` as a separator. If a line ends with
            `\r\n` (CRLF), the `\r` is included in the computed line length
            and therefore becomes part of the extracted event type value. For
            example, an event block terminated by `\r\n\r\n` whose internal
            lines are also CRLF-terminated will produce an event type that ends
            with a carriage return character.
          </notable>
        </event-field-line>

        <data-field-line order="2">
          A line at least 5 characters long that begins with the literal text
          `data:` contributes to the data payload. The characters immediately
          after `data:` form the content. If the first of those characters is a
          space, exactly one space is stripped. All remaining characters up to
          the end of the line are the content for this line.

          The first `data:` line in a block initializes the data payload to
          that content. Each subsequent `data:` line appends a single `\n`
          character followed by the new content to the payload. The final data
          value is the concatenation of all data lines, joined by `\n`.

          A `data:` line with no characters after the colon (or only a single
          space that is stripped) contributes an empty string to the payload.
          If it is the first data line, the payload is initialized to an empty
          string. If it is a subsequent line, a `\n` followed by an empty
          string is appended (adding a trailing newline to the existing
          payload).

          <notable reason="carriage return included in value">
            The same carriage return inclusion described for event-field lines
            applies to data lines when internal lines use CRLF endings.
          </notable>
        </data-field-line>

        <unrecognized-lines order="3">
          Any line that does not meet the `event:` prefix condition and does
          not meet the `data:` prefix condition is silently ignored. This
          includes lines shorter than 5 characters, comment lines beginning
          with `:`, and lines beginning with any other field name such as `id:`
          or `retry:`.
        </unrecognized-lines>
      </line-parsing>

      <empty-event order="4">
        When the delimiter appears at the very start of the buffer (event text
        length is zero), the extracted event has a null event type and null
        data. No lines are processed.
      </empty-event>

      <returned-event order="5">
        The returned event is allocated on the caller-provided memory context.
        Its event type field and data field, when present, are also owned by
        that same event object and are released when the event is released. The
        event type is null when no `event:` line appeared in the block. The
        data is null when no `data:` line appeared in the block.
      </returned-event>
    </event-extraction>

    <done-marker-detection order="4">
      An event is tested to determine whether it signals end-of-stream.

      If the event's data field is null, the result is false.

      If the event's data field is exactly the 6-character string `[DONE]`
      (case-sensitive, with no leading or trailing whitespace), the result is
      true.

      For any other data value, the result is false.
    </done-marker-detection>

  </behavior>

</specification>
