<specification topic="Status Layer">

  <topic-statement>
    The status layer renders a 2-row display consisting of a horizontal
    separator line and the agent's current model identifier with thinking level.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Status visibility determination, fixed height reporting, and rendering
      of the separator and model/thinking-level content row.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer Cake">
      This topic provides three callbacks to the layer cake: visibility,
      height, and render.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent Fields">
      This topic holds live references (raw pointers) to three fields in the
      agent: a boolean visibility flag, a nullable model string pointer, and
      an integer thinking-level. Changes to these fields are reflected
      immediately on the next render call; the layer does not cache copies.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Thinking Level Values">
      <field name="IK_THINKING_MIN" type="integer constant"
             note="maps to string 'min'" />
      <field name="IK_THINKING_LOW" type="integer constant"
             note="maps to string 'low'" />
      <field name="IK_THINKING_MED" type="integer constant"
             note="maps to string 'medium'" />
      <field name="IK_THINKING_HIGH" type="integer constant"
             note="maps to string 'high'" />
      <field name="any other value" type="integer"
             note="maps to string 'unknown'" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <visibility-check order="1">
      Returns the current value of the agent's boolean visibility flag.
      The flag is initialized to true for all newly created agents.
    </visibility-check>

    <height-reporting order="2">
      Always returns 2 regardless of terminal width or any other input.
    </height-reporting>

    <rendering order="3">
      The start_row and row_count parameters are ignored; both rows are always
      written unconditionally.

      <row-1-separator order="1">
        The light horizontal box-drawing character (─, 3 bytes UTF-8) is
        repeated for the full terminal width. An ANSI erase-to-end-of-line
        sequence and CRLF follow.
      </row-1-separator>

      <row-2-model-status order="2">
        A robot emoji (🤖, 4 bytes UTF-8) followed by a space is appended first.
        Then a foreground color sequence for 256-color index 153 (soft blue)
        is generated.

        <no-model-path order="1">
          If the agent's model pointer is null, the soft blue color sequence,
          the literal text "(no model)", and an ANSI color reset are appended.
        </no-model-path>

        <model-set-path order="2">
          If the agent's model pointer is non-null, the thinking-level integer
          is converted to a string using the mapping in the data contract above.
          The soft blue color sequence, the model string, a forward slash,
          the thinking-level string, and an ANSI color reset are appended.
          Example output: "claude-sonnet-4/medium".
        </model-set-path>

        An ANSI erase-to-end-of-line sequence and CRLF follow.
      </row-2-model-status>
    </rendering>

  </behavior>

</specification>
