<specification topic="Talloc Wrapper Seam">

  <topic-statement>
    The talloc wrapper seam exposes hierarchical memory allocation operations as
    individually mockable link seams so that tests can intercept or replace any
    allocation call without modifying production code.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Five allocation wrappers: zero-initialized allocation by size, string
      duplication, zero-initialized array allocation, reallocation, and
      formatted-string allocation.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Memory Management">
      All allocations are performed within the hierarchical memory manager. The
      caller supplies a parent context for each operation; ownership of the
      resulting memory belongs to that context tree.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Test Infrastructure">
      Tests define strong-symbol replacements for any subset of these wrappers.
      The strong definition shadows the default weak symbol, giving the test
      full control over that operation's behavior (e.g., simulating allocation
      failure by returning NULL).
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <build-mode-selection order="1">
      The wrappers exist in two forms depending on the build configuration.

      In a debug or test build (when the NDEBUG macro is not defined), each
      wrapper is compiled as a weak symbol. A weak symbol has a default
      implementation but yields to any strong-symbol definition of the same
      name in the final link. This is the mechanism that makes individual
      wrappers replaceable in tests.

      In a release build (when NDEBUG is defined), each wrapper is a static
      inline function defined in the header. No separate compilation unit is
      involved; the call is inlined at every call site with zero runtime
      overhead and no exported symbol.

      <notable reason="Coverage exclusion">
        The debug-build compilation unit that contains all five wrapper bodies
        is marked to be excluded from line-coverage measurement. This is
        intentional: the wrappers are pass-through delegators, and measuring
        coverage of one-line forwarding functions adds noise without signal.
      </notable>
    </build-mode-selection>

    <zero-allocation order="2">
      Allocates a block of the requested byte size as a child of the given
      parent context. The entire block is zero-initialized before being
      returned. Returns NULL if the allocation fails.
    </zero-allocation>

    <string-duplication order="3">
      Allocates a null-terminated copy of the given string as a child of the
      given parent context. The length of the allocation equals the string
      length plus the null terminator. Returns NULL if the string pointer is
      NULL or if the allocation fails.
    </string-duplication>

    <array-allocation order="4">
      Allocates a contiguous block sized to hold the given number of elements,
      each of the given byte size, as a child of the given parent context.
      The total byte count is the product of element size and element count.
      The entire block is zero-initialized before being returned.

      <notable reason="Manual sizing, no type safety">
        Unlike a type-safe array macro, this wrapper accepts raw element size
        and count integers. The caller is responsible for passing the correct
        element size. The implementation multiplies the two values and calls
        the raw sized allocator — no overflow protection is applied to the
        multiplication.
      </notable>
    </array-allocation>

    <reallocation order="5">
      Resizes an existing allocation to the given byte size, keeping the
      allocation under the given parent context. The parent context must match
      the context under which the pointer was originally allocated. Returns the
      (potentially moved) pointer, or NULL if the reallocation fails. If NULL
      is returned, the original allocation is freed.

      <notable reason="Context parameter required by signature but unused internally">
        The underlying memory manager does not require the parent context to
        perform a reallocation — it tracks ownership internally. The context
        parameter is present solely to satisfy the link-seam calling convention
        and to allow tests that inject failures based on the context.
      </notable>
    </reallocation>

    <formatted-string-allocation order="6">
      Produces a formatted string as a child of the given parent context, using
      the given format string and variadic arguments. The behavior matches
      standard printf formatting. The variadic argument list is captured into
      a local argument list object, which is then forwarded to the underlying
      variadic-accepting allocator. The local argument list is cleaned up
      before the function returns. Returns the allocated string, or NULL if
      the allocation fails.
    </formatted-string-allocation>

    <test-override-pattern order="7">
      A test that needs to control a specific allocation operation defines a
      function with the exact same signature as the wrapper, without any weak
      attribute. Because the linker resolves strong symbols before weak ones,
      the test's definition becomes the active implementation for that link
      unit. The test can then consult thread-local or file-local flags to
      decide whether to forward the call normally, return NULL to simulate
      out-of-memory, or return a controlled substitute value.

      Thread-local state is used for the flags so that test binaries running
      multiple test suites in parallel do not interfere with one another.
    </test-override-pattern>

  </behavior>

</specification>
