<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Template Processor">

  <topic-statement>
    The template processor substitutes named variable placeholders in text with
    values drawn from agent context, configuration, environment variables, and
    runtime-computed functions.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Placeholder syntax recognition, scanning and substitution, all four
      variable namespaces and their resolvable fields, escape sequences, and
      the collection of unresolved placeholder names.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Caller">
      The caller supplies text and, optionally, agent context and configuration.
      What the caller does with the processed output — including assembling a
      system prompt from multiple documents — is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Environment">
      Environment variable values are read from the process environment at the
      moment of substitution. The environment itself is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Input">
      <field name="text" type="text" note="the source document to process; may contain any UTF-8 content" />
      <field name="agent context" type="object" required="false" nullable="true" note="provides agent.* namespace values; if null, all agent.* variables are unresolvable" />
      <field name="configuration" type="object" required="false" nullable="true" note="provides config.* namespace values; if null, all config.* variables are unresolvable" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Output">
      <field name="processed text" type="text" note="the input text with all resolved placeholders replaced and $$ sequences converted to literal $" />
      <field name="unresolved variables" type="list of text" note="deduplicated list of placeholder expressions that could not be resolved, in first-occurrence order" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <scanning order="1">
      The input text is scanned left to right, one character at a time. The
      output is built incrementally by appending characters or resolved values
      as each position is processed.

      <escape-sequence order="1">
        When two consecutive dollar signs (`$$`) are encountered, exactly one
        dollar sign is appended to the output and the scanner advances past
        both characters. The character following the second `$` is processed
        normally on the next step.

        <notable reason="escape prevents interpolation">
          The sequence `$${agent.uuid}` produces the literal text
          `${agent.uuid}` in the output — the double dollar escapes the
          opening of what would otherwise be a placeholder.
        </notable>
      </escape-sequence>

      <placeholder-recognition order="2">
        When a dollar sign followed by an opening brace (`${`) is encountered,
        the scanner searches forward for the next closing brace (`}`). If a
        closing brace is found, the text between `${` and `}` is the variable
        name and is passed to variable resolution. If no closing brace is found,
        the dollar sign is appended to the output as a literal character and
        the scanner advances past it only, leaving `{` and subsequent text to
        be processed normally.
      </placeholder-recognition>

      <other-characters order="3">
        Any character that is not part of a `$$` sequence or a `${...}` opener
        is appended to the output verbatim, including lone dollar signs not
        followed by `{`.
      </other-characters>
    </scanning>

    <variable-resolution order="2">
      A variable name is a dot-separated pair: a namespace and a field. The
      namespace determines which resolution source is consulted. If resolution
      produces a value, that value is appended to the output in place of the
      `${...}` placeholder. If resolution produces no value, the original
      placeholder text (including `${` and `}`) is appended to the output
      unchanged, and the placeholder is recorded in the unresolved list.

      <agent-namespace order="1">
        Variables in the `agent` namespace resolve against the provided agent
        context. If no agent context is provided, all agent-namespace variables
        are unresolvable.

        The following fields are recognized:

        `uuid` — the agent's unique identifier, as text. If null, unresolvable.

        `name` — the agent's display name. If null, unresolvable.

        `parent_uuid` — the unique identifier of the parent agent. If null,
        unresolvable.

        `provider` — the name of the LLM provider in use (e.g., `anthropic`,
        `openai`, `google`). If null, unresolvable.

        `model` — the model identifier in use. If null, unresolvable.

        `created_at` — the agent's creation timestamp as a decimal integer
        string. Always resolvable when an agent context is provided.

        Any other field name in the `agent` namespace is unresolvable.
      </agent-namespace>

      <config-namespace order="2">
        Variables in the `config` namespace resolve against the provided
        configuration. If no configuration is provided, all config-namespace
        variables are unresolvable.

        The following fields are recognized:

        Text fields (unresolvable when null): `openai_model`, `db_host`,
        `db_name`, `db_user`, `default_provider`, `listen_address`,
        `openai_system_message`.

        Integer fields (always resolvable when configuration is provided,
        formatted as decimal strings): `db_port`, `max_tool_turns`,
        `max_output_size`, `history_size`, `listen_port`.

        Floating-point fields (always resolvable when configuration is
        provided, formatted to two decimal places): `openai_temperature`.

        Integer field (always resolvable when configuration is provided,
        formatted as decimal string): `openai_max_completion_tokens`.

        Any other field name in the `config` namespace is unresolvable.
      </config-namespace>

      <env-namespace order="3">
        Variables in the `env` namespace resolve by looking up the field name
        as an environment variable in the process environment at the moment of
        substitution. If the variable is set, its value is used. If the
        variable is not set, the placeholder is unresolvable.
      </env-namespace>

      <func-namespace order="4">
        Variables in the `func` namespace produce computed values regardless
        of agent context or configuration.

        `func.now` — the current UTC time formatted as an ISO 8601 timestamp
        (e.g., `2024-01-01T00:00:00Z`). If the system clock cannot be read,
        unresolvable.

        `func.cwd` — the current working directory of the process as an
        absolute path. If the directory cannot be obtained, unresolvable.

        `func.hostname` — the system hostname. If the hostname cannot be
        obtained, unresolvable.

        `func.random` — a freshly generated version-4 UUID in lowercase
        hyphenated form (e.g., `550e8400-e29b-41d4-a716-446655440000`).

        Any other field name in the `func` namespace is unresolvable.
      </func-namespace>

      <unknown-namespace order="5">
        A variable whose namespace is not `agent`, `config`, `env`, or `func`
        is unresolvable. The placeholder is appended to the output verbatim
        and recorded in the unresolved list.
      </unknown-namespace>
    </variable-resolution>

    <unresolved-tracking order="3">
      Each placeholder that cannot be resolved is recorded in the unresolved
      list. Before recording, the list is checked for an existing entry with
      the same placeholder text. If an identical placeholder has already been
      recorded, it is not added again. The unresolved list contains each
      distinct unresolved placeholder exactly once, in the order of its first
      appearance in the input text.
    </unresolved-tracking>

    <always-succeeds order="4">
      The template processor does not return an error. For any valid input, it
      produces processed text and an unresolved list. Placeholders that cannot
      be resolved are passed through to the output verbatim rather than
      causing failure. The only condition that terminates the process is a
      memory allocation failure, which aborts the process.
    </always-succeeds>

  </behavior>

</specification>
