<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Terminal Layers">

  <topic-statement>
    The terminal UI is composed of seven named layers that render specific
    content to distinct regions of the terminal screen, stacking from top to
    bottom to form the complete interactive display.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The identity, content, visibility rules, and height of each of the seven
      layers, and their spatial relationship to each other.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer rendering">
      How layers are composited, clipped to the viewport, and written to the
      terminal in a single atomic pass is covered by the layer rendering
      specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Scrollback buffer">
      How the text lines stored in the scrollback buffer are structured and
      how physical row counts are computed is covered by the scrollback buffer
      specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <stack-order order="1">
      The seven layers occupy the terminal from top to bottom in the following
      fixed order:

      1. Banner
      2. Scrollback
      3. Separator
      4. Input
      5. Spinner
      6. Status
      7. Completion

      The scrollback region dominates the middle of the terminal and expands
      or contracts to fill whatever vertical space is not consumed by the other
      layers.
    </stack-order>

    <banner-layer order="2">
      The banner is an optional decorative header occupying exactly 6 rows. It
      displays a stylized ASCII art face with the application name and version.
      The visual elements use 256-color styling: cyan eyes with gold pupils,
      a coral smile, dim gray border lines, soft blue version text, and a
      light-gray tagline. The top and bottom of the banner are framed by
      double horizontal lines.

      The banner contains no dynamic content — it does not reflect agent state
      or user input. It is purely decorative.

      When hidden, the 6 rows it would occupy become available to the scrollback
      layer.
    </banner-layer>

    <scrollback-layer order="3">
      The scrollback layer is always visible and occupies all vertical space
      not claimed by other layers. It renders the agent's conversation history:
      user messages, LLM responses, tool calls and results, command output, and
      system events, in chronological order.

      The layer maintains a layout cache mapping logical scrollback lines to
      physical screen rows, accounting for text wrapping at the terminal width.
      It renders only the subset of rows that fall within the viewport (as
      determined by the current scroll offset). Newlines embedded within a
      scrollback line are rendered with ANSI clear-to-end-of-line sequences to
      ensure correct display across wrapped lines.

      When the terminal is resized, the layout cache is recomputed using the
      pre-calculated per-segment widths stored with each line, without rescanning
      the text.
    </scrollback-layer>

    <separator-layer order="4">
      The separator is an optional 1-row horizontal divider composed of light
      box-drawing characters that marks the boundary between the scrollback and
      the input area.

      The separator can optionally embed two kinds of overlay information:

      1. **Navigation context**: abbreviated UUIDs of the current agent's
         parent, previous sibling, next sibling, and most recent child, shown
         with directional arrow characters. If a direction has no agent (for
         example, the root agent has no parent), a dim dash is shown instead.
      2. **Debug statistics**: scroll offset, viewport position, viewport
         height, document height, computed scrollback row count, and last render
         time in milliseconds or microseconds.

      Both overlays are conditional on external configuration; neither appears
      in normal production use.
    </separator-layer>

    <input-layer order="5">
      The input layer displays the text currently being typed or edited by the
      user. Its height is dynamic: it occupies the minimum number of rows
      required to display the full input text at the current terminal width,
      with a minimum of 1 row (to provide a cursor position even when the
      buffer is empty).

      Newlines in the input text are converted to ANSI clear-to-end-of-line
      sequences before rendering, matching the behavior used in the scrollback
      layer.

      The cursor position within the input layer is the cursor byte offset
      translated to a terminal row and column using the rendering context's
      cursor position calculation.
    </input-layer>

    <spinner-layer order="6">
      The spinner is a 1-row indicator that appears while the agent is waiting
      for an LLM response. It cycles through ten Braille dot-pattern frames
      to produce a subtle animation indicating ongoing activity. The animation
      advances every 120 milliseconds. A fixed label follows the animation
      frame.

      The spinner is hidden when the agent is idle (not awaiting a response).
    </spinner-layer>

    <status-layer order="7">
      The status layer is a fixed 2-row footer. The first row is a light
      horizontal line separator. The second row displays the current agent's
      configured model name and thinking level, separated by a forward slash.
      If no model is configured, a placeholder is shown in soft blue.

      The status layer always occupies its 2 rows; it is never hidden.
    </status-layer>

    <completion-layer order="8">
      The completion layer is an optional dropdown that appears at the bottom
      of the screen when a tab-completion session is active. It renders one
      row per candidate. Each row shows the command name followed by its
      description. The currently highlighted candidate is rendered with reverse
      video and bold styling to distinguish it from the others. Each row is
      padded to the terminal width to clear any previously rendered content.

      The layer is hidden when no completion session is active. When visible,
      its height equals the number of available candidates.
    </completion-layer>

  </behavior>

</specification>
