<specification topic="Terminal Setup">

  <topic-statement>
    The terminal setup component initializes a TTY file descriptor into raw mode with
    an alternate screen buffer, probes for enhanced keyboard protocol support, and
    restores the terminal to its original state on cleanup.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Headless terminal creation, terminal initialization from a TTY file descriptor,
      CSI u protocol probing and activation, terminal size querying, and terminal
      cleanup and state restoration.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="TTY Device">
      Normal (non-headless) initialization opens /dev/tty directly. The test-facing
      variant accepts a pre-opened file descriptor. All terminal I/O — escape
      sequences, attribute changes, size queries — goes through this descriptor.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Logger">
      CSI u enable and unexpected-response events are written to the logger when one
      is provided. Logging is optional; no logger produces no log output.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Terminal Context">
      <field name="tty_fd" type="integer" note="file descriptor; -1 in headless mode" />
      <field name="screen_rows" type="integer" note="terminal height in rows; 50 in headless mode" />
      <field name="screen_cols" type="integer" note="terminal width in columns; 100 in headless mode" />
      <field name="csi_u_supported" type="boolean" note="whether enhanced keyboard protocol was activated; false in headless mode" />
      <field name="orig_termios" type="terminal attributes" note="saved original terminal settings for restoration on cleanup" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <headless-initialization order="1">
      When headless initialization is requested, a terminal context is returned with
      a file descriptor of -1, 50 rows, 100 columns, and CSI u marked as not
      supported. No TTY is opened and no I/O is performed.
    </headless-initialization>

    <normal-initialization order="2">
      Terminal initialization takes a TTY file descriptor and proceeds through the
      following steps in order. If any step fails, preceding state changes are rolled
      back before the error is returned.

      <save-original-attributes order="1">
        The current terminal attributes are saved. Failure to retrieve them closes
        the file descriptor and returns an I/O error.
      </save-original-attributes>

      <raw-mode-activation order="2">
        Terminal attributes are modified from the saved copy:
        - Input flags cleared: BRKINT, ICRNL, INPCK, ISTRIP, IXON
        - Output flags cleared: OPOST
        - Control flags set: CS8
        - Local flags cleared: ECHO, ICANON, IEXTEN, ISIG
        - Minimum read size set to 1; read timeout set to 0

        The modified attributes are applied immediately (no drain). Failure
        closes the file descriptor and returns an I/O error.
      </raw-mode-activation>

      <input-flush order="3">
        Any bytes already queued in the input buffer from before raw mode was active
        are discarded. Failure restores the original terminal attributes, closes the
        file descriptor, and returns an I/O error.
      </input-flush>

      <alternate-screen-entry order="4">
        The escape sequence to enter the alternate screen buffer (ESC[?1049h, 8 bytes)
        is written to the TTY. Failure restores original attributes, closes the file
        descriptor, and returns an I/O error.
      </alternate-screen-entry>

      <screen-clear order="5">
        The escape sequence to clear the entire screen and move the cursor to the
        home position (ESC[2J ESC[H, 6 bytes) is written to the TTY. Failure restores
        original attributes, closes the file descriptor, and returns an I/O error.

        <notable reason="no alternate-screen exit on clear failure">
          On screen-clear failure, the code restores terminal attributes and closes
          the file descriptor but does not send the alternate-screen exit sequence.
          The terminal is left in the alternate screen buffer.
        </notable>
      </screen-clear>

      <csi-u-probe order="6">
        The enhanced keyboard protocol (CSI u) is probed by sending the query sequence
        (ESC[?u, 4 bytes) and waiting up to 100 milliseconds for a response. If a
        response of at least 4 bytes arrives and begins with ESC [ ?, and a 'u'
        character appears anywhere after the third byte, the protocol is considered
        supported. Any other outcome — timeout, read error, response shorter than 4
        bytes, missing ESC[? prefix, or no 'u' terminator — means the protocol is
        not supported.

        <notable reason="no rollback if CSI u fails">
          CSI u support failure is non-fatal. Initialization continues regardless
          of probe outcome.
        </notable>
      </csi-u-probe>

      <csi-u-enable order="7">
        If CSI u support was detected, the enable sequence (ESC[>9u, 5 bytes, flag
        value 9 which requests key disambiguation and all-key reporting) is sent.
        The system waits up to 100 milliseconds for a response.

        If no response arrives within the timeout, the protocol is assumed to have
        been successfully enabled and the terminal context records it as active.

        If a response arrives and begins with ESC [ ?, and a 'u' character appears
        after the third byte, the decimal digits preceding 'u' are parsed as the
        enabled flags value. A log event named "csi_u_enabled" carrying the flags
        value is written to the logger. The protocol is recorded as active.

        If a response arrives but does not match the expected ESC[?…u format, a log
        event named "csi_u_unexpected_response" is written, carrying the response
        length in bytes and a space-separated lowercase hexadecimal dump of up to
        the first 32 bytes of the response. Despite the unexpected format, the
        protocol is still recorded as active.

        If the read call returns zero or a negative value, the enable attempt fails
        and CSI u is recorded as inactive.

        <notable reason="unexpected response still treated as success">
          Any response that does not match the expected format still causes CSI u
          to be recorded as active. Only a zero or error return from the read
          actually disables it.
        </notable>
      </csi-u-enable>

      <terminal-size-query order="8">
        The terminal size is queried from the system. Failure exits the alternate
        screen buffer (ESC[?1049l), restores original attributes, closes the file
        descriptor, and returns an I/O error. On success, the row and column counts
        are stored in the terminal context.
      </terminal-size-query>

    </normal-initialization>

    <size-query order="3">
      When the terminal size is queried after initialization, if the file descriptor
      is valid, the size is re-read from the system and the stored values are updated.
      If the file descriptor is -1 (headless), the stored values are returned without
      any system call. Failure to query a live terminal size returns an I/O error.
    </size-query>

    <cleanup order="4">
      Terminal cleanup is a no-op if the context is absent or the file descriptor is
      -1. Otherwise, the following steps are performed in order:

      1. If CSI u was active, the disable sequence (ESC[&lt;u, 4 bytes) is written.
      2. The alternate screen exit sequence (ESC[?1049l, 8 bytes) is written.
      3. The original terminal attributes are restored immediately (no drain).
      4. Any remaining queued input is discarded.
      5. The file descriptor is closed.

      All write and flush failures are silently ignored during cleanup. Freeing the
      terminal context is the caller's responsibility.
    </cleanup>

  </behavior>

</specification>
