<specification topic="Token Count Cache">

  <topic-statement>
    The token count cache tracks per-component token costs for an agent's sliding context window.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Cache lifecycle (creation, cloning), per-component cost retrieval (system prompt, tool
      definitions, per-turn, total), known-cost recording, cache invalidation, structural
      operations (adding turns, pruning oldest turn, removing turns from a given index), budget
      configuration, and non-computing introspection.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Provider Token Counting">
      This topic submits a constructed request to the provider and receives either a token count
      integer or a failure indication. Requests are constructed from agent messages, model name,
      and system prompt text as part of this topic's computation; the counting itself is across
      this boundary.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent Context">
      This topic reads the agent's message list (role and content per message), current message
      count, model name, and effective system prompt. It does not modify the agent.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Cache State">
      <field name="system prompt token cost" type="int32" note="uncached sentinel when not yet known" />
      <field name="tool definitions token cost" type="int32" note="uncached sentinel when not yet known" />
      <field name="per-turn token costs" type="int32 array" note="each entry independently uncached or known; array grows dynamically" />
      <field name="active turn count" type="unsigned integer" />
      <field name="turn array capacity" type="unsigned integer" note="initial 8; doubles on overflow" />
      <field name="total token cost" type="int32" note="uncached sentinel when not yet known" />
      <field name="token budget" type="int32" note="default 100000" />
      <field name="context start message index" type="unsigned integer" note="index into agent message list of oldest active message" />
      <field name="pruned turn count" type="unsigned integer" note="cumulative count of turns removed from the front" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Message Content Block">
      <field name="type" type="enumerated" note="text, tool call, tool result, thinking, or other" />
      <field name="text content" type="string" required="false" nullable="true" note="present when type is text or thinking" />
      <field name="tool call arguments" type="string" required="false" nullable="true" note="present when type is tool call" />
      <field name="tool result content" type="string" required="false" nullable="true" note="present when type is tool result" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      A new cache is created associated with a specific agent. All component costs — system
      prompt, tool definitions, and total — are initialized to uncached. The per-turn array is
      allocated with an initial capacity of 8 entries and a turn count of 0. The token budget
      defaults to 100,000. The context start message index is 0. The pruned turn count is 0.
    </creation>

    <cloning order="2">
      A cache is cloned for a different agent (used when an agent is forked). The clone receives
      copies of all cached values from the source: system cost, tool cost, total cost, all per-turn
      costs, context start message index, pruned turn count, and token budget. If the source's
      turn array capacity is 0, the clone uses a capacity of 8; otherwise the source's capacity
      is used. The clone is associated with the new agent, not the source agent.
    </cloning>

    <retrieving-system-tokens order="3">
      When the system token cost is requested:

      <cached-hit order="1">
        If the system token cost is already known, it is returned immediately.
      </cached-hit>

      <provider-computation order="2">
        If uncached, the agent's effective system prompt text is retrieved. A request is
        constructed using the agent's model name and the system prompt. The request is submitted
        to the provider for token counting.

        <notable reason="null model name fallback">
          If the agent has no model name set, the string "default" is used.
        </notable>

        If the provider returns a count, that count is stored as the system token cost, the total
        token cost is reset to uncached, and the count is returned.
      </provider-computation>

      <bytes-fallback order="3">
        If any step in provider computation fails — prompt retrieval fails, request construction
        fails, or the provider call fails — the system prompt's byte length is divided by 4
        (integer division, truncating toward zero) and that value is returned.

        <notable reason="fallback not stored">
          The bytes-based estimate is not stored. The system token cost remains uncached, and
          the total token cost is not reset. On the next request for the system cost, the provider
          will be contacted again.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="null prompt treated as zero bytes">
          If the system prompt is null, the byte length is treated as 0 and 0 is returned.
        </notable>
      </bytes-fallback>
    </retrieving-system-tokens>

    <retrieving-tool-tokens order="4">
      When the tool definitions token cost is requested:

      <cached-hit order="1">
        If the tool token cost is already known, it is returned immediately.
      </cached-hit>

      <provider-computation order="2">
        If uncached, a request is constructed using only the agent's model name — no system
        prompt and no messages. The request is submitted to the provider for token counting.

        <notable reason="null model name fallback">
          If the agent has no model name set, the string "default" is used.
        </notable>

        If the provider returns a count, that count is stored as the tool token cost, the total
        token cost is reset to uncached, and the count is returned.
      </provider-computation>

      <failure-fallback order="3">
        If request construction or the provider call fails, 0 is returned.

        <notable reason="fallback not stored">
          The value 0 is not stored. The tool token cost remains uncached.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="fallback is zero not a bytes estimate">
          Unlike system and per-turn costs, the tool definitions fallback on failure is 0,
          not a bytes-based estimate.
        </notable>
      </failure-fallback>
    </retrieving-tool-tokens>

    <retrieving-turn-tokens order="5">
      When the token cost of a specific turn is requested by its zero-based index:

      <out-of-bounds-check order="1">
        If the requested index is greater than or equal to the active turn count, the process
        terminates abnormally.
      </out-of-bounds-check>

      <cached-hit order="2">
        If that turn's token cost is already known, it is returned immediately.
      </cached-hit>

      <turn-bounds-resolution order="3">
        The boundaries of the turn within the agent's message list are found by iterating forward
        from the context start message index, counting user-role messages. Turn index N begins at
        the (N+1)th user-role message encountered and ends at the message immediately before the
        (N+2)th user-role message. The last active turn (with no subsequent user-role message)
        extends through the final message in the agent's list.
      </turn-bounds-resolution>

      <provider-computation order="4">
        A request is constructed from the turn's messages using the agent's model name. The
        request is submitted to the provider for token counting.

        If the provider returns a count, that count is stored as the turn's token cost, the
        total token cost is reset to uncached, and the count is returned.
      </provider-computation>

      <bytes-fallback order="5">
        If the provider call fails, the byte lengths of qualifying content across all messages
        in the turn are summed. The sum is divided by 4 (integer division, truncating toward
        zero) and returned. This value is not stored; the turn's cost remains uncached.

        Qualifying content types and their contributing fields:
        - Text blocks: the text field, if not null
        - Tool call blocks: the arguments field, if not null
        - Tool result blocks: the content field, if not null
        - Thinking blocks: the text field, if not null

        Content blocks of all other types contribute 0 bytes. Null fields contribute 0 bytes.
      </bytes-fallback>

      <no-messages-fallback order="6">
        If no messages are found for the turn (turn bounds resolution yields nothing), 0 is
        returned.
      </no-messages-fallback>
    </retrieving-turn-tokens>

    <retrieving-total-tokens order="6">
      When the total token cost is requested:

      <cached-hit order="1">
        If the total token cost is already known, it is returned immediately.
      </cached-hit>

      <summing order="2">
        If uncached, the system token cost, tool token cost, and each per-turn token cost are
        retrieved in sequence (each triggering its own computation logic if uncached). The sum
        of all retrieved values is stored as the total token cost and returned.

        <notable reason="total always stored even with estimates">
          The total is stored regardless of whether any component costs used bytes-based
          estimates rather than provider counts. On the next request for the total, the stored
          value is returned without recomputing any component — even if those components are
          still individually marked uncached and would produce a different result if re-queried.
        </notable>
      </summing>
    </retrieving-total-tokens>

    <recording-known-turn-cost order="7">
      A confirmed token count for a specific turn can be stored directly (used after turn
      completion when the response carries an authoritative token delta). If the turn index is
      greater than or equal to the active turn count, the process terminates abnormally. The
      stored value replaces any previously cached value for that turn, and the total token cost
      is reset to uncached.
    </recording-known-turn-cost>

    <invalidation order="8">
      Four operations reset cached values to uncached:

      <invalidate-all order="1">
        All component costs — system, tools, every per-turn entry, and total — are reset to
        uncached. The turn count, context start index, and pruned turn count are not changed.
      </invalidate-all>

      <reset order="2">
        All component costs are reset to uncached. Additionally, the active turn count is set to
        0, the context start message index is set to 0, and the pruned turn count is set to 0.
        Per-turn array capacity is not changed.
      </reset>

      <invalidate-system order="3">
        The system token cost and the total token cost are reset to uncached.
      </invalidate-system>

      <invalidate-tools order="4">
        The tool token cost and the total token cost are reset to uncached.
      </invalidate-tools>
    </invalidation>

    <adding-a-turn order="9">
      When a new turn slot is appended, a new uncached entry is added to the per-turn array.
      If the array is already at capacity, its capacity is doubled before adding the entry.

      <notable reason="zero-capacity edge case">
        If the current capacity is 0 at the time of growth, the new capacity is set to 8.
      </notable>

      The active turn count is incremented by 1. The total token cost is reset to uncached.
    </adding-a-turn>

    <pruning-oldest-turn order="10">
      When the oldest active turn is removed from context:

      <no-op-case order="1">
        If the active turn count is 0, nothing happens.
      </no-op-case>

      <total-adjustment order="2">
        If both the total token cost and the oldest turn's token cost are known, the oldest
        turn's cost is subtracted from the total. If the result is negative, the total is reset
        to uncached.

        If either value is uncached, the total is reset to uncached.
      </total-adjustment>

      <context-start-advancement order="3">
        The context start message index advances to the index of the second user-role message
        encountered starting from the current context start index. If no second user-role message
        exists in the agent's message list from that point forward, the context start index is
        set to the agent's total message count (one past the last message).
      </context-start-advancement>

      <accounting order="4">
        The pruned turn count is incremented by 1.
      </accounting>

      <array-shift order="5">
        All per-turn cost entries are shifted one position toward index 0, removing the entry
        that was at index 0. The active turn count is decremented by 1.
      </array-shift>
    </pruning-oldest-turn>

    <removing-turns-from-index order="11">
      When turns from a given index onward (inclusive) are removed:

      <out-of-bounds-check order="1">
        If the turn index is strictly greater than the active turn count, the process terminates
        abnormally.
      </out-of-bounds-check>

      <no-op-case order="2">
        If the turn index equals the active turn count, nothing happens.
      </no-op-case>

      <total-adjustment order="3">
        For each turn being removed — from the given index to the last active turn — if that
        turn's cost is uncached, the total is reset to uncached and iteration stops. If the
        turn's cost is known and the total is currently known, that cost is subtracted from the
        total; if the result is negative, the total is reset to uncached.
      </total-adjustment>

      <truncation order="4">
        The active turn count is set to the given index.
      </truncation>

      <conditional-context-reset order="5">
        If the active turn count is now 0 and the context start message index is greater than 0,
        the context start message index is reset to 0 and the pruned turn count is reset to 0.

        <notable reason="reset only when context was advanced">
          If the active turn count reaches 0 but the context start message index is already 0
          (no pruning had ever occurred), the pruned turn count is not touched and remains at
          whatever value it held — though this value is also 0 in normal operation.
        </notable>
      </conditional-context-reset>
    </removing-turns-from-index>

    <budget-operations order="12">
      A token budget value can be read or set at any time. Reading returns the current budget
      without any side effects. Setting stores the new value immediately. No validation is
      performed on the supplied budget value.
    </budget-operations>

    <non-computing-introspection order="13">
      Several read operations return state without triggering any computation:

      <turn-count order="1">
        Returns the active turn count.
      </turn-count>

      <context-start-turn order="2">
        Returns the pruned turn count, which is the absolute index of the oldest active turn
        relative to the full history.
      </context-start-turn>

      <context-start-index order="3">
        Returns the context start message index: the position in the agent's message list of the
        oldest message currently included in active context.
      </context-start-index>

      <peek-total order="4">
        Returns the cached total if known, or 0 if uncached. Does not compute.
      </peek-total>

      <peek-turn-tokens order="5">
        Returns the cached cost for a specific turn index if known, or 0 if uncached. If the
        turn index is greater than or equal to the active turn count, the process terminates
        abnormally. Does not compute.
      </peek-turn-tokens>
    </non-computing-introspection>

  </behavior>

  <state-transitions>
    <transition trigger="system cost retrieved via provider">
      System token cost changes from uncached to the provider count; total resets to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="system cost retrieved via bytes fallback">
      System token cost remains uncached; total is unchanged.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="tool cost retrieved via provider">
      Tool token cost changes from uncached to the provider count; total resets to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="tool cost retrieval fails">
      Tool token cost remains uncached; total is unchanged.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="turn cost retrieved via provider">
      That turn's cost changes from uncached to the provider count; total resets to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="turn cost retrieved via bytes fallback">
      That turn's cost remains uncached; total is unchanged.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="total retrieved while uncached">
      Total token cost changes from uncached to the sum of all current component costs.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="known turn cost recorded">
      That turn's cost updated to the given value; total resets to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="turn added">
      Active turn count increases by 1; new turn entry is uncached; total resets to uncached.
      Array capacity may double.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="oldest turn pruned">
      Active turn count decreases by 1; per-turn array shifts left; context start index
      advances to next user-role message; pruned turn count increases by 1; total is adjusted
      or reset to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="turns removed from index">
      Active turn count truncated to the given index; total adjusted or reset to uncached;
      context start index and pruned turn count may reset to 0 if all turns removed and context
      had been advanced.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="invalidate-all">
      All component costs and total reset to uncached.
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="reset">
      All costs reset to uncached; turn count, context start index, and pruned turn count all
      set to 0.
    </transition>
  </state-transitions>

</specification>
