<specification topic="Tool Call Formatting">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool call formatting system renders tool invocations and their results into
    human-readable terminal text with structured argument display and content truncation.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Formatting tool call arguments from JSON into a key=value display, formatting
      tool results with type-sensitive extraction, content truncation, and the buffer
      management that supports incremental construction of formatted strings.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Terminal Display">
      This topic produces formatted strings. Rendering those strings to the terminal
      is outside this topic's scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool Execution">
      This topic receives tool names, argument JSON strings, and result JSON strings.
      Executing tools or producing those values is outside this topic's scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Tool Call Input">
      <field name="tool name" type="string" />
      <field name="arguments JSON" type="string" nullable="true" note="JSON object string; may be null or empty" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool Result Input">
      <field name="tool name" type="string" />
      <field name="result JSON" type="string" nullable="true" note="any JSON value; may be null" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Formatted Output">
      <field name="text" type="string" note="null-terminated string allocated under the caller-provided context" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <buffer-management order="1">
      Formatted output is built incrementally using an internal byte-array buffer.
      The buffer supports printf-style formatted appends, raw string appends, and
      indentation appends (repeated space characters). The final string is extracted
      from the buffer as a null-terminated string; if the last byte already is a null
      terminator it is reused rather than appended again. The buffer length excludes
      any trailing null terminator.
    </buffer-management>

    <formatting-a-tool-call order="2">
      A tool call is formatted as a single line of the form:

        → tool_name: arg1="value1", arg2=42, arg3=true

      <prefix-and-name order="1">
        The line begins with the arrow prefix "→ " followed by the tool name and a
        colon and space.
      </prefix-and-name>

      <no-arguments order="2">
        If the arguments string is null or empty, only the prefix and tool name are
        produced. No colon, space, or argument list is appended.
      </no-arguments>

      <invalid-json-arguments order="3">
        If the arguments string is non-empty but cannot be parsed as JSON, the raw
        argument string is appended directly after a ": " separator, subject to the
        standard content truncation rules (three lines or 400 characters). No
        key=value formatting is applied.
      </invalid-json-arguments>

      <non-object-arguments order="4">
        If the arguments parse successfully as JSON but the root value is not a JSON
        object, the serialized JSON is appended after a ": " separator, subject to
        truncation. No key=value formatting is applied.
      </non-object-arguments>

      <empty-object-arguments order="5">
        If the arguments are a valid JSON object with no fields, only the prefix and
        tool name are produced.
      </empty-object-arguments>

      <key-value-arguments order="6">
        For a valid non-empty JSON object, each field is formatted as key=value and
        the fields are separated by ", ". The formatting of each value depends on its
        JSON type:
        - String values are surrounded by double quotes.
        - Number, boolean, and null values are rendered without quotes.
        - Array and object values are serialized back to compact JSON without quotes.

        The complete argument list is produced without truncation.
      </key-value-arguments>
    </formatting-a-tool-call>

    <formatting-a-tool-result order="3">
      A tool result is formatted as a single line of the form:

        ← tool_name: content

      <prefix-and-name order="1">
        The line begins with the left-arrow prefix "← " followed by the tool name.
      </prefix-and-name>

      <null-result order="2">
        If the result string is null, the prefix and tool name are produced with no
        additional content.
      </null-result>

      <invalid-json-result order="3">
        If the result string is non-null but cannot be parsed as JSON, the raw result
        string is appended after a ": " separator, subject to truncation.
      </invalid-json-result>

      <string-result order="4">
        If the result parses as a JSON string, the string value (without JSON quotes)
        is extracted and appended after ": ", subject to truncation. If the extracted
        string is empty, the text "(no output)" is appended instead.
      </string-result>

      <array-result order="5">
        If the result parses as a JSON array, the array elements are joined with ", "
        and appended after ": ", subject to truncation. String elements in the array
        are appended directly (without JSON quotes); all other element types are
        serialized to compact JSON.
      </array-result>

      <object-or-other-result order="6">
        If the result parses as any other JSON type (object, number, boolean, null),
        the entire value is serialized to compact JSON and appended after ": ", subject
        to truncation.
      </object-or-other-result>

      <no-extractable-content order="7">
        If, after type dispatch, no content string was produced, the text "(no output)"
        is appended after ": ".
      </no-extractable-content>
    </formatting-a-tool-result>

    <content-truncation order="4">
      Content is truncated before being appended if it exceeds either of two limits:
      more than three lines, or more than 400 characters (whichever limit is reached
      first). Scanning stops at the first byte that would violate either limit.

      If the content is empty, the text "(no output)" is appended.

      If truncation occurs, "..." is appended after the truncated content.

      If truncation does not occur, the full content is appended as-is.
    </content-truncation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
