<specification topic="Tool Management Commands">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool management commands allow the user to inspect the active tool
    registry and reload it from disk, updating the set of tools available to
    the LLM.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The inspect command (listing all tools or showing a single tool's
      schema) and the refresh command (clearing and rebuilding the registry
      from tool discovery and internal tool registration).
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Discovery">
      How external tool executables are located in the file system and how
      their schemas are obtained by invoking them is handled by the tool
      discovery subsystem.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool Registry">
      How the registry is structured, how entries are stored and sorted, and
      how lookups are performed is handled by the tool registry subsystem.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Document Cache">
      How the per-agent document cache stores and retrieves previously fetched
      documents is out of scope. The refresh command clears the cache but does
      not implement it.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <inspect-command order="1">
      The inspect command displays information about the tool registry.

      <list-mode order="1">
        When invoked with no argument, all registered tools are listed. For
        each tool, the name and path are shown. Internal tools show a fixed
        "(internal)" placeholder in place of a filesystem path. If the
        registry contains no tools, a message indicating no tools are
        available is displayed instead of a list.
      </list-mode>

      <detail-mode order="2">
        When invoked with a tool name as its argument, the schema of the named
        tool is displayed in pretty-printed JSON format, preceded by the tool's
        name and path. If the named tool is not found in the registry, a
        message indicating the tool was not found is displayed. A tool not
        found condition is not treated as an error; the command returns
        successfully.
      </detail-mode>

      All output is appended to the current agent's scrollback.
    </inspect-command>

    <refresh-command order="2">
      The refresh command rebuilds the tool registry and clears the document
      cache.

      <registry-reset order="1">
        All entries are removed from the tool registry, leaving it empty.
      </registry-reset>

      <cache-reset order="2">
        The current agent's document cache is cleared. This ensures that any
        cached tool schemas are evicted and will be re-fetched on the next
        access.
      </cache-reset>

      <rediscovery order="3">
        Tool discovery is run across the three tool directories (system, user,
        and project). Each qualifying tool executable is invoked to obtain its
        schema and is added to the registry.
      </rediscovery>

      <internal-tool-registration order="4">
        The built-in internal tools are registered after external discovery
        completes. An internal tool with the same name as a discovered external
        tool replaces it.
      </internal-tool-registration>

      <sort order="5">
        The registry is sorted alphabetically by tool name after all tools are
        registered.
      </sort>

      <reporting order="6">
        A message reporting the total number of tools now in the registry is
        appended to the current agent's scrollback.
      </reporting>

      <notable reason="refresh rebuilds from the filesystem">
        The refresh command reflects changes to tool executables on disk
        since the last initialization or refresh. New tools become visible,
        removed tools disappear, and updated schemas take effect.
      </notable>
    </refresh-command>

  </behavior>

</specification>
