<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Toolset Filter">

  <topic-statement>
    The toolset filter restricts which tools from the tool registry are offered
    to the LLM on each request, allowing an agent to work with a named subset
    of available tools.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The whitelist data structure on the agent, the /toolset command (setting,
      listing, and clearing the filter), delimiter parsing, and database
      persistence. Toolset inheritance during agent forking is covered in the
      agent fork specification.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool request assembly">
      How the whitelist is applied when building the tools array for an LLM
      request (filtering the tool registry) is covered by the LLM request
      specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool registry">
      How tools are discovered and registered is covered by the tool execution
      specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <behavior>

    <whitelist-storage order="1">
      The toolset filter is stored on the agent as a dynamically sized array
      of tool name strings, alongside a count of entries. An empty array (count
      of zero) means no filter is active and all registered tools are offered
      to the LLM. A non-empty array means only tools whose names appear in the
      list are offered.
    </whitelist-storage>

    <toolset-command order="2">
      The `/toolset` command with a tool name list sets the filter, replacing
      any existing filter entirely:

      1. The argument string is tokenized using both spaces and commas as
         delimiters (they may be mixed freely: `"tool1, tool2 tool3"` is valid).
      2. Each token becomes one entry in the new whitelist array.
      3. The existing whitelist is replaced.
      4. A toolset event is persisted to the database with the original argument
         string (not the tokenized form).

      The `/toolset` command with no arguments lists the current whitelist and
      takes no other action.

      <notable reason="both spaces and commas are valid delimiters">
        Users may separate tool names with spaces, commas, or a mix of both.
        The delimiter style is not preserved — on session restoration, the
        original argument string is replayed and re-tokenized.
      </notable>
    </toolset-command>

    <clear-behavior order="3">
      Providing an argument string that contains no non-whitespace tokens (for
      example, an argument containing only spaces or commas) results in a
      zero-count filter, which is equivalent to no filter (all tools visible).
      No explicit "clear" sub-command exists; providing an empty effective
      argument achieves this effect.
    </clear-behavior>

    <persistence order="4">
      Toolset changes are persisted to the database as command events containing
      the original argument string. During session restoration, the most recent
      toolset command in the agent's history is replayed to reconstruct the
      filter. If no toolset command exists in the history but the agent was
      forked, the toolset is inherited from the fork event.
    </persistence>

  </behavior>

</specification>
