<specification topic="Tool Discovery">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool discovery system scans configurable directories for tool executables and
    populates the tool registry with their definitions.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Directory scanning, executable detection, schema extraction via subprocess
      invocation, tool name derivation, and registration with override precedence.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Registry">
      This topic sends tool names, paths, and parsed schema documents to the registry.
      How the registry stores or retrieves entries is outside this topic's scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Schema Content">
      This topic parses the raw JSON schema output from tools but does not validate
      its structure or interpret its contents. The schema is passed opaquely to the
      registry.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="File System">
      This topic reads directory listings and file metadata from the file system.
      Directory creation, modification, and any writes are outside scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Discovery Input">
      <field name="system tools directory" type="path" note="lowest priority" />
      <field name="user tools directory" type="path" note="middle priority" />
      <field name="project tools directory" type="path" note="highest priority" />
      <field name="tool registry" type="registry reference" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Discovered Tool">
      <field name="name" type="string" note="derived from filename by stripping -tool suffix and converting hyphens to underscores" />
      <field name="path" type="string" note="full filesystem path to the executable" />
      <field name="schema" type="parsed JSON document" note="output of running the executable with --schema" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <scan-order-and-override-precedence order="1">
      Discovery scans three directories in a fixed order: system, then user, then
      project. When a tool with the same name appears in more than one directory, the
      later-scanned directory's version replaces the earlier one. Project tools override
      user tools; user tools override system tools.

      If any directory scan returns an error, discovery stops immediately and propagates
      the error without scanning subsequent directories.

      After all three directories have been scanned, the registry is sorted alphabetically
      by tool name.
    </scan-order-and-override-precedence>

    <scanning-a-directory order="2">
      Each directory is opened for reading. If the directory does not exist or cannot
      be opened, it is silently skipped — no error is produced and discovery continues
      with the next directory.

      <notable reason="graceful-skip on missing directory">
        A missing or inaccessible directory is not an error condition. Discovery simply
        moves on. This allows a system with no user-level tools, or no project-level
        tools, to operate normally.
      </notable>

      Every entry in the directory is examined in the order returned by the operating
      system. The entries named "." and ".." are skipped. For each remaining entry, the
      full file path is constructed by joining the directory path and the entry name.

      An entry is eligible for registration only if both conditions are met:
      1. The file has the user-execute permission bit set (determined by inspecting the
         file's metadata; if metadata cannot be read, the file is skipped silently).
      2. The filename ends with the suffix "-tool".

      Files that fail either condition are silently skipped without error.
    </scanning-a-directory>

    <schema-extraction order="3">
      For each eligible file, a child process is spawned to run the tool executable
      with the single argument "--schema". The child process's standard output is
      captured. Standard error is discarded silently.

      The parent waits for the child's output with a one-second timeout enforced via
      a system alarm signal. If the child does not produce output or does not exit
      within one second, the alarm fires.

      The child's output is read into a buffer with a maximum capacity of 8191 bytes
      (plus a null terminator for 8192 bytes total). If the tool produces more output
      than this, the excess is silently truncated.

      After reading completes, the alarm is cancelled, the pipe is closed, and the
      parent waits for the child process to exit.

      A schema extraction is considered successful only if both of these are true:
      - The child process exited normally with exit status zero.
      - At least one byte was read from its output.

      If either condition fails, the tool is silently skipped — no error is produced
      and discovery continues with the next file.

      <notable reason="silent-skip on schema failure">
        A tool that crashes, produces no output, or exits with a non-zero status is
        ignored without any warning or log message. The tool simply does not appear
        in the registry.
      </notable>

      If the output is non-empty and the child exited successfully, the output is
      parsed as JSON. If JSON parsing fails, the tool is silently skipped.
    </schema-extraction>

    <tool-name-derivation order="4">
      A tool's registry name is derived from its filename by two transformations:
      1. The trailing "-tool" suffix is removed.
      2. Every hyphen in the remaining name is replaced with an underscore.

      Examples:
      - "bash-tool" becomes "bash"
      - "file-read-tool" becomes "file_read"
      - "git-commit-tool" becomes "git_commit"

      If the file does not end with "-tool", the behavior is undefined — this case
      is treated as a precondition violation.
    </tool-name-derivation>

    <registration order="5">
      Each successfully extracted tool is added to the registry by name, path, and
      schema. If a tool with the same name already exists in the registry (from an
      earlier directory scan), the existing entry is replaced with the new one.

      If registration fails (due to a registry-internal error), the error is propagated
      immediately and discovery halts.
    </registration>

  </behavior>

</specification>
