<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Tool Execution">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool execution pipeline dispatches an LLM-requested tool call to either an
    in-process handler or an external executable, wraps the result, and appends
    both the call and the result to the conversation before continuing the LLM
    request loop.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Trigger conditions, the two execution paths (internal and external), the worker
      thread lifecycle, completion polling, result wrapping, URI translation,
      database persistence, the tool registry and discovery, and the tool loop
      continuation mechanism.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="LLM request dispatch">
      How the LLM API request is formed and sent, and how the streaming response is
      parsed to detect tool calls, is covered by the provider and SSE parser
      specifications.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent state machine">
      The state transitions between idle, waiting-for-LLM, and executing-tool are
      covered by the agent state machine specification.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Tool registry entry">
      <field name="name" type="text" note="the tool's callable name (e.g., 'bash', 'file_read'); derived from the executable filename by stripping the '-tool' suffix and converting hyphens to underscores" />
      <field name="path" type="text or null" note="absolute filesystem path to the executable; null for internal tools" />
      <field name="schema" type="parsed JSON" note="the tool's JSON schema, obtained by invoking the tool with the '--schema' flag during discovery" />
      <field name="type" type="enumeration" note="one of: external (fork/exec), internal (in-process function)" />
      <field name="handler" type="function reference or null" note="the C function for internal tools; null for external tools" />
      <field name="on-complete hook" type="function reference or null" note="called on the main thread after the tool's worker thread finishes; null if no post-completion work is needed" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool result envelope">
      <field name="tool_success" type="boolean" note="true if the tool executed without error" />
      <field name="result" type="JSON value" note="present when tool_success is true; the tool's output" />
      <field name="error" type="text" note="present when tool_success is false; a human-readable error message" />
      <field name="error_code" type="text" note="present when tool_success is false; a short machine-readable error identifier" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <trigger order="1">
      Tool execution begins when an LLM response is received with a tool call
      content block and a finish reason indicating tool use. The tool call's name,
      identifier, and JSON arguments are extracted from the response and stored as
      the agent's pending tool call.

      Only the first tool call block in a response is executed. Any additional tool
      call blocks in the same response are discarded.
    </trigger>

    <worker-thread order="2">
      Tool execution runs on a dedicated worker thread, not on the main event loop
      thread. The thread is created when execution begins and joined when the main
      loop detects completion.

      While the thread is running, the agent is in the executing-tool state. The
      main loop polls for completion every 50 milliseconds by checking an atomic
      completion flag.

      When the flag is set, the main loop joins the thread, harvests the result
      from a shared field, and proceeds with result processing.

      <notable reason="thread is joined from the main loop, not from a callback">
        There is no asynchronous notification. The main loop polls the completion
        flag on every iteration when any agent is in the executing-tool state and
        joins the thread synchronously when the flag is observed as set.
      </notable>
    </worker-thread>

    <internal-tool-path order="3">
      If the tool name matches a registered internal tool, its handler function is
      called directly on the worker thread. The handler receives a talloc allocator
      context, the agent context, and the JSON arguments string. It returns a JSON
      string result.

      Internal tools currently registered are:
      - **fork**: creates a child agent with a given name and prompt.
      - **kill**: terminates a named agent and all of its descendants.
      - **send**: delivers a message to another agent.
      - **wait**: blocks until a message is received from one or more other agents.
    </internal-tool-path>

    <external-tool-path order="4">
      If the tool name matches a registered external tool, the tool executable is
      invoked as a child process.

      <uri-translation order="1">
        Before invocation, `ik://` URIs in the JSON arguments are translated to
        absolute filesystem paths. After the tool returns, any absolute filesystem
        paths in the result that fall under the state or data directories are
        translated back to `ik://` URIs. This translation is transparent to the
        tool process.
      </uri-translation>

      <process-creation order="2">
        The executable is launched as a child process with:
        - The JSON arguments supplied on standard input.
        - The calling agent's UUID set in the `IKIGAI_AGENT_ID` environment variable.
        - A new process group (the child becomes its own process group leader),
          enabling group-based interruption of any subprocesses it spawns.
        - Standard output and standard error captured via pipes.
      </process-creation>

      <timeout order="3">
        A 30-second alarm is set before reading from the pipes. If the tool has
        not produced all output within 30 seconds, the alarm fires.
      </timeout>

      <result-collection order="4">
        The parent reads all of the child's standard output and standard error via
        the pipes, then waits for the child to exit. If the child exits with a
        non-zero status, the standard error output (if any) is returned as an error.
        If the child produces no standard output, an error is returned. If the child
        produces standard output and exits cleanly, the output is the tool result.
      </result-collection>
    </external-tool-path>

    <result-wrapping order="5">
      All tool results — from both internal and external paths — are wrapped in a
      standard envelope before being added to the conversation. A successful result
      becomes `{"tool_success": true, "result": <output>}`. A failure becomes
      `{"tool_success": false, "error": "<message>", "error_code": "<code>"}`.

      Invalid JSON returned by an external tool is treated as a failure with the
      error code `INVALID_OUTPUT`.

      A lookup failure (the tool name is not in the registry) is treated as a
      failure with the error code `tool_not_found`.
    </result-wrapping>

    <conversation-update order="6">
      After the result is collected and wrapped, two messages are added to the
      conversation:

      1. A tool call message (assistant role) containing the original tool call
         block and any thinking blocks from the LLM response.
      2. A tool result message (tool role) containing the tool call identifier and
         the wrapped result.

      Both messages are persisted to the database and rendered to the scrollback.
    </conversation-update>

    <on-complete-hook order="7">
      If the tool registry entry has an on-complete hook, it is called on the main
      thread after the result has been harvested from the worker thread. The hook
      may modify REPL state (for example, the fork tool's hook transfers the newly
      created child agent into the REPL's agent array). The hook runs before the
      tool loop continuation.
    </on-complete-hook>

    <tool-loop-continuation order="8">
      After result processing, the agent automatically resubmits the conversation
      to the LLM. The LLM may respond with another tool call, continuing the loop,
      or with a text response that ends the loop. Each tool call iteration
      increments an iteration counter on the agent.

      <notable reason="no configured iteration limit">
        There is no hardcoded or configured maximum number of tool loop iterations.
        The loop continues as long as the LLM requests tool calls. The iteration
        counter is tracked but not checked against a limit.
      </notable>
    </tool-loop-continuation>

    <tool-discovery order="9">
      The tool registry is populated at startup and on `/refresh` by scanning three
      directories in order: the system libexec directory, the user tools directory
      (`~/.ikigai/tools/`), and the project tools directory (`.ikigai/tools/`
      relative to the current working directory). Tools found in later directories
      override tools with the same name found in earlier directories.

      An executable file qualifies as a tool if its name ends with `-tool`. The
      tool name is derived by stripping the `-tool` suffix and replacing hyphens
      with underscores in the remainder.

      Each candidate tool is invoked with the `--schema` flag and given 1 second to
      output its JSON schema on standard output. If the invocation times out,
      produces no output, or produces invalid JSON, the tool is skipped and not
      added to the registry.

      Internal tools are registered unconditionally after external tools are
      discovered.
    </tool-discovery>

  </behavior>

</specification>
