<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Tool Data JSON">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool data JSON builder constructs the structured JSON string stored in the
    data_json column of tool call and tool result database records.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Construction of tool call data records including thinking and redacted-thinking
      fields; construction of tool result data records including success derivation
      from the tool output string.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Database persistence">
      The caller is responsible for supplying the produced JSON string to the database
      layer. How and when the record is persisted is out of scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool call execution">
      The tool call and tool result inputs to the builder — identifiers, names,
      arguments, output strings, and thinking content — are produced by the tool
      execution pipeline. Their origin and meaning are out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Tool call record fields">
      <field name="tool_call_id" type="string" note="tool call identifier; always present" />
      <field name="tool_name" type="string" note="name of the invoked tool; always present" />
      <field name="tool_args" type="string" note="tool argument JSON as a string value (not a nested object); always present" />
      <field name="thinking" type="object" note="optional; present only when thinking text is non-null; contains 'text' (string, always present when object is included) and optionally 'signature' (string, present only when thinking signature is non-null)" />
      <field name="redacted_thinking" type="object" note="optional; present only when redacted thinking data is non-null; contains 'data' (string)" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Tool result record fields">
      <field name="tool_call_id" type="string" note="tool call identifier this result answers" />
      <field name="name" type="string" note="tool name" />
      <field name="output" type="string" note="the raw tool output string, stored verbatim" />
      <field name="success" type="boolean" note="derived by parsing the output string as JSON and extracting the 'tool_success' boolean field; defaults to false if the output is not valid JSON, if parsing fails, or if the field is absent" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <tool-call-data-construction order="1">
      A JSON object is built from the provided tool call record. The three required
      fields — tool call identifier, tool name, and tool arguments — are always
      present as string values.

      When thinking text is provided (non-null), a nested "thinking" object is appended
      to the root object. This nested object always contains the "text" field. If a
      thinking signature is also provided (non-null), a "signature" field is added to
      the nested object. If the signature is null, the "signature" field is omitted
      entirely.

      When redacted thinking data is provided (non-null), a separate nested
      "redacted_thinking" object is appended to the root object, containing a single
      "data" field with the redacted content.

      Neither "thinking" nor "redacted_thinking" appears in the output object when their
      respective inputs are null. Both may be present simultaneously, one, or neither,
      depending on what is supplied.

      The result is serialized to a compact JSON string, copied into a talloc-allocated
      buffer owned by the provided talloc context, and returned. Any failure to allocate
      memory causes an immediate panic.
    </tool-call-data-construction>

    <tool-result-data-construction order="2">
      A JSON object is built from the provided tool result inputs. The tool call
      identifier, tool name, and raw output string are always written as string fields.

      The "success" boolean is derived by parsing the raw output string as JSON and
      looking up a top-level "tool_success" boolean field. If parsing fails (the string
      is not valid JSON), if the parsed document has no "tool_success" field, or if any
      other error occurs during extraction, the success value defaults to false. The
      success value is appended to the object after the output field.

      The result is serialized, copied into a talloc-allocated buffer, and returned.
      Any allocation failure causes an immediate panic.

      <notable reason="success is derived from the output string, not passed directly">
        The caller does not supply a success flag. Success is always inferred by
        re-parsing the tool output. A tool output that is not valid JSON always produces
        success = false, regardless of the execution outcome.
      </notable>
    </tool-result-data-construction>

  </behavior>

</specification>
