<specification topic="Tool Argument Parsing">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool argument parser extracts typed values from JSON-encoded tool
    call argument strings.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Parsing a JSON object string and extracting either a string-typed or
      integer-typed field value by key name.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="JSON Library">
      The argument string is parsed into an in-memory document by a JSON
      library. This topic drives the parse and field lookup but does not
      implement the parsing.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Memory Management">
      Extracted string values are duplicated into a caller-provided allocation
      context. This topic initiates the allocation; ownership of the returned
      string belongs to that context.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="String Extraction Input">
      <field name="allocation context" type="pointer" note="talloc context; may be null for root allocation" />
      <field name="arguments JSON" type="text" note="null-terminated JSON string" />
      <field name="key" type="text" note="field name to extract" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="String Extraction Output">
      <field name="value" type="text" nullable="true" note="null on any failure" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="Integer Extraction Input">
      <field name="arguments JSON" type="text" note="null-terminated JSON string" />
      <field name="key" type="text" note="field name to extract" />
      <field name="output location" type="pointer" note="must be non-null" />
    </contract>
    <contract name="Integer Extraction Output">
      <field name="success flag" type="boolean" note="true if value was written, false on any failure" />
      <field name="value" type="integer" note="written to output location only on success; untouched on failure" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <string-extraction order="1">
      Extracting a string value from a JSON argument string follows these steps
      in order, returning null at the first failure:

      <null-guard order="1">
        If the argument string or the key is null, null is returned immediately
        without attempting any parsing.
      </null-guard>

      <json-parse order="2">
        The argument string is parsed as JSON. If parsing fails (malformed JSON,
        empty input, or other read error), null is returned.
      </json-parse>

      <root-type-check order="3">
        The root value of the parsed document must be a JSON object. If the root
        is absent or is any other type (array, string, number, boolean, or null),
        the document is freed and null is returned.
      </root-type-check>

      <key-lookup order="4">
        The requested key is looked up in the root object. If the key is not
        present, the document is freed and null is returned.
      </key-lookup>

      <type-check order="5">
        The value associated with the key must be a JSON string. If it is any
        other type (number, boolean, object, array, or null), the document is
        freed and null is returned.
      </type-check>

      <string-copy order="6">
        The string content is duplicated into the caller-provided allocation
        context. The JSON document is freed. The duplicated string is returned.

        If the allocation fails, the process terminates immediately (out-of-memory
        is treated as an unrecoverable condition). This path is the only
        unrecoverable failure mode.
      </string-copy>

      <notable reason="all failures indistinguishable">
        Null is returned for any failure — missing key, wrong type, invalid JSON,
        or null input — with no indication of which condition occurred.
      </notable>
    </string-extraction>

    <integer-extraction order="2">
      Extracting an integer value from a JSON argument string follows the same
      parse-and-lookup sequence, returning false at the first failure:

      <null-guard order="1">
        If the argument string, the key, or the output location is null, false
        is returned immediately without parsing.
      </null-guard>

      <json-parse order="2">
        The argument string is parsed as JSON. If parsing fails, false is
        returned.
      </json-parse>

      <root-type-check order="3">
        The root must be a JSON object. Any other root type causes the document
        to be freed and false to be returned.
      </root-type-check>

      <key-lookup order="4">
        The key is looked up in the root object. If absent, the document is
        freed and false is returned.
      </key-lookup>

      <type-check order="5">
        The value must be a JSON integer type. Floating-point numbers, strings,
        booleans, objects, arrays, and null all cause the document to be freed
        and false to be returned.
      </type-check>

      <integer-extraction order="6">
        The integer value is read as a signed 64-bit integer. The document is
        freed. The 64-bit value is cast to a platform-native integer and written
        to the output location. True is returned.

        <notable reason="silent truncation on overflow">
          The 64-bit value is cast to a native integer without range validation.
          If the JSON integer value exceeds the maximum or minimum value
          representable by a native integer, the stored result is silently
          truncated. No error is returned.
        </notable>
      </integer-extraction>

      <notable reason="all failures indistinguishable">
        False is returned for any failure — missing key, wrong type, invalid JSON,
        null parameters — with no indication of which condition occurred. The
        output location is not written on failure.
      </notable>
    </integer-extraction>

  </behavior>

</specification>
