<specification topic="Tool Registry">

  <topic-statement>
    The tool registry maintains an ordered, overrideable in-memory set of tool
    definitions available to agents.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Storing, looking up, adding, replacing, clearing, sorting, and enumerating
      tool definitions (both external and internal). Growth strategy of the backing
      store.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Tool Discovery">
      Tools are added to the registry by an external discovery process. How tools
      are found or how their schemas are obtained is outside this topic's scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="LLM Integration">
      This topic produces a JSON array of tool schemas for LLM consumption but does
      not interact with the LLM or serialize requests directly.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="External Tool Entry">
      <field name="name" type="string" note="registry key; derived from executable filename" />
      <field name="path" type="string" note="full filesystem path to the executable" />
      <field name="schema" type="parsed JSON document" note="the tool's schema as returned by --schema" />
      <field name="type" type="enum" note="always 'external' for externally discovered tools" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Internal Tool Entry">
      <field name="name" type="string" />
      <field name="path" type="null" note="always absent for internal tools" />
      <field name="schema" type="parsed JSON document" note="statically defined schema" />
      <field name="type" type="enum" note="always 'internal'" />
      <field name="handler" type="function reference" note="invoked directly when the tool is called" />
      <field name="completion hook" type="function reference" required="false" note="invoked after tool result is processed; null if not needed" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Registry">
      <field name="entries" type="dynamic array of tool entries" />
      <field name="count" type="integer" note="current number of entries" />
      <field name="capacity" type="integer" note="current allocated slots; starts at 16" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <creation order="1">
      A new registry is created with an initial capacity of 16 slots and zero entries.
      Both the registry structure and its backing array are zero-initialized.
    </creation>

    <lookup order="2">
      Looking up a tool by name performs a linear scan from the first entry to the
      last. The first entry whose name matches exactly (case-sensitive) is returned.
      If no entry matches, nothing is returned.

      <notable reason="linear-scan performance">
        Lookup is O(n) in the number of registered tools. There is no hash index or
        binary search despite the registry being kept sorted.
      </notable>
    </lookup>

    <adding-an-external-tool order="3">
      When an external tool is added, the registry first looks up whether a tool with
      the same name already exists.

      <replacement order="1">
        If an entry with the same name already exists, it is replaced in-place. The
        old name string, path string, and schema document are freed. New copies of the
        name and path strings are allocated under the registry. The new schema document's
        ownership is transferred to the registry. The entry's type is set to external,
        and its handler and completion-hook fields are cleared.
      </replacement>

      <growth order="2">
        If no existing entry matches and the registry is at capacity (count equals
        capacity), the capacity is doubled and the backing array is reallocated to
        accommodate the new size. The count then increments by one, and the new entry
        is written at the newly claimed slot.
      </growth>

      In both the replacement and growth cases, new copies of the name and path strings
      are allocated under the registry. Ownership of the schema document is transferred
      to the registry (not copied).
    </adding-an-external-tool>

    <adding-an-internal-tool order="4">
      Adding an internal tool follows the same replacement and growth logic as adding
      an external tool, with two differences:
      - The path field is not set (internal tools have no executable path).
      - The handler and completion-hook function references are stored in the entry.
      - The entry type is set to internal.

      <notable reason="path-is-null">
        Internal tool entries have a null path. Code that operates on tool entries
        must handle a null path field without crashing.
      </notable>
    </adding-an-internal-tool>

    <clearing order="5">
      Clearing the registry frees the name string, path string (if non-null), and
      schema document of every entry. The entry count is reset to zero. The backing
      array capacity is preserved — subsequent additions reuse the existing allocation.
    </clearing>

    <sorting order="6">
      If the registry has one or fewer entries, sorting is a no-op. Otherwise, all
      entries are sorted in-place in ascending alphabetical order by name
      (lexicographic, byte-value comparison). This is the order in which entries are
      enumerated and in which they appear in the JSON tools array.
    </sorting>

    <building-the-llm-tools-array order="7">
      A JSON array is produced containing a deep copy of every tool's schema root
      object, in the order the entries appear in the registry (typically alphabetical
      after sorting). The resulting array is a mutable JSON structure suitable for
      inclusion in an LLM request.
    </building-the-llm-tools-array>

  </behavior>

</specification>
