<specification topic="VCR HTTP">

  <topic-statement>
    The VCR HTTP layer intercepts HTTP client operations during test runs to deliver
    pre-recorded response fixtures instead of making live network requests.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      VCR state tracking per HTTP handle, write-callback interception for record and
      playback modes, chunk delivery during playback, synthetic completion signaling,
      HTTP status code injection, and passthrough behavior when VCR is inactive.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="HTTP Client Library">
      This layer wraps each HTTP client operation. When VCR is inactive, every
      operation is forwarded unchanged to the underlying library. When VCR is active,
      operations are intercepted as described.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="VCR Fixture System">
      This layer queries the fixture system for the active VCR mode, retrieves
      response status codes and chunks during playback, records captured chunks
      during recording, and checks whether more data remains. The fixture system
      itself is outside scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="VCR Handle State">
      <field name="handle" type="pointer" note="the HTTP easy handle this state belongs to" />
      <field name="write callback" type="function pointer" nullable="true" note="the caller's original write callback" />
      <field name="write context" type="pointer" nullable="true" note="the caller's original write context" />
      <field name="http status" type="integer" note="HTTP response status code from the fixture" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <inactive-mode order="1">
      When VCR is not active, all HTTP client calls are forwarded directly to the
      underlying library with their arguments unchanged. No state tracking occurs.
    </inactive-mode>

    <write-callback-interception order="2">
      When the caller registers a write callback on an HTTP handle, the VCR layer
      intercepts this registration.

      <record-mode order="1">
        In record mode, the caller's callback and context are saved in per-handle
        state. A wrapper callback is registered with the library in place of the
        caller's callback, and the per-handle state is registered as the context.
        When data arrives, the wrapper first forwards the chunk to the fixture system
        for recording, then calls the original callback with the original context.
        If the original callback is absent, the wrapper consumes the data silently
        and reports success.
      </record-mode>

      <playback-mode order="2">
        In playback mode, the caller's callback and context are saved in per-handle
        state. The registration call returns success without forwarding anything to
        the underlying library — no callback is registered with it.
      </playback-mode>
    </write-callback-interception>

    <handle-lifecycle order="3">
      When an HTTP handle is added to a multi-handle in playback mode, the HTTP
      response status code is retrieved from the fixture system and stored in the
      per-handle state. The message-delivered flag is reset to false for the new
      request. The underlying library call is still made.

      When an HTTP handle is cleaned up, any per-handle VCR state for that handle
      is removed before the underlying cleanup call is made.
    </handle-lifecycle>

    <playback-data-delivery order="4">
      When the HTTP multi-handle is polled for progress in playback mode, the next
      chunk is retrieved from the fixture system. If a chunk is available, it is
      delivered to the write callback of the first handle in the state list that
      has a registered callback. The running-handles count is set to 1 if more
      chunks remain, or 0 if the fixture is exhausted. If no chunk is available,
      running-handles is set to 0. Success is always returned.

      <notable reason="first-handle assumption">
        Chunk delivery targets only the first handle in the state list that has
        a registered callback. When multiple HTTP handles are active within one
        multi-handle, chunks for subsequent handles are not delivered. The
        implementation assumes at most one active handle per multi-handle.
      </notable>
    </playback-data-delivery>

    <playback-wait order="5">
      When the HTTP multi-handle wait operation is called in playback mode, it
      returns immediately with success. The number-of-file-descriptors-ready output
      is set to 1 to simulate activity. No actual waiting occurs.
    </playback-wait>

    <playback-completion-signaling order="6">
      When the message-read operation is called in playback mode:

      If the message has already been delivered for this request, zero messages
      are reported and nothing is returned.

      If the fixture has no more chunks and at least one handle exists in the state
      list, a completion message is synthesized. The message carries the type
      "done", the handle from the first entry in the state list, and a success
      result code. The delivered flag is set to true. Zero further messages are
      reported. The synthesized message is returned.

      If the fixture still has chunks remaining, zero messages are reported and
      nothing is returned.

      <notable reason="single synthesized message object">
        The synthesized completion message is written into a single static object.
        Concurrent or overlapping requests would overwrite this object.
      </notable>
    </playback-completion-signaling>

    <playback-status-retrieval order="7">
      When the caller queries the HTTP response code for a handle in playback mode,
      the status code stored in the per-handle state (populated when the handle was
      added to the multi-handle) is written to the output parameter and success is
      returned. All other info queries are forwarded to the underlying library.
    </playback-status-retrieval>

    <compile-time-scope order="8">
      <notable reason="debug-only compilation">
        This entire interception layer is only compiled in debug and test builds.
        In release builds, the HTTP wrappers are defined as direct passthrough
        functions inlined at the call site and the VCR layer does not exist.
      </notable>
    </compile-time-scope>

  </behavior>

</specification>
