<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Viewport">

  <topic-statement>
    The viewport tracks how far the user has scrolled up from the bottom of the
    document and derives the visible row range used to clip layer rendering on each
    frame.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      The scroll offset field, scroll commands and their step sizes, automatic
      scroll-to-bottom triggers, maximum offset calculation, viewport row derivation,
      and resize clamping.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer rendering">
      How the derived viewport row is used to clip and render individual layers is
      covered by the layer rendering specification.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input buffer position">
      The terminal row where the input buffer layer begins is calculated as part
      of viewport derivation and exposed to the cursor positioning code. The
      calculation is part of this specification; how the cursor uses that row
      is out of scope.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Scroll state (per agent)">
      <field name="scroll offset" type="non-negative integer" note="number of document rows the view has been scrolled up from the bottom; 0 means the bottom of the document is visible" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Derived viewport">
      <field name="scrollback start line" type="non-negative integer" note="index of the first scrollback logical line visible in the current frame" />
      <field name="scrollback line count" type="non-negative integer" note="number of scrollback logical lines visible" />
      <field name="input buffer start row" type="non-negative integer" note="terminal row (0-indexed from top) at which the input buffer layer begins; equals the terminal height when the input buffer is off-screen" />
      <field name="separator visible" type="boolean" note="true when the separator layer intersects the visible range" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <scroll-offset-semantics order="1">
      The scroll offset is a per-agent value representing how many document rows
      the view has been scrolled upward from the natural bottom position. An offset
      of zero means the bottom of the document is visible. An offset of N means
      the view has been scrolled up by N rows.

      The offset is stored on each agent independently, so switching between agents
      preserves each agent's scroll position.
    </scroll-offset-semantics>

    <scroll-commands order="2">
      Four scroll commands modify the offset:

      - **Scroll up** (mouse wheel up): advances the offset by 3 rows, clamped to
        the maximum offset.
      - **Scroll down** (mouse wheel down): reduces the offset by 3 rows, clamped
        to zero.
      - **Page up**: advances the offset by one full terminal height in rows,
        clamped to the maximum offset.
      - **Page down**: reduces the offset by one full terminal height in rows,
        clamped to zero.
    </scroll-commands>

    <auto-scroll-to-bottom order="3">
      The scroll offset is reset to zero (scroll to bottom) by any of the following:

      - Any character typed into the input buffer.
      - Backspace, forward delete, or any line-kill key pressed.
      - Any cursor movement key (arrow keys, line-start, line-end).
      - The input buffer submitted (Enter pressed).
      - The LLM begins producing a response.

      The effect is that any active user input or new LLM output snaps the view
      back to the bottom, ensuring the most recent content is always visible during
      interactive use.
    </auto-scroll-to-bottom>

    <maximum-offset-calculation order="4">
      The maximum valid offset is the document height minus the terminal height,
      clamped to zero when the document fits entirely within the terminal. The
      document height is the sum of the heights of all visible layers at the
      current terminal width.

      Before calculating the maximum, layout for the scrollback buffer and the
      input buffer is updated to the current terminal width if it has changed.
    </maximum-offset-calculation>

    <viewport-derivation order="5">
      On each frame, the visible row range is derived from the scroll offset and
      terminal height:

      - The last visible document row is the document height minus one minus the
        scroll offset.
      - The first visible document row is the last visible row plus one minus the
        terminal height.
      - These bounds define which layers and which rows within each layer are passed
        to the layer rendering pipeline.

      The derived values (first visible row, terminal height) are set on the layer
      stack before rendering, so that each layer's render function receives pre-
      clipped row parameters.

      <notable reason="scroll offset may exceed maximum after resize">
        When the terminal shrinks, the document height may decrease, making a
        previously valid offset larger than the new maximum. The offset is not
        corrected on the stored field; instead the clamped value is used when
        deriving the viewport on the next frame. The stored offset remains
        out-of-range until the next scroll command or auto-scroll event.
      </notable>
    </viewport-derivation>

    <input-buffer-position-derivation order="6">
      The terminal row where the input buffer begins is calculated by accumulating
      the heights of all visible layers above the input buffer (banner, scrollback,
      spinner, separator) and subtracting the first visible document row. If the
      resulting position is negative or falls entirely below the terminal height,
      the input buffer is considered off-screen and its start row is reported as
      the terminal height.

      If the input buffer starts above the viewport (the user has scrolled up so
      far that the top of the input buffer is above the first visible row), the
      start row is reported as zero (clamped to the top of the terminal).
    </input-buffer-position-derivation>

  </behavior>

</specification>
