<specification topic="Viewport Rendering">

  <topic-statement>
    The viewport rendering system calculates which portion of the document
    is visible given the current scroll offset and renders a complete terminal
    frame using the layer cake.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Document height calculation, viewport window computation, scrollback
      logical-to-physical row mapping, input buffer screen position
      calculation, layer cake viewport configuration, framebuffer construction
      with ANSI cursor control, cursor position calculation, framebuffer
      storage, and render timing.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Layer Cake">
      Individual layer visibility checks, height queries, and render calls
      are performed by the layer cake. The viewport system sets the viewport
      row and height on the layer cake and delegates rendering to it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Scrollback">
      Physical-to-logical row mapping is computed by the scrollback system.
      Layout synchronization is requested before any calculations.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Terminal">
      The framebuffer is written atomically to the terminal file descriptor.
      In headless mode (file descriptor is -1), write errors are suppressed.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Viewport State">
      <field name="scrollback_start_line" type="numeric"
             note="first logical scrollback line visible" />
      <field name="scrollback_lines_count" type="numeric"
             note="number of logical scrollback lines to render" />
      <field name="input_buffer_start_row" type="numeric"
             note="terminal row where input buffer begins; equals terminal_rows if off-screen" />
      <field name="separator_visible" type="boolean" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Document Layer Order (top to bottom)">
      <field name="1. Banner" type="0 or 6 rows"
             note="6 rows when banner_visible is true" />
      <field name="2. Scrollback" type="sum of physical lines" />
      <field name="3. Spinner" type="0 or 1 row"
             note="1 row when spinner_state.visible is true" />
      <field name="4. Separator" type="1 row (always)" />
      <field name="5. Input buffer" type="0, 1, or more rows"
             note="0 when hidden; 1 minimum when visible and empty" />
      <field name="6. Completion list" type="0 or N rows"
             note="present only when completion is active" />
      <field name="7. Status" type="0 or 2 rows"
             note="2 rows when status_visible is true" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <document-height-calculation order="1">
      The total document height in rows is the sum of each layer's row count
      according to the ordering in the data contract above. The input buffer
      contributes either zero rows (when hidden), one row (when visible and
      empty), or the actual physical line count of its text. Scrollback
      contributes its total physical lines (accounting for line wrapping at
      the current terminal width).
    </document-height-calculation>

    <viewport-window-computation order="2">
      Input buffer and scrollback layouts are synchronized to the current
      terminal width before any computation.

      <entire-document-fits order="1">
        If the document height is less than or equal to the terminal height,
        the entire document is visible: the first visible row is 0 and the
        last visible row is document_height minus 1.
      </entire-document-fits>

      <document-overflows order="2">
        If the document height exceeds the terminal height:
        - The maximum scroll offset is document_height minus terminal_height.
        - The viewport offset is clamped to the maximum if it exceeds it.
        - The last visible row is document_height minus 1 minus the (clamped)
          offset.
        - The first visible row is last_visible_row plus 1 minus
          terminal_height.

        A viewport offset of zero shows the bottom of the document (most
        recent content). Increasing the offset scrolls toward the top.
      </document-overflows>
    </viewport-window-computation>

    <scrollback-visibility-mapping order="3">
      The document row where the scrollback region begins is determined from
      the banner height. The separator is at banner_rows plus total scrollback
      physical rows plus spinner rows.

      If the first visible row is at or after the separator row, no scrollback
      is visible: scrollback_start_line and scrollback_lines_count are both
      zero.

      Otherwise, the physical row offset within the scrollback region at the
      first visible document row is computed and converted to a logical line
      index by the scrollback system. The number of logical lines that fit in
      the visible range is counted from that starting index.
    </scrollback-visibility-mapping>

    <input-buffer-screen-position order="4">
      The input buffer begins one row after the separator in the document.

      - If the input buffer start is within the visible range, its screen row
        is its document row minus the first visible document row.
      - If the input buffer start is before the first visible row (scrolled
        partially out of view), its screen row is zero.
      - If the input buffer start is after the last visible row (scrolled
        completely out of view), its screen row is set to terminal_height
        (a sentinel value indicating off-screen).
    </input-buffer-screen-position>

    <separator-visibility order="5">
      The separator is visible if its document row falls within the range
      [first_visible_row, last_visible_row] inclusive.
    </separator-visibility>

    <state-based-visibility-overrides order="6">
      Before rendering, the current agent's state is read atomically and
      layer visibility flags are set:

      - If the agent is dead: both the spinner and input buffer are hidden.
      - If the agent is in WAITING_FOR_LLM or EXECUTING_TOOL state: the
        spinner is shown and the input buffer is hidden.
      - If the agent is idle: the spinner is hidden and the input buffer
        visibility follows whether its screen position is on-screen.

      These visibility values are written back to the agent's state fields,
      causing them to take effect immediately in the layer cake render.
    </state-based-visibility-overrides>

    <layer-cake-rendering order="7">
      The layer cake's viewport row is set to the first visible document row
      and viewport height is set to the terminal height. The layer cake then
      renders by iterating through all layers in order:
      - Invisible layers are skipped.
      - Each visible layer's height is computed.
      - Only the portion of the layer overlapping the viewport window is
        rendered; start_row and row_count clip the layer to the visible range.
      - Rendering stops once past the viewport.

      All rendered output is accumulated in an output buffer initialized to
      4 KB.
    </layer-cake-rendering>

    <trailing-crlf-removal order="8">
      If the document fills or overflows the terminal height, and the output
      buffer ends with a carriage-return followed by a newline, those two
      bytes are removed. This prevents the terminal from auto-scrolling when
      the last rendered row is at the bottom of the screen.
    </trailing-crlf-removal>

    <cursor-position-calculation order="9">
      If the input buffer is visible and contains text, the cursor's screen
      coordinates are computed from the cursor byte offset within the text,
      the terminal width, and the input buffer's screen row from the viewport
      calculation. The resulting screen row and column are stored on the REPL
      context.

      If the input buffer is visible but empty, the cursor is placed at the
      first column of the input buffer's screen row.

      If the input buffer is hidden, the cursor coordinates are left at zero.
    </cursor-position-calculation>

    <framebuffer-construction order="10">
      A framebuffer is built by concatenating:
      1. Hide cursor escape sequence
      2. Home cursor escape sequence (move to row 1, column 1)
      3. The rendered layer cake output
      4. Erase-to-end-of-screen sequence
      5. Either show-cursor or hide-cursor sequence depending on whether the
         input buffer is visible
      6. If input buffer is visible: cursor positioning escape sequence for
         the computed row and column

      The complete framebuffer is written to the terminal file descriptor in
      a single write call. Write errors are returned unless the file
      descriptor is -1 (headless mode).
    </framebuffer-construction>

    <framebuffer-storage order="11">
      The previous framebuffer is freed and replaced with the newly rendered
      one. The framebuffer length and cursor position are updated on the REPL
      context. These values are made available to the control socket for the
      read_framebuffer command.
    </framebuffer-storage>

    <render-timing order="12">
      If a render-start timestamp was recorded (set when terminal input was
      received), the elapsed time from that timestamp to the current
      CLOCK_MONOTONIC time is computed in microseconds and stored on the REPL
      context. The start timestamp is cleared after each measurement.
    </render-timing>

    <legacy-rendering-fallback order="13">
      If the current agent has no layer cake (used in test mode), a combined
      legacy renderer is invoked directly with the scrollback and viewport
      parameters, bypassing the layer cake entirely.
    </legacy-rendering-fallback>

    <debug-info-recording order="14">
      The viewport offset, first visible document row, viewport height, and
      document height are stored on the REPL context for display by the debug
      viewport layer.
    </debug-info-recording>

  </behavior>

</specification>
