<specification topic="Viewport Scroll Actions">

  <topic-statement>
    The viewport scroll action system adjusts the scrollback viewport offset
    in response to page, mouse scroll, and arrow input events, and drives
    completion and cursor navigation when the viewport is at the bottom.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Page-up and page-down actions, scroll-up and scroll-down actions
      (mouse wheel at 3 lines per event), arrow-up and arrow-down contextual
      routing, maximum offset calculation, and the scroll detector state
      machine that distinguishes mouse-wheel bursts from keyboard arrow
      presses.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Completion System">
      When the viewport is at the bottom and a completion is active, arrow
      keys delegate to the completion navigation system. Completion state
      management is handled externally.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Input Buffer">
      When the viewport is at the bottom and no completion is active, arrow
      keys delegate to input buffer cursor movement. Cursor tracking is
      handled externally.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Viewport Offset Semantics">
      <field name="offset = 0" type="numeric"
             note="bottom of document visible (most recent content)" />
      <field name="offset = N" type="numeric"
             note="scrolled N rows upward from the bottom" />
      <field name="offset = max" type="numeric"
             note="top of document visible; max = document_height - terminal_height (or 0 if fits)" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <maximum-offset-calculation order="1">
      Before any scroll action that increases the offset, the maximum
      allowable offset is calculated. Input buffer and scrollback layouts
      are synchronized to the current terminal width. The document height
      is computed as the sum of all layer heights. If the document fits
      within the terminal, the maximum offset is zero. Otherwise it is
      document_height minus terminal_height.
    </maximum-offset-calculation>

    <page-up order="2">
      One full terminal height (in rows) is added to the current viewport
      offset. If the result exceeds the maximum offset, it is clamped to
      the maximum. The viewport now shows content one full screen height
      higher.
    </page-up>

    <page-down order="3">
      One full terminal height is subtracted from the current viewport
      offset. If the offset is already less than one terminal height, the
      offset is set to zero. The viewport moves one full screen height
      toward the bottom.
    </page-down>

    <scroll-up order="4">
      Three rows are added to the current viewport offset. If the result
      exceeds the maximum offset, it is clamped to the maximum. This
      corresponds to one mouse wheel scroll event upward.
    </scroll-up>

    <scroll-down order="5">
      Three rows are subtracted from the current viewport offset. If the
      offset is less than three, it is set to zero. This corresponds to
      one mouse wheel scroll event downward.
    </scroll-down>

    <arrow-up order="6">
      The action is routed based on the current viewport state:

      - If the viewport offset is greater than zero (the user has scrolled
        up from the bottom): scroll-up is performed (adds 3 rows to offset).
      - If the viewport is at the bottom and a completion is active:
        the completion moves to the previous candidate.
      - Otherwise: the input buffer cursor moves up one row.
    </arrow-up>

    <arrow-down order="7">
      The action is routed based on the current viewport state:

      - If the viewport offset is greater than zero: scroll-down is performed
        (subtracts 3 rows from offset, clamping to zero).
      - If the viewport is at the bottom and a completion is active:
        the completion moves to the next candidate.
      - Otherwise: the input buffer cursor moves down one row.
    </arrow-down>

    <scroll-detection order="8">
      Arrow-up and arrow-down events are intercepted before dispatch and
      passed through a state machine that detects mouse-wheel scroll bursts.
      The state machine uses a 5-millisecond threshold between consecutive
      arrow events:

      <waiting-state order="1">
        The first arrow event starts a timer. If a second arrow event in
        the same direction arrives within 5 milliseconds, the state machine
        enters the absorbing state and emits a scroll event. If 5 milliseconds
        elapse without a second event, the buffered arrow is released as a
        keyboard arrow action.
      </waiting-state>

      <absorbing-state order="2">
        Additional arrow events within 5 milliseconds of the last absorbed
        event are silently consumed (the scroll was already emitted). The
        state machine returns to idle after 5 milliseconds without an event.
      </absorbing-state>

      <non-arrow-flush order="3">
        When any non-arrow, non-unknown event arrives, any buffered pending
        arrow from the waiting state is flushed and processed as a keyboard
        arrow action before the new event is handled.
      </non-arrow-flush>

      <select-timeout-flush order="4">
        When the select() call times out, the scroll detector's timeout check
        may release a buffered pending arrow and trigger the corresponding
        viewport action.
      </select-timeout-flush>
    </scroll-detection>

  </behavior>

</specification>
