<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification topic="Wait Tool Handler">

  <topic-statement>
    The wait tool handler translates a JSON tool invocation from the LLM into
    a blocking wait operation and serializes the result back into a JSON
    envelope for the tool call infrastructure.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Argument parsing and validation for the wait tool, dispatch to the
      appropriate wait mode based on argument presence, and construction of
      the JSON result object from the wait result structure.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Wait Core Logic">
      The blocking poll loop, PostgreSQL notification registration, mailbox
      queries, fan-in state tracking, and interrupt handling are implemented
      by the wait synchronization subsystem. This topic invokes that subsystem
      but does not implement it.
      <shared topic="Wait Synchronization" />
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Tool Result Wrapping">
      The raw JSON result produced here is wrapped in a standard tool envelope
      before being returned to the tool execution infrastructure.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>

    <contract name="Tool Arguments">
      <field name="timeout" type="number" note="required; maximum seconds to wait; 0 means non-blocking instant check" />
      <field name="from_agents" type="array of string" note="optional; if present and is an array, enables fan-in mode; each element must be a string UUID" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Next-Message Success Result">
      <field name="from" type="string" note="present only when a message was received; UUID of the sending agent" />
      <field name="message" type="string" note="present only when a message was received; the message body" />
      <field name="status" type="string" note="present only when no message was received; the value 'timeout'" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Fan-in Success Result">
      <field name="results" type="array of objects" note="one object per target agent, in the order targets were specified" />
      <field name="results[].agent_uuid" type="string" note="UUID of the target agent" />
      <field name="results[].agent_name" type="string" note="display name of the target agent" />
      <field name="results[].status" type="string" note="one of: running, received, idle, dead" />
      <field name="results[].message" type="string" note="present only when status is 'received'; the message body" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Error Result">
      <field name="error" type="text" note="human-readable description" />
      <field name="code" type="text" note="one of: PARSE_ERROR, INVALID_ARG" />
    </contract>

  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <argument-parsing order="1">
      The JSON argument string is parsed. If parsing fails, the handler returns
      an error with code PARSE_ERROR and does not proceed.

      The parsed object must contain a "timeout" field whose value is any
      numeric type. If the field is absent or not a number, the handler returns
      an error with code INVALID_ARG. The timeout value is truncated to a
      signed 32-bit integer.

      The presence of a "from_agents" field is then examined. Fan-in mode is
      activated if and only if the field is present in the parsed object and
      its value is a JSON array. A missing field or a field with a non-array
      value (including null) selects next-message mode. An empty array is
      treated as a valid fan-in invocation with zero targets.

      <notable reason="from_agents type is not validated element-by-element before dispatch">
        Each element of the "from_agents" array is validated to be a string
        during the element-copying loop. If a non-string element is encountered,
        the handler returns an error with code INVALID_ARG at that point, but
        elements already copied into the target array before the failing element
        are left allocated.
      </notable>
    </argument-parsing>

    <next-message-dispatch order="2">
      When fan-in mode is not selected, the handler delegates to the
      next-message wait operation, passing the calling agent's identifier,
      the session identifier, the timeout, and the agent's interrupt flag.

      The wait runs synchronously on the calling thread (which is the tool
      execution background thread). The main REPL thread is not involved
      until the wait completes.
    </next-message-dispatch>

    <fan-in-dispatch order="3">
      When fan-in mode is selected, all UUIDs from the "from_agents" array
      are copied into a fresh array. The handler then delegates to the fan-in
      wait operation, passing the calling agent's identifier, the session
      identifier, the timeout, the UUID array, the count of targets, and the
      agent's interrupt flag.

      The wait runs synchronously on the calling thread.
    </fan-in-dispatch>

    <result-serialization order="4">
      After the wait operation returns, the handler constructs a JSON result
      object from the wait result structure:

      For next-message mode:
      - If a message was received (indicated by a non-null sender identifier),
        the result object contains a "from" field with the sender UUID and a
        "message" field with the message body.
      - If no message was received (timeout or interrupt), the result object
        contains a "status" field with the value "timeout".

      <notable reason="interrupt is reported as timeout">
        When the wait is interrupted (e.g., due to a user abort), the result
        object is constructed the same way as a timeout: a "status" field with
        value "timeout". The caller cannot distinguish an interrupt from a
        genuine timeout expiration through the JSON result alone.
      </notable>

      For fan-in mode:
      - A "results" array is constructed with one object per entry in the
        wait result. Each object contains "agent_uuid", "agent_name", and
        "status" fields. A "message" field is added only when the entry's
        message is non-null.

      The JSON result is wrapped in a success envelope and returned.
    </result-serialization>

  </behavior>

</specification>
