<specification topic="Wait Synchronization">

  <topic-statement>
    The wait synchronization system blocks the calling agent until a message
    arrives from any sender or until a specified set of target agents each
    reach a terminal state.
  </topic-statement>

  <scope>
    <in-scope>
      Two wait modes (next-message and fan-in), PostgreSQL LISTEN/NOTIFY setup
      and teardown, poll loop with select and timeout, interrupted-turn detection,
      fan-in state tracking per target agent, and result rendering.
    </in-scope>

    <boundary name="Mailbox">
      Whether a message exists in the mailbox, and reading or deleting that
      message, is delegated to the mail storage layer. This topic queries the
      mailbox but does not implement it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Agent State">
      Whether a target agent is idle or dead is read from the agent record.
      How that record is updated is outside this scope.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="REPL Threading">
      How the REPL detects that a background tool thread has completed and
      invokes the completion callback is handled by the REPL event loop.
      This topic participates in that protocol but does not implement it.
    </boundary>

    <boundary name="Scrollback Rendering">
      How the formatted result strings are displayed to the user is handled
      by the event rendering layer.
    </boundary>
  </scope>

  <data-contracts>
    <contract name="Next-Message Result">
      <field name="from identifier" type="string" nullable="true" note="UUID of the agent that sent the message; null on timeout or error" />
      <field name="message" type="string" note="message body, or a status string such as 'Timeout' or 'Interrupted'" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Fan-in Entry">
      <field name="agent identifier" type="string" note="UUID of the target agent" />
      <field name="agent name" type="string" note="display name of the target agent; 'undefined' if lookup failed" />
      <field name="status" type="string" note="one of: running, received, idle, dead" />
      <field name="message" type="string" nullable="true" note="message body; only present when status is 'received'" />
    </contract>

    <contract name="Fan-in Result">
      <field name="entries" type="array of Fan-in Entry" note="one entry per target agent, in the order targets were specified" />
    </contract>
  </data-contracts>

  <behavior>

    <invocation order="1">
      The wait command is invoked with an optional timeout (in seconds) and an
      optional list of target agent identifiers. When no targets are listed,
      next-message mode is used. When one or more targets are listed, fan-in
      mode is used. Execution is dispatched to a background thread so the REPL
      remains responsive. The calling agent's state transitions to executing-tool
      for the duration of the wait.
    </invocation>

    <next-message-mode order="2">
      In next-message mode, the system waits for any message sent to the calling
      agent's mailbox from any sender.

      <setup order="1">
        A PostgreSQL notification channel is registered for the calling agent.
        The mailbox is checked immediately before entering the poll loop. If a
        message is already present, it is consumed and the wait completes without
        entering the loop.
      </setup>

      <poll-loop order="2">
        The poll loop repeats until a message is received, the timeout expires,
        or the interrupted flag is set.

        Each iteration:
        1. The interrupted flag is checked. If true, the wait ends with the text
           "Interrupted" as the result message and a null sender.
        2. Elapsed time is calculated using a monotonic clock. If the timeout
           has expired, the wait ends with the text "Timeout" as the result
           message and a null sender.
        3. A file descriptor watch is set on the database connection socket with
           a timeout capped at 50 milliseconds. If the watch returns a socket
           error other than an interrupted system call, the loop exits with the
           result message set to "Select failed" and the sender set to null.
           An interrupted system call causes the iteration to restart.
        4. Pending database notifications are consumed from the connection.
        5. The mailbox is checked. If a message is present, it is consumed, the
           sender identifier and message body are recorded, and the loop exits.
           The consumed message is then deleted from the mailbox; if the deletion
           fails, the failure is silently ignored and the message remains in the
           inbox.

        <notable reason="mailbox is polled regardless of notification">
          The mailbox is checked after every socket event and after every 50
          millisecond poll interval expiration, whether or not a notification
          was received. The notification is used only to wake the socket watch
          early; the actual message is always retrieved by querying the mailbox.
        </notable>

        <notable reason="notification payload is discarded">
          The content of any PostgreSQL notification payload is stored in a local
          context structure but never read or acted upon. Only the fact that the
          socket became readable triggers the mailbox check.
        </notable>
      </poll-loop>

      <teardown order="3">
        The notification channel registration is cancelled before the function
        returns, regardless of the exit reason.
      </teardown>
    </next-message-mode>

    <fan-in-mode order="3">
      In fan-in mode, the system waits until each target agent has either sent
      a message to the calling agent's mailbox, entered an idle state, or died.

      <setup order="1">
        A notification channel is registered for the calling agent. A notification
        channel is also registered for each target agent. The result entries array
        is initialized with one entry per target agent, all in status "running"
        and with name "undefined". A batch lookup of target agent display names
        is attempted; if successful, the "undefined" placeholders are replaced.
        If the name lookup fails for any reason, the "undefined" values are
        retained without error. When the batch lookup succeeds but an individual
        entry's name is null, the "undefined" placeholder for that target is also
        retained.

        <notable reason="target channel LISTEN errors silently ignored">
          The notification channel registration for each target agent is performed
          without checking the result. If a LISTEN fails for one or more targets,
          the system continues with those channels unregistered. Notifications
          from those targets will never wake the socket watch; the wait will rely
          on the 50-millisecond polling interval to detect their state changes.
          All channels, including those that were never successfully registered,
          are submitted to UNLISTEN on teardown.
        </notable>
      </setup>

      <poll-loop order="2">
        The poll loop repeats until all targets are resolved, the timeout expires,
        or the interrupted flag is set.

        Each iteration:
        1. The interrupted flag is checked. If true, the loop exits immediately.
           Unresolved targets remain in "running" status.
        2. Elapsed time is calculated. If the timeout has expired, the loop exits.
           Unresolved targets remain in "running" status.
        3. Each target's entry is updated:
           - If the entry's status is already not "running", it is skipped (the
             check is idempotent once resolved).
           - The calling agent's mailbox is checked for a message from this
             specific target. If found, the message is consumed, the entry status
             is set to "received", and the message body is stored. The consumed
             message is then deleted; if the deletion fails, the failure is
             silently ignored.
           - If no message was found, the target agent's record is retrieved. If
             the agent's status is "dead", the entry status is set to "dead". If
             the agent is idle, the entry status is set to "idle".
        4. If all entries have a status other than "running", the loop exits.
        5. A file descriptor watch is set on the database connection socket with
           a timeout capped at 50 milliseconds. If the watch returns a socket
           error other than an interrupted system call, the loop exits with entries
           in their current state and no result message set. An interrupted system
           call causes the iteration to restart.
        6. Pending database notifications are consumed.

        <notable reason="50ms timeout minimum">
          Because the socket watch is capped at 50 milliseconds, a timeout value
          shorter than 50 milliseconds may not be honored precisely. The first
          iteration will block for up to 50 milliseconds before recalculating
          elapsed time.
        </notable>
      </poll-loop>

      <teardown order="3">
        The notification channel registrations for the calling agent and all
        target agents are cancelled before the function returns.
      </teardown>
    </fan-in-mode>

    <result-rendering order="4">
      After the background thread completes, the completion callback renders
      the result to the calling agent's scrollback.

      For next-message mode: the sender identifier and message body are rendered
      as a single entry.

      For fan-in mode: a "Fan-in results:" header is rendered, followed by one
      line per target entry showing the agent identifier, status, and — when the
      status is "received" — the message body.
    </result-rendering>

    <database-connection-failure order="5">
      If the database socket file descriptor is unavailable after notification
      channel registration, the notification registration is cancelled and the
      wait completes immediately. For next-message mode, the result message is
      set to "Database connection error" with a null sender. For fan-in mode,
      all notification channels are cancelled and the function returns with
      entries in their initialized state.

      <notable reason="error is not surfaced as a command error">
        Database connection failure causes the wait to complete with a sentinel
        message rather than returning an error result to the REPL. The user sees
        a result entry rather than an error notification.
      </notable>
    </database-connection-failure>

  </behavior>

  <state-transitions>
    <transition trigger="wait command invoked">
      Calling agent enters executing-tool state
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="background thread completes">
      Calling agent returns to idle state (via REPL completion callback)
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="target sends message (fan-in)">
      Target entry status transitions from "running" to "received"
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="target agent becomes idle (fan-in)">
      Target entry status transitions from "running" to "idle"
    </transition>
    <transition trigger="target agent dies (fan-in)">
      Target entry status transitions from "running" to "dead"
    </transition>
  </state-transitions>

</specification>
